<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A discourse concerning the nature of idolatry in which a late author's true and onely notion of idolatry is considered and confuted.</title>
            <author>Wake, William, 1657-1737.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1688</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 210 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 57 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A66169</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W239</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R13002</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13312843</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13312843</idno>
            <idno type="VID">99012</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A66169)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 99012)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 442:1)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A discourse concerning the nature of idolatry in which a late author's true and onely notion of idolatry is considered and confuted.</title>
                  <author>Wake, William, 1657-1737.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], xvi, 91, [4] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for William Rogers ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1688.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"By the Archbishop of Wake in reply to Bishop Parker's Reasons for abrogating the test"--BM.</note>
                  <note>Advertisement ([4] p.) at end.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Cambridge University Library.</note>
                  <note>Marginal notes.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Parker, Samuel, 1640-1688. --  Reasons for abrogating the test imposed upon all members of Parliament.</term>
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature.</term>
               <term>Idols and images --  Worship.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <pb facs="tcp:99012:1"/>
            <p>Imprimatur Liber cui Titulus, <hi>A Diſcourſe concerning the Nature of Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Ex Aedib.</hi> Lambeth, <date>
                     <hi>Febr.</hi> 18. 1687.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Guil. Needham,</hi> R. R. in Chriſto I. ac D.D. <hi>Wilhelmo</hi> Archiepiſc. <hi>Cant.</hi> à Sacr. Domeſt.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:99012:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A DISCOURSE Concerning the <hi>Nature of Idolatry:</hi> In which a Late Author's True and Onely NOTION of IDOLATRY IS Conſidered and Confuted.</p>
            <q>
               <hi>Si inter ſolos Pontificios verſarer,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>i. e.</hi> If I converſed with none but Papiſts, and conſidered their Religion corrupted with Old Wives Tales, and were altogether deſtitute of a Rule of Faith, by which to diſcern the vaſt difference between the Chriſtian Religion, and the Trifles of Popery; and laſtly, if no Hiſtories were extant, ſhewing how theſe Dotages crept in: If it were thus, I ſay, then I frankly confeſs, that I ſhould very much ſuſpect the Chriſtian Religion, nay I ſhould utterly reject it as fooliſh and mean, and beneath the eſteem of old Goſſips; nor ſhould I leſs hate the name of Chriſtianity, than I do that of Popery. <bibl>
                  <hi>Tentam. Phyſic. Theol. Auth. Samuele Parkero,</hi> P. 4.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>William Rogers,</hi> at the <hi>Sun</hi> over againſt St. <hi>Dunſtan</hi>'s Church in <hi>Fleet-ſtreet.</hi> MDCLXXXVIII.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:99012:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb n="i" facs="tcp:99012:2"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE.</head>
            <p>WEre we to judge of the <hi>Merits</hi> of a <hi>Book</hi> meerly by the <hi>good Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion</hi> which the <hi>Author</hi> ſeems to have of it, we might reaſonab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly believe, that the <hi>Diſcourſe</hi> concerning the <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture</hi> of <hi>Idolatry,</hi> which I am about to conſider, was not onely ſet forth in Defence of a truly <hi>Infallible Church,</hi> but that the Author of it thought himſelf delivering nothing but <hi>Oracles</hi> all the while he was compoſing of it.</p>
            <p>If his <hi>Reaſons</hi> had born proportion to the nature of his Attempt, we ſhould eaſily have forgiven him, or rather we ſhould have thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him, no leſs than the Gentlemen of the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> Communion would have done in ſuch a caſe. He does indeed Treat men with Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt, whom all the World knows to be above his Contempt, nor can I believe him to be ſo
<pb n="ii" facs="tcp:99012:3"/>ſingular as not to know it himſelf; but yet had he <hi>reaſoned</hi> well, we had yielded to him: for an over-bearing Spirit in an Adverſary, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther makes us to ſubmit to a bad Argument, nor to reſiſt a good one.</p>
            <p>It ſeemed ſomething ſtrange, that that Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor ſhould think to Trample upon us now, for pretending that the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> has de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fined <hi>Tranſubſtantiation</hi> as 'tis underſtood by us, and that ſhe has eſtabliſhed an Idolatrous Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip in her Communion: For not only the greateſt Perſons of the Reformed Religion have brought this Charge againſt her, but to the truth of it himſelf has ſubſcribed in his time. But it was much more amazing to find ſo new a Confidence ſupported by Arguments ſo weak, that 'tis not without reaſon that ſome of the <hi>Roman</hi> Communion are ſaid to complain, That they have been Betrayed, rather than Defend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by him.</p>
            <p>How unſucceſsfully he has managed his De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign of Expounding <hi>Tranſubſtantiation,</hi> has been ſhewn in a late Diſcourſe proving <hi>Tranſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiation</hi> to be the <hi>peculiar</hi> Doctrine of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and in the <hi>Preface</hi> to the <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amination</hi> of the New Articles of the <hi>Roman</hi>
               <pb n="iii" facs="tcp:99012:3"/>Creed by <hi>Catholick Tradition.</hi> If I make it appear that he has miſcarried as much in the point of <hi>Idolatry,</hi> his <hi>Theological</hi> part will then be conſidered; and for the reſt, we do not by any means preſume to meddle with it.</p>
            <p>As for the Subject which I have undertaken, one would have thought, that a man who re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved to deſpiſe all that had ever written upon it, and not according to his <hi>Opinion,</hi> ſhould have taken care, if not to produce ſomething <hi>that could not be Anſwer'd,</hi> yet at leaſt not to offer any thing that had <hi>been already Confuted.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But on the contrary, this Author, after all this noiſe, has for the moſt part been only an humble Tranſcriber of the Old <hi>Exploded Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences;</hi> and which I may truly ſay were much more <hi>ſtrongly,</hi> as well as more <hi>modeſtly</hi> urged by Dr. <hi>Godden</hi> againſt his learned Adverſary. And when I conſider how much more roughly this Author uſes him, than that Doctor did, I am apt to think it might in ſome meaſure proceed from the ſence he had that Dr. <hi>St.</hi> in diſcover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the <hi>Sophiſtry</hi> of his Old Antagoniſt, had be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore-hand confuted whatever this New one could find out again to revive the Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſie.</p>
            <pb n="iv" facs="tcp:99012:4"/>
            <p>And for this I ſhall leave the following <hi>Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe</hi> to be my Evidence; and of which I ſhall ſay no more here, than that in his own phraſe: <q>I have delivered my Judgment,
<note place="margin">Pag. 135.</note> as I will an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer for my <hi>Integrity</hi> to <hi>God</hi> and the <hi>World.</hi>
               </q> But now there is another thing, which I ought not in this place to paſs by. It has been inſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuated by this not <hi>Reaſoner,</hi> as no ſmall Crime in us, that we charge the <hi>Church of Rome</hi> with Idolatry,
<note place="margin">Pag. 72.</note> 
               <q>Not only (ſays he) becauſe of the <hi>falſeneſs</hi> of the <hi>Calumny,</hi> but the barbarous <hi>conſequence</hi> that may follow upon it, to incite and warrant the <hi>Rabble,</hi> whenever Opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity favours, to deſtroy the <hi>Roman Catholics</hi> and their <hi>Images,</hi> as the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> were com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded to deſtroy the <hi>Canaanites</hi> and their <hi>Idols.</hi> And in the next Page he tells us, That this Charge of <hi>Idolatry</hi> has ever been ſet up as the <hi>Standard</hi> againſt Monarchy.</q>
               <note place="margin">73.74.</note>
            </p>
            <p>There are many more Paſſages of the like kind, in which he exerciſes his <hi>Gift</hi> of Elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence: for I dare ſay he never learnt it, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs he has in his time ſtudied to imitate a Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſt; for I know not what other Original he could propound to himſelf. This ſtile is the fitteſt in the World to his purpoſe, and will
<pb n="v" facs="tcp:99012:4"/>perhaps be a Copy for the future to them that intend to ſpeak neither according to <hi>Charity</hi> nor <hi>Truth;</hi> which are ever beſt heard in a Calm.</p>
            <p>But however, if this too were for the <hi>decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration</hi> of his <hi>Judgment,</hi> we will no more com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain of the <hi>Violence</hi> of his <hi>Expreſſions,</hi> than we do of the <hi>Force</hi> of his <hi>Arguments;</hi> only I would beg leave to ſay, that he ſhould have been ſure he could <hi>diſcharge</hi> the <hi>Church of Rome</hi> of that <hi>Guilt,</hi> before he had fix'd a Mark of <hi>Calumny</hi> upon the whole Body of the <hi>Reform'd,</hi> who accuſe them of it; leſt when men examine his <hi>Proofs,</hi> and find them defective, they be tempted to retort the <hi>Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure,</hi> eſpecially conſidering with what Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom and Violence he has been pleaſed to lay it upon us.</p>
            <p>But now for his great fear that this ſhould incite the <hi>Rabble</hi> to any <hi>Violence</hi> againſt thoſe of the other Communion, I dare venture to ſay, there is not the leaſt reaſon to be at all apprehenſive of it. He knows very well how free the <hi>Chriſtians</hi> of the firſt three <hi>Centuries</hi> were in laying the very ſame <hi>Charge</hi> againſt the <hi>Gentile World;</hi> and yet we do not
<pb n="vi" facs="tcp:99012:5"/>find that they ever ſhew'd themſelves either the leſs <hi>obedient</hi> to their <hi>Emperours,</hi> or the leſs <hi>charitable</hi> to their <hi>Neighbours,</hi> upon the account of it. And though I am verily per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded that the <hi>Romaniſts,</hi> in the <hi>Invocation</hi> of <hi>Saints,</hi> and in the <hi>Worſhip</hi> of <hi>Images</hi> and <hi>Reliques,</hi> and of the <hi>Hoſt,</hi> are guilty of <hi>Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry;</hi> yet I thank <hi>God</hi> I am not conſcious to my ſelf of one <hi>diſloyal</hi> Thought to my <hi>King,</hi> or of the leaſt <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncharitableneſs</hi> towards any of my <hi>Country-men,</hi> who differ from me in theſe <hi>Particulars.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And what I can thus truly profeſs in my own behalf, I doubt not but I may do for all others the <hi>true</hi> and <hi>genuine Members</hi> of the <hi>Church of England;</hi> and who by being ſuch, muſt, I am ſure by <hi>Principle,</hi> be both <hi>Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient Subjects,</hi> and <hi>Charitable Chriſtians.</hi> As for this Author, he has made as broad a ſigne that he intends to leave us, by inſinuating, that the Charge of Idolatry ought to be fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed with Blows, as by his concern not to have Idolatry charged upon the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi> We who do proteſt againſt certain Practices as Idolatrous, do alſo proteſt againſt violating either Loyalty or Charity, upon the
<pb n="vii" facs="tcp:99012:5"/>account of Religion. This Author, it ſeems, likes us neither upon one account, nor the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; or this at leaſt is to be ſaid, that he has been thus long of our Communion, and has not all this while underſtood what we teach concerning a Chriſtian's Duty to his Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour.</p>
            <p>Did we indeed profeſs that of <hi>Idolatry,</hi> which ſome others do of <hi>Hereſie,</hi> that 'tis a ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient Ground for the <hi>Excommunicating</hi> of a <hi>King,</hi> and <hi>Abſolving</hi> his <hi>Subjects</hi> of their Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legiance; had we ever been caught not in <hi>Oteſian Conſpiracies,</hi> but in <hi>Real Plots</hi> againſt our <hi>Soveraign</hi> upon this account, there might then have been juſt cauſe for ſuch an <hi>Inſinua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi> But whilſt our <hi>Principles</hi> are ſo <hi>Loyal,</hi> that we have even been laught at for our aſſert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them, and that too by ſome of thoſe who would now be thought ſo <hi>zealous</hi> for their Princes Safety; it was a very unreaſonable Apprehenſion, to think that the Charge of Idolatry (and that too begun in the time of a Prince of whom it was Miſpriſion of Treaſon, but to ſay that he was guilty of it) ſhould in the bottom have been the deſigne againſt the <hi>Monarchy,</hi> which we have ſo often declared,
<pb n="viii" facs="tcp:99012:6"/>and in the very Perſon of our preſent <hi>King</hi> have ſhewn, we think our ſelves obliged to ſupport, whatever his Religion be who is to ſit upon the Throne.</p>
            <p>And for what concerns our Brethren of the <hi>Roman Communion,</hi> it is well known that we are not of thoſe who <hi>deſtroy</hi> men for <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience</hi> ſake. We have never been infamous either for <hi>Pariſian Maſſacres,</hi> or Military Converſions. They are Others that have ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ined at once both the <hi>Churches</hi> and the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants of the <hi>Living God,</hi> out of <hi>Zeal</hi> for their <hi>Religion.</hi> We have indeed taken care to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move the <hi>Idols</hi> out of our <hi>Iſrael;</hi> but for the <hi>Worſhippers</hi> of them, if they have ſuffer'd a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing, it has not been for their <hi>Idolatry,</hi> but for that which ſhews there is <hi>ſomething elſe</hi> more dangerous to the <hi>Engliſh Monarchy</hi> than this Charge.</p>
            <p>The truth is, when I conſider how heinous a <hi>Suggeſtion</hi> this is, and what little <hi>foundation</hi> there is, either from our <hi>Principles,</hi> or our Practices, to ſupport it, I am under ſome tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptation to reply to this Author, as an ancient <hi>Father</hi> once did to a <hi>Heathen</hi> who accuſed them of ſuch <hi>Cruelties</hi> and <hi>Filthineſs</hi> in their
<pb n="ix" facs="tcp:99012:6"/>
               <hi>Ceremonies,</hi> as none but themſelves were ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of committing. <q>
                  <hi>Nemo hoc PO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TEST CREDERE,
<note place="margin">Minut. Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lix. Oct. <hi>p.</hi> 34.</note> niſi qui POSSIT A<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>DERE.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>And this I hope may ſerve for my Excuſe, if I have at this time appear'd in <hi>defence</hi> of a Charge in which every true <hi>Member</hi> of the Church of <hi>England</hi> is ſo highly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern'd; and for which all <hi>Orders</hi> and <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees</hi> among us, have been ſo contemptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly exploded by this <hi>Author.</hi> Or if I muſt ſtill be content to bear the Cenſure of ſuch as He, I ſhall at leaſt comfort my ſelf in this, that I can fall under no <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach,</hi> but what muſt at the ſame time reflect upon all the great <hi>Names</hi> of the <hi>Primitive Chriſtian Church,</hi> with whom I had rather ſuffer the angry Reflections of a few of our own Communion, than flouriſh with them, and gain their Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plauſes.</p>
            <p>To ſay the truth, when ſuch Learned Defenders of our Church are ſtruck at, and that in ſo impetuous a manner as that
<pb n="x" facs="tcp:99012:7"/>moſt <hi>deſervedly eſteemed Perſon</hi> he has ſo often mentioned, and I think never with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſomething to raiſe his Repute amongſt <hi>Honest</hi> and <hi>Judicious</hi> Men; I ſhould be e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven aſhamed not to be ill ſpoken of by ſuch a one at the ſame time, if I had had the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of his Acquaintance.</p>
            <p>As for what concerns the charge its ſelf, I ſhall leave it to any one to judge, whether if the <hi>Roman Church</hi> be indeed guilty of what we ſay it is, we can diſcharge our Duty either towards <hi>God,</hi> or our <hi>Neighbour,</hi> as we ought to do, without endeavouring to convince them of their danger. And when others are ſo <hi>zealous</hi> for the Reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a few <hi>Men whoſe breath is in their Noſtrils;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pag. 80.</note> ſure we may be excuſed if we expreſs <hi>ſome Jealouſie</hi> for the Honour of that God who has made both them and us.</p>
            <p>It is indeed a moſt deplorable Spectacle to conſider whether <hi>blind Superſtition,</hi> and a <hi>Zeal</hi> not according to <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding,</hi> has been able to carry otherwiſe good and pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
<pb n="xi" facs="tcp:99012:7"/>Men. Nor is it the leaſt of my Won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, to conſider Perſons whoſe Learning I admire, and whoſe <hi>Sincerity</hi> I am unwilling to queſtion, yet either by the Prejudice of <hi>Education,</hi> or by ſome other <hi>Cauſes</hi> to me unknown, ſo byaſſed in their Affections to the <hi>groſſest</hi> Errors, that the moſt plain and convincing Arguments have not been able to prevail upon them.</p>
            <p>'Tis hardly to be believed, but that they are themſelves the <hi>Publiſhers</hi> of their own <hi>Doings,</hi> that in the clear Light of <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity</hi> men ſhould be ſo blind as to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend for giving <hi>Religious Worſhip</hi> to their Fellow <hi>Creatures,</hi> and ſet up ſenſeleſs <hi>Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges</hi> to be joyned in the very ſame Act of <hi>Divine Adoration</hi> with the great <hi>God</hi> the <hi>Creator</hi> of <hi>Heaven</hi> and <hi>Earth.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Vaſquez in 3 part. D. Th. q. 25. diſp. 110.</note> And I would to <hi>God</hi> their Impiety had ſtopp'd here; but indeed it has gone much farther; they have found out ways how not only all <hi>o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther things, Animate</hi> and <hi>Inanimate,</hi> may be warrantably <hi>adored</hi> with <hi>Divine Adoration,</hi> but even the <hi>Devil</hi> himſelf be Worſhipped, without ſin; by virtue of a <hi>good Intention</hi>
               <pb n="xii" facs="tcp:99012:8"/>to Honour God; and not certainly know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it to be the <hi>Devil.</hi> And if we may believe a <hi>Man</hi> in his <hi>own Caſe,</hi> one of them once went much farther: He made no ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to <hi>Worſhip</hi> the <hi>Devil</hi> whom he <hi>knew</hi> to be ſo, and that without taking any care (for ought appears by his Relation) to <hi>terminate</hi> his <hi>Worſhip finally upon God.</hi> And becauſe it is indeed a ſingular inſtance, to ſhew to what <hi>Extravagance</hi> ſuch <hi>Principles</hi> as we oppoſe, are apt to carry indiſcreet <hi>Votaries,</hi> I will, to avoid all ſuſpicion of falſhood, give you a ſhort account of it in his own words.</p>
            <p>Father <hi>Gauffre</hi> being ſent for to <hi>Exorciſe</hi> a terrible <hi>Devil</hi> call'd <hi>Arfaxa,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Recit Verita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble de ce qui s'eſt fait &amp; paſsé ans Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orciſmes de pluſieurs Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligienſes de la Ville de Louciers en preſente de Monſieur le Penitencier d' Evreus &amp; de Monſieur le Gauffré.</hi> pag. 30, 31. This Book was printed at <hi>Paris, Anno</hi> 1643. With Permiſſion.</note> which was got into the foot of Siſter <hi>Bonaventure</hi> a <hi>Nun,</hi> ſhe earneſtly pray'd him that he would Confeſs her; for as the <hi>Father</hi> obſerves, the <hi>Devil</hi> had a particular deſire to ſpeak to him. After ſome Diſcourſe had paſs'd betwixt them, and they began to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand one another a little better, <q>I threw
<pb n="xiii" facs="tcp:99012:8"/>my ſelf (ſays the <hi>Father</hi>) upon my knees before him, telling him, that my deſigne was to confound my <hi>Pride</hi> by that of the <hi>Devils,</hi> and to learn <hi>Humility</hi> of them that had none. The <hi>Devil,</hi> enra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged to ſee me in that <hi>poſture,</hi> told me, that he had received a Command to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent me. But when I continued, for all that, to <hi>humble</hi> my ſelf before him, he thought to take advantage of it, and told me, <hi>Thou dost this to Adore Me.</hi> I repli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, Villain, thou art too infamous, I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider thee as the Creature of my <hi>God,</hi> and the Object of his Wrath; and therefore I will ſubmit my ſelf to thee, though thou doſt not deſerve it: and for that very reaſon I will immediately <hi>Kiſs thy Feet.</hi> The Devil ſurprized at this Action, hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred me. Upon which I conjured him to tell me, as far as he could gueſs at it, what the <hi>Will</hi> of <hi>God</hi> was, whether that I ſhould <hi>Kiſs his Feet,</hi> or <hi>He</hi> mine? He anſwer'd, Thou knoweſt what <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion God</hi> gives thee; follow that. Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately I threw my ſelf upon the <hi>Ground,</hi> and <hi>Kiſſed his Feet:</hi> at which
<pb n="xiv" facs="tcp:99012:9"/>he was in a Rage: And then I comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded <hi>Him</hi> by the <hi>Reliques</hi> of <hi>Father Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nard,</hi> to <hi>Kiſs mine;</hi> which he did accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly, with great readineſs. After this, I continued upon my Knees before him, for about half a quarter of an hour.</q>
            </p>
            <p>And now when theſe things are publick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly taught and done in the <hi>Roman Church,</hi> is it not high time for us to ſpeak, and to aſſert the <hi>Honour</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> and the Purity of his <hi>Religion?</hi> Shall <hi>others,</hi> without ſcruple, <hi>maintain</hi> and <hi>propagate</hi> their <hi>Errours,</hi> and ſhall it be a Crime in <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s,</hi> even when at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tacked in the moſt violent manner, to <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend</hi> the <hi>Truth?</hi> Nay, but let <hi>God</hi> be <hi>Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved,</hi> though all the World be <hi>Diſſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the mean time, whilſt forced by theſe Conſiderations to aſſert our <hi>Religion,</hi> we purſue theſe <hi>Examinations,</hi> be it your parts (for whoſe ſake we principally labour) to encourage our Endeavours by a firm ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herence to that <hi>Form of Sacred Doctrine</hi> which you have received. As you have
<pb n="xv" facs="tcp:99012:9"/>hitherto maintained an Unreprovable <hi>Zeal</hi> for your <hi>Profeſſion,</hi> ſo go on more and more to contend <q>
                  <hi>Earneſtly for the Faith that was once deliver'd to the Saints.</hi>
               </q>
               <note place="margin">Jude, v. 3.</note> And above all, be careful to adorn your <hi>Holy Religion</hi> with a <hi>ſuitable Practice,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Pet. 3.16.</note> 
               <q>
                  <hi>That they may be aſhamed, who falſly accuſe your good Converſation in Christ. For ſo is the Will of God,
<note place="margin">Joh. 2.15.</note> that with well doing ye ſhould put to ſilence the ignorance of fooliſh men.</hi>
               </q> Let the ſame mind be in us, which was alſo in thoſe Primitive Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians before-mentioned. Let us boldly aſſert the Truth, as thoſe who know what Account they are one day to give unto God for it;
<note place="margin">Mat. 5.44.</note> but let us alſo be <hi>Charitable</hi> towards our <hi>Neighbours:</hi> and if they will rather be eſteem'd our <hi>Enemies,</hi> let us re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member, that even under that <hi>Name,</hi> we are yet to <hi>Love them.</hi> Let us ſtill be care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to maintain the <hi>Character</hi> of the <hi>Best Subjects,</hi> as we have long aſſerted the moſt <hi>Loyal Principles:</hi> that as the <hi>Proſperity</hi> of our <hi>King</hi> makes up a conſiderable part of our Daily <hi>Prayers,</hi> ſo by a ſincere diſcharge of all humble <hi>Obedience</hi> towards Him, He
<pb n="xvi" facs="tcp:99012:10"/>may be convinced of the Malice of thoſe who would inſinuate any falſe Suggeſtions againſt us; and effectually ſee, that, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepting only our <hi>Duty towards God,</hi> we are much more Forward and Ready to do his Majeſty Effectual Service, than any man can be, whoſe Loyalty is not Supported by Religion.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="chapter">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:99012:10"/>
            <head>CHAP. I. <hi>In which the Charge of</hi> Idolatry <hi>which we bring against thoſe of the Church of</hi> Rome, <hi>is freed from thoſe</hi> O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious Imputations <hi>that have been of late ſuggeſted against it.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>IT may poſſibly appear to ſome not a little ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prizing, that a <hi>Church</hi> which makes no ſcruple of <hi>practiſing</hi> what is <hi>Idolatrous,</hi> ſhould yet be ſo very unwilling to lie under the <hi>imputation</hi> of it: There is nothing in all our <hi>Diſputes</hi> with thoſe of the <hi>other Communion,</hi> which they would be thought ſo highly to reſent as this; the very mention of it has ſeem'd to <hi>Scandalize</hi> them; and if heat and confidence could have born us down, they had long ſince effectually deliver'd themſelves from all <hi>ſuſpicion</hi> of it.</p>
            <p>It is not my buſineſs to enquire into the <hi>Reaſons</hi> of this <hi>Proceeding,</hi> and which, when duly conſider'd, will be found to have nothing in it, but what is exceeding natural. Men are always more forward to do ill things, than to <hi>avow</hi> them, or to own them under their proper names: <hi>Idolatry</hi> (as our Author ſays) <hi>is a ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalous Charge.</hi> By his leave, the <hi>Charge</hi> is not always
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:99012:11"/>ſcandalous, though the Crime be ever ſo, and the Charge reputed ſcandalous by them who are charged with it. Though a <hi>Church</hi> that does countenance the Commiſſion of it, may by ſubtile Arguments and bold Denials keep up its <hi>Reputation</hi> well enough amongſt thoſe who are reſolv'd at any rate to believe her, yet 'twere impoſſible ſhe ſhould long ſupport her <hi>Interest,</hi> ſhould ſhe freely avow the doing of it.</p>
            <p>But of all the <hi>Methods</hi> that have been made uſe of to put a ſtop to this <hi>Charge,</hi> there has been none ſo ſurprizing as what this <hi>Author</hi> has here found out; and could he but have made it good, I am perſwaded there would not have been any more effectual. He repreſents it as inconſiſtent not only with the <hi>Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples</hi> of <hi>Charity</hi> towards our <hi>Neighbour,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Page</hi> 71, &amp;c.</note> but even of <hi>Loyalty</hi> towards our <hi>Prince;</hi> and makes the very men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of it to be little leſs than <hi>a ſetting up of the Stan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dard against Monarchy.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Page</hi> 74.</note> And yet he is not ſo unac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with the <hi>Principles</hi> and <hi>Diſpoſitions</hi> of thoſe of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> as not to know, that next to our ſollicitude for the Honour of God, there are no two things in the World, we value our ſelves more up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, than that Character we have ſo juſtly obtained, of teaching the beſt Meaſures both of <hi>Duty</hi> to our <hi>King,</hi> and of <hi>Love,</hi> and <hi>Kindneſs,</hi> and <hi>Charity</hi> towards <hi>One A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I muſt therefore, before I proceed to vindicate our <hi>Notion</hi> of <hi>Idolatry,</hi> firſt ſay ſomewhat to remove this great <hi>prejudice</hi> that has been offer'd againſt it; And this I ſhall do,
<list>
                  <item>I. By conſidering upon what <hi>weak Grounds</hi> this <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor</hi> has undertaken to inſinuate theſe <hi>Crimes</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt us.</item>
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:99012:11"/>
                  <item>II. By ſhewing what <hi>horrible Conſequences</hi> would follow from it, ſhould what he pretends indeed be <hi>true.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. Of the <hi>weak Grounds</hi> upon which he has under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taken to inſinuate ſuch things againſt us.</p>
            <p>Now all that he has to ſay for this odious <hi>Charge,</hi> if taken out of his turbulent and declamatory Stile, is but this: <q>That <hi>Idolatry</hi> is a Sin very heighnous to <hi>God,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Page</hi> 71, 72, 73.</note> and which he therefore, under the <hi>Law,</hi> commanded to be puniſhed with <hi>Death.</hi>
               </q> This is the ſum of what he has dilated upon in <hi>three</hi> whole <hi>Pages;</hi> and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt this I have many things to except. For,</p>
            <p n="1">1. What if <hi>Idolatry</hi> be a damnable Sin, may we not therefore ſay, without uncharitableneſs, that thoſe are guilty of it, whom we effectually prove to be ſo? <hi>Muſt we therefore become mens Enemies becauſe we tell them the Truth?</hi> I am ſure a very little <hi>Charity</hi> would have taught him to have made a better <hi>Concluſion;</hi> nor can I imagine what greater inſtance of my Affection, I could ſhew my beſt Friend, if I ſaw him in ſuch a courſe as I thought would render him <hi>eternally miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable,</hi> than to tell him freely of the <hi>danger</hi> of his <hi>Sin,</hi> and preſs him with the beſt <hi>Reaſons</hi> I had to perſwade him to forſake it.</p>
            <p>It may be he will ſay, he does not deny but that we may <hi>charge</hi> men with great <hi>Sins,</hi> provided that they be truly <hi>guilty</hi> of them: But yet that the heighnouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of this <hi>Crime</hi> ſhould make us careful not to do it, but upon very good grounds; for to this purpoſe I find he ſometimes expreſſes himſelf: <q>So black a <hi>Crime</hi> as this (ſays he) is not <hi>Lightly</hi> to be charg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed on any Party of <hi>Chriſtians.</hi>
               </q>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Page</hi> 73.</note> And again, <q>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:99012:12"/>ſo <hi>bloudy</hi> an <hi>Indictment</hi> be preferred againſt the greateſt Party of <hi>Chriſtendom,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Page</hi> 73.</note> the nature of the thing ought to be very well underſtood.</q> And if this be all hemeans, we readily acknowledge the reaſonablneſs of it: but then he ought not to fly out into ſuch Tragical common places againſt us for charging the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi> with <hi>Idolatry;</hi> but to come cloſe to the <hi>Point,</hi> and ſhew that we have not ſufficient <hi>grounds</hi> for what we do.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Page</hi> 70, 71.</note> If thoſe whom we accuſe of this <hi>Crime,</hi> be indeed <hi>innocent</hi> of it, whether <hi>God</hi> had commanded <hi>Idolaters</hi> to be Stoned under the <hi>Law</hi> or not, we could not juſtifie our charging of them with it: but if our <hi>Arguments</hi> do prove them <hi>guilty,</hi> the <hi>heinouſneſs</hi> of the Sin, and the <hi>danger</hi> of it, may be a good <hi>motive</hi> to diſpoſe them ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly to weigh our <hi>Allegations,</hi> but I am ſure it can lay no obligation upon us not to impute to it them.</p>
            <p n="2">2.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Page</hi> 71.</note> As to the other <hi>inſinuation,</hi> that God command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Idolaters</hi> under the <hi>Law</hi> to be put to Death: And for proof of which, we have two long paſſages tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed out of <hi>Exodus</hi> and <hi>Deuteronomy;</hi> What would he infer from it? would he prove to us, that therefore they ought to be put to Death by us under the Goſpel too? does he look upon theſe <hi>Precepts</hi> as <hi>Obligatory</hi> to us now? If ſo, I dare be bold to ſay, he has done more in one ſingle Page, to ſtir up the <hi>People</hi> againſt <hi>the Romaniſts</hi> and <hi>their Images,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Page</hi> 72, 73.</note> than all thoſe <hi>popular Divines</hi> he ſo complains of, in all the <hi>Books</hi> they have ever written upon this <hi>Subject.</hi> And yet this muſt be his <hi>Meaning,</hi> if it has any <hi>Meaning</hi> at all. For to exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine this matter a little more cloſely: <hi>God</hi> (he ſays) commanded the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> in <hi>Deut.</hi> 13.6. <hi>If thy bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, the ſon of thy mother, or thy ſon, or thy daughter, or the wife of thy boſom, or thy friend which is as thine own
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:99012:12"/>ſoul, entice thee ſecretly, ſaying. Let us go and ſerve o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther gods,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Thou ſhalt not conſent unto him, nor hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken unto him, neither ſhall thine eye pity him; But thou ſhalt ſurely kill him: thine hand ſhall be firſt upon him to death, and afterward the hand of all the people. And thou ſhalt ſtone him with ſtones that he die.</hi> Now either he looks upon this <hi>Precept</hi> as ſtill in force, and would hereby inſinuate to the <hi>People,</hi> that it is their Duty, if they think the <hi>Romaniſts</hi> guilty of <hi>Idolatry,</hi> utterly to deſtroy them; and this is certainly one of the moſt <hi>Seditious,</hi> as well as one of the moſt <hi>falſe</hi> Suggeſtions in the World: or if he does not believe this <hi>Command</hi> obligatory to us now, nor would inſinuate any ſuch thing by the repetition of it, what <hi>impertinence</hi> muſt it be to ſay that we cannot in <hi>Charity</hi> charge the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi> with <hi>Idolatry,</hi> becauſe <hi>God</hi> command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed heretofore under the <hi>Law</hi> that all thoſe that were <hi>guilty</hi> of it ſhould be put to Death.</p>
            <p>But though theſe kind of <hi>Precepts</hi> do not oblige us now, yet may not ſuch a <hi>Charge</hi> be apt to ſtir up the deluded <hi>Rabble</hi> to think ſo;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Page</hi> 72.</note> and ſo upon occaſion en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage them to deſtroy the <hi>Roman Catholicks</hi> and their <hi>Images,</hi> as the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> were commanded to deſtroy the <hi>Canaanites</hi> and their <hi>Idols?</hi> Anſwer, Yes; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided there were but a few ſuch <hi>Orators</hi> as himſelf a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them, to fill their heads with ſuch Notions as theſe, and never tell them the <hi>impertinence</hi> of them. For inſtance: That theſe were onely the <hi>Political Laws</hi> of the <hi>Jews,</hi> and therefore can no more warrant us now to do any violence to our Neighbour, upon any ſuch pretence, than becauſe the <hi>Jews</hi> were com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded to do no work upon the <hi>Sabbath day,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Numb.</hi> 15.32, &amp;c.</note> we may therefore lawfully Stone any one that we ſee <hi>gather<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:99012:13"/>a few Sticks</hi> upon it. But if the <hi>Queſtion</hi> be, Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the <hi>Charge</hi> of <hi>Idolatry,</hi> as it is managed by us a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi> may not be apt to cauſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſuch miſchief? I ſay, it is not; and that for theſe Reaſons: For,</p>
            <p n="1">1. Let him examin all our <hi>Books</hi> of <hi>Controverſie,</hi> and ſee if he can find any of theſe old Laws produced, much leſs inſiſted upon, and inforced by us, to <hi>miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lead</hi> the <hi>People</hi> into any ſuch <hi>deſperate Miſtakes:</hi> On the contrary, we take all occaſions to declare to them, that no pretences of this kind can warrant us ſo much as to withdraw our <hi>Affection</hi> from thoſe who differ from us:
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.43, &amp;c.</note> That the <hi>Jews</hi> indeed eſteem'd themſelves allowed to <hi>hate their Enemies;</hi> that is, thoſe who were not of the ſame Religion with themſelves, but Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped other Gods; and more eſpecially thoſe <hi>Cana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anites,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Page</hi> 72.</note> whom we are told it pleaſed <hi>God</hi> to <hi>deſtroy from off the face of the earth</hi> for their <hi>Idolatry:</hi> but that our Saviour Chriſt has utterly forbid us to make any ſuch diſtinction:
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Verſe</hi> 44.</note> 
               <hi>I ſay unto you, love your enemies, bleſs them that curſe you, do good to them that hate you, and pray for them that deſpitefully uſe you, and perſecute you.</hi> We ſet before them the Examples of the <hi>Primitive Chriſtians;</hi> with what <hi>Charity</hi> they behaved themſelves towards the <hi>Gentiles</hi> among whom they lived; with what an <hi>humble Obedience</hi> they ſubmitted themſelves to their <hi>Idolatrous Emperours,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tertul. Apol.</note> and underwent the moſt cruel <hi>Perſecutions</hi> for their <hi>Religion</hi>'s ſake, even when they had power ſufficient to have aſſerted their Faith, and to have deſtroyed both the <hi>Idolaters</hi> and their <hi>Idols</hi> together. And by theſe Maxims we exhort them to walk; and according to theſe it is that we both now do, and I am perſwaded ſhall always behave ourſelves
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:99012:13"/>with all <hi>Chriſtian Charity</hi> towards thoſe of the <hi>Roman Communion,</hi> notwithſtanding we both believe them to be guilty of <hi>Idolatry,</hi> and charge them accordingly. But</p>
            <p n="2">2. We do not only tell them, that thoſe kind of <hi>Laws</hi> are now no longer in force, and that therefore we may not by vertue of them preſume to run into any <hi>violence</hi> againſt our <hi>Brethren:</hi> but we teach them moreover, (what yet more ſhews the impertinent Malice of this <hi>Suggeſtion</hi>) that they never were intended, even un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the <hi>Jewiſh State,</hi> to be in force againſt ſuch <hi>Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters</hi> as they of the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi> are. It is manifeſt to every one that has impartially conſidered the <hi>Noti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> of <hi>Idolatry,</hi> in the Old Teſtament, that there were <hi>two</hi> very different <hi>kinds</hi> of it: 1. One whereby they to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tally Apoſtatized from the <hi>Law,</hi> to Worſhip other <hi>Gods</hi> than the <hi>GOD</hi> of <hi>Iſrael;</hi> as when 'tis ſaid that they fell off to Worſhip <hi>ſtrange Gods; i. e.</hi> they renounced the Religion eſtabliſhed by the <hi>Law</hi> of <hi>Moſes,</hi> and took in another Religion, with all the <hi>Ceremonies</hi> and <hi>Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices</hi> belonging to it, as the <hi>Aegyptian, Canaanitiſh,</hi> or <hi>Chaldaean:</hi> And ſuch as theſe were concluded under the Sentence of the <hi>Law</hi> before mentioned. 2. But then another ſort of <hi>Idolatry</hi> there was, in which they ſtill pretended to adhere to the <hi>Law</hi> of <hi>Moſes,</hi> and Worſhip the <hi>God</hi> of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> but yet after an <hi>Idolatrous</hi> manner, as when <hi>Jeroboam</hi> ſet up the <hi>two Calves</hi> in <hi>Dan</hi> and <hi>Bethel;</hi> parallel to which, is that <hi>Idolatry</hi> with which we charge thoſe of the <hi>other Communion</hi> at this day. Now in this <hi>Caſe,</hi> though we find the Prophets ſeverely exclaiming againſt their new Altars, yet we do not meet with any inforcement of this <hi>Precept</hi> for putting ſuch <hi>Idolat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rs</hi> to Death, or that they are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:99012:14"/>where charged as guilty of it upon this Account.</p>
            <p>In ſhort, he that would know how innocent this <hi>Charge</hi> is, of any of thoſe ill <hi>Conſequences</hi> that are here brought againſt it, need onely look back to the State of the Church in the days of <hi>Conſtantine:</hi> there he will find our <hi>Primitive Fathers,</hi> freely accuſing the <hi>Arrians</hi> of <hi>Idolatry,</hi> and ſometimes warm enough too in their Diſputes againſt them; but yet I believe all the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cords of thoſe times, will not furniſh <hi>this Author</hi> with ſo much as one inſtance of any <hi>Biſhop</hi> that ever put the Emperour in mind of this Law againſt them; or ſo much as inſinuated to him, that he might warrantly <hi>deſtroy</hi> them out of his <hi>Dominions</hi> for their <hi>Idolatry.</hi> And ſure our behaviour towards thoſe of the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi> has not been ſo different from what theirs was againſt the <hi>Arrians,</hi> that any <hi>ſuch violence</hi> ſhould be fear'd from us now, as was never ſo much as urged by the <hi>hottest Oppoſers</hi> of <hi>Idolatry</hi> in thoſe days.</p>
            <p>But 2dly, If there be then no good <hi>Grounds</hi> for ſuch <hi>Inſinuations</hi> as theſe, which he has here offer'd onely to render our <hi>Charge</hi> of <hi>Idolatry</hi> odious, I am ſure there is cauſe enough upon other accounts, to make them juſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be deteſted by all <hi>good Men.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For 1. Not to ſay any thing of the <hi>ſad Conſequences</hi> that may ariſe from hence, ſhould ſuch inſinuations as theſe ever be able to gain ſo much credit with his <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Majeſty,</hi> as to make him entertain that ill Opinion of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s</hi> and our <hi>Religion,</hi> as we ſhould juſtly deſerve, were we ſuch as we are here <hi>repreſented</hi> to be: Can a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing be more deſperate, than to impeach at once the whole Body of a Great and Orthodox <hi>Church,</hi> of holding Principles ſo <hi>inhumane,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Page</hi> 73.</note> 
               <q>As to out do the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry <hi>Cannibals</hi> themſelves; and for which they have
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:99012:14"/>no <hi>other Grounds</hi> than the (rude and raſh Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſertions of ſome <hi>popular Divines,</hi> that have no other meaſure of Truth or Zeal, but Hatred to <hi>Popery.</hi> In ſhort, of maintaining <hi>Fanatick Pretences,</hi> and ſuch as have <hi>ever been</hi> ſet up as the Standard a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Monarchy.</q> What is this but, in other words, to ſay, that all the Orders and Degrees of Men a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt us, that have ever been concern'd in charging the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> with <hi>Idolatry,</hi> our <hi>Princes</hi> and our <hi>Nobles,</hi> the Houſes of <hi>Parliament</hi> and <hi>Convocati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> as many as concurred either to the <hi>Approving</hi> or <hi>Subſcribing</hi> the <hi>Book</hi> of <hi>Homilies,</hi> or to the <hi>Eſtabliſhing</hi> or the obeying of the Laws made in the laſt Reign, not to ſay any thing of thoſe <hi>Learned Men</hi> who have from time to time written expreſly on this Subject, were all in plain terms neither better nor worſe than a Pack of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nlearned, Cruel, Barbarous, Cannibal, Fanatical, Antimonarchical Villains.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Certainly, a man had need have either a very good Cauſe, or a very <hi>hard Forehead,</hi> that can have the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence to pronounce ſuch a Sentence as this, and of which I will only ſay, in his own words,
<note place="margin">Pag. 73.</note> 
               <q>That how inconſiſtent ſoever <hi>Idolatry</hi> may be with Salvation, I fear ſo <hi>uncharitable a Calumny</hi> can be of no leſs dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable conſequence.</q> But however,</p>
            <p n="2">2. To allow this great Author to take any Liberty he pleaſes with us: What ſhall we ſay as to the <hi>Primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Chriſtians,</hi> whoſe Examples we follow, by whoſe <hi>Principles</hi> we manage this whole <hi>Controverſie,</hi> and with whom therefore we muſt either ſtand or fall. Were all they a parcel of <hi>Seditious Fellows</hi> too? It cannot be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny'd, but that thoſe <hi>Holy Men</hi> very freely charged the <hi>Gentiles</hi> firſt, and then the <hi>Heretical Chriſtians,</hi> the <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians,</hi>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:99012:15"/>and others, with <hi>Idolatry.</hi> And the Paſſages of thoſe Writers, <hi>Juſtin Martyr, Origen, Clemens Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drinus, Tertullian, Cyprian, Athanaſius, Greg. Nazian<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zen, Epiphanius, Theodoret,</hi> and others, have been too often alledged, to need a Repetition here. And which ought not to be forgot, at the time that they did this, their Emperours were themſelves of that very <hi>Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> which they ſo Accuſed. Now then, according to this <hi>Learned Gentleman,</hi> all theſe Holy <hi>Biſhops</hi> and <hi>Martyrs</hi> were even as bad as we; and <hi>Antiquity</hi> has been ſo ſottiſh as to celebrate the <hi>Praiſes,</hi> and recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend to us the <hi>Examples</hi> of a long Series of <hi>Factious Fanaticks,</hi> who for their Rudeneſs to their <hi>Emperours,</hi> and <hi>Cannibal</hi> uncharitable <hi>Cenſures</hi> of their Brethren, juſtly deſerv'd all the <hi>Torments</hi> and <hi>Perſecutions</hi> that they underwent. But,</p>
            <p n="3">3. Becauſe thoſe that pretend the higheſt regard to the Authority of the Fathers, can yet eaſily except againſt it, when they are preſſed with it, what will this Author ſay to that of the Apoſtles? It cannot reaſonably be doubted but that St. <hi>Paul</hi> very well underſtood the true nature of <hi>Charity,</hi> who ſo often and earneſtly recommended it to his Diſciples; and that he was no Friend to any <hi>Seditious, Anti-monarchical</hi> Principles, I believe his 13th Chapter to the <hi>Romans,</hi> will ſufficiently demonſtrate. Yet behold this very St. <hi>Paul</hi> charging the <hi>Emperours Religion</hi> as <hi>Idolatrous,</hi> exhorting all men to forſake it as ſuch; and going up and down in all parts, preaching where-ever he came againſt it, on this account. And I deſire this <hi>Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> to conſider with himſelf what he can ſay in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of this <hi>Holy Apoſtle,</hi> that ſhall not vindicate <hi>us</hi> too.</p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:99012:15"/>
            <p>So that now then upon the whole it appears, that out of an over-eager deſire to <hi>Traduce</hi> us, this <hi>judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Author</hi> has in his <hi>Heat</hi> expoſed all the <hi>Chriſtians</hi> of the firſt three hundred years, the <hi>Catholicks</hi> of the following <hi>Centuries,</hi> nay the bleſſed <hi>Apoſtles</hi> themſelves, beſides the whole <hi>Body</hi> of the <hi>Reform'd Religion</hi> in this and the laſt Age, as the worſt of <hi>Monſters,</hi> and ſuch as deſerve to be eſteem'd any thing, rather than Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians.</p>
            <p>Let thoſe, whoſe Cauſe he has ſo unfortunately un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertaken, conſider this; and I am perſwaded they will begin to grow <hi>aſham'd</hi> of their Advocate. And how unjuſt ſoever they may eſteem our <hi>Charge</hi> of <hi>Idolatry,</hi> yet they will not ſay, it is ſuch as cannot be main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd againſt them, without inſpiring us at the ſame time with all the horrible impulſes of <hi>Cruelty</hi> and <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barity</hi> againſt themſelves, and of Faction and Rebellion againſt the <hi>Government;</hi> which ſome men would inſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuate.</p>
            <p>As for our ſelves, we earneſtly beſeech all thoſe of the <hi>Church of Rome,</hi> againſt whom we at any time ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance this <hi>Imputation,</hi> that they will as <hi>candidly</hi> conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der our <hi>Arguments,</hi> as we can truly profeſs they are <hi>charitably</hi> propoſed by Us; and whether they ſhall remain ſatisfied or not, that there is Reaſon in our <hi>Charge,</hi> yet to give us ſo much <hi>Credit</hi> with them at leaſt, as to believe that we think there is; and ſhall be heartily glad to be convinced that we were miſtaken in our <hi>Opinion.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="chapter">
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:99012:16"/>
            <head>CHAP. II. <hi>In which this Author's</hi> True <hi>and</hi> on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Notion <hi>of</hi> Idolatry <hi>is Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider'd, and the Method laid down for a more</hi> particular Examina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion <hi>of it.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>I Will now take it for granted, that under the ſhel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of ſo great an <hi>Authority</hi> as I have ſhewn to be equally concern'd with us, in all the ſcandalous impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations that can be raiſed againſt our charging thoſe of the <hi>Church of Rome</hi> with <hi>Idolatry,</hi> I may venture to ſearch a little more particularly into the nature of it, without being thought either a <hi>Cannibal</hi> or a <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natick,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pag. 73, 74.</note> or to have any deſign of <hi>ſetting up a Standard againſt the Monarchy,</hi> for my ſo doing; eſpecially con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering that I reſolve not to encounter any <hi>Church</hi> or <hi>Party</hi> of men in the <hi>World</hi> on this occaſion, but meer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to ſhew that this Man's <hi>Notion</hi> of <hi>Idolatry,</hi> though ſet off with ſuch aſſurance as few Writers have ever equalled, is yet, after all, ſo far from being ſupported either by <hi>Scripture</hi> or <hi>Antiquity,</hi> that it is indeed utterly repugnant to both. And therefore that the <hi>Church of Rome</hi> is only Vindicated by him from the Charge of an <hi>Idolatry</hi> that no man ever produced againſt her,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:99012:16"/>but for ſuch <hi>Idolatry</hi> as we accuſe her of, ſhe may ſtill fall under the weight of that, for any thing that has here been offer'd to the contrary.</p>
            <p>According to this Author, <hi>Idolatry</hi> is neither more nor leſs than this: <hi>The Worſhip of the heavenly Bodies, the Sun, the Moon, and the Stars, or any other Viſible and Corporeal Deity, as the Supream God, ſo as to exclude all Senſe and Apprehenſion of a Spiritual and Inviſible Godhead.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>From whence it follows, that to make a Man an <hi>Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>later,</hi> theſe three things are required.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That he caſt off all <hi>Senſe</hi> and <hi>Apprehenſion</hi> of a <hi>Spiritual</hi> and <hi>Inviſible Godhead.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. That he believes there is no other <hi>Supream God</hi> than either the <hi>Sun, Moon,</hi> or <hi>Stars,</hi> or ſome other the like <hi>Viſible</hi> and <hi>Corporeal parts of the World.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. That in purſuance of this Apprehenſion, he wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips theſe Viſible and Corporeal Deities as the Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pream God.</p>
            <p>Now to exclude all <hi>Senſe</hi> and <hi>Apprehenſion</hi> of a <hi>Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual</hi> and <hi>Inviſible Godhead,</hi> and to believe no other <hi>Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pream God,</hi> but ſome <hi>Viſible</hi> and <hi>Corporeal</hi> part of the World, in oppoſition to a <hi>Spiritual</hi> and <hi>Inviſible God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head,</hi> is, I think, to be an <hi>Atheiſt,</hi> though here is much ado to deſcribe him. For to believe none but a <hi>Viſible God,</hi> in oppoſition to an <hi>Inviſible One,</hi> and to believe none but a <hi>Corporeal God,</hi> in oppoſition to a <hi>Spiritual God,</hi> is to believe no God at all; unleſs a man can ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe a <hi>Supream God,</hi> without Underſtanding, or any Perfection whatſoever of a <hi>Spiritual</hi> and <hi>Inviſible Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:99012:17"/>
            <p>By conſequence, for a man with theſe Apprehenſions to worſhip this <hi>God</hi> which he has made to himſelf, is not well capable of any other conſtruction, than that he takes ſome pains, and goes a little way about to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe all <hi>Religion</hi> and <hi>Worſhip</hi> to Contempt.</p>
            <p>I would be very glad to underſtand our <hi>Author</hi>'s Notion of <hi>Idolatry;</hi> and therefore if it were poſſible, I ſhould be content that his <hi>Idolater</hi> ſhould not be an <hi>Atheiſt</hi> for a while, that we might ſee what elſe we can make of him. For a man to take nothing elſe for the <hi>Supream God,</hi> but a certain <hi>Viſible Being,</hi> from which he ſhuts out all <hi>Apprehenſion</hi> of a <hi>Spiritual</hi> and <hi>Inviſible Godhead,</hi> is certainly to be a downright <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theiſt,</hi> though his <hi>Atheiſm</hi> might have been deſcribed in fewer words. And yet on the other ſide, to wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip ſomething in good earneſt as the <hi>Supream God,</hi> ſeems to imply that a man is not an <hi>Atheiſt:</hi> For an <hi>Atheiſt</hi> is one that does not ſo much as believe that there is a <hi>Supream God.</hi> But he ſurely <hi>believes</hi> a <hi>God,</hi> who worſhips any thing for the <hi>Supream God,</hi> whatever that be which he ſo worſhips.</p>
            <p>Now if <hi>Thomas Aquinas</hi> were here, it would ſtrange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly perplex him to clear this matter. I do not mean to make good ſenſe of the words, for that I take to be impoſſible, but to tell us by the words, what the <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor</hi>'s drift ſhould be. For they make up a <hi>Nonſenſe</hi> ſo very ſtiff, that it will not bend one way or the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. And if I muſt underſtand ſomething by every word that he ſays, I can have no more Notion of his <hi>Idolatry</hi> than I have of nothing. And if he had ſaid, <hi>Idolatry</hi> is neither <hi>more</hi> nor <hi>leſs</hi> than <hi>Nothing,</hi> I had been as much edified as I am now. Unleſs he would give us to underſtand, that <hi>Idolatry</hi> is meer ſpecula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:99012:17"/>Madneſs, which no body that has common ſenſe and underſtanding, can poſſibly be guilty of.</p>
            <p>For all that part of the World that either is or ought to be out of <hi>Bethlehem</hi> and the like <hi>Hoſpitals,</hi> do by the <hi>Supream God,</hi> underſtand ſomething at leaſt, that is not only able to help or to hinder, but knows alſo when to do one and t'other, and is willing to do accordingly. And therefore to worſhip any thing as the <hi>Supream God,</hi> and at the ſame time <hi>to exclude all Senſe and Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion of a Spiritual and Inviſible Godhead,</hi> is to wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip a thing becauſe I am ſure it knows ſomething, while I take care to be as ſure at the ſame time, that it knows nothing at all. I can compare this to no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, as I have already intimated, but to ſome extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary inſtance of <hi>Madneſs.</hi> For inſtance: If I ſhould ever ſee a man fall down upon his Knees, and ſeem in good earneſt to ask Bleſſing of a Poſt, and to call it Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, I ſhould preſently think of this <hi>Author's Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter:</hi> for his <hi>Idolater</hi> is rather more than leſs mad than he that fancies a <hi>Post</hi> to be his <hi>Father.</hi> For men in their Wits, have at leaſt as high an Opinion of what they take to be their <hi>Supream God,</hi> as they have of their <hi>Parents:</hi> And therefore to worſhip that as the <hi>Supream God,</hi> which no leſs wants the Perfections of a <hi>Spiritual</hi> and <hi>Inviſible Nature,</hi> than a <hi>Post</hi> does, is a Misfortune that cannot light upon any Body but a Mad man.</p>
            <p>So that our <hi>Author's Idolater</hi> is a man whom ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther all the World muſt acknowledge to be out of his <hi>Wits,</hi> or if you put him into his <hi>Wits,</hi> he is a meer <hi>Atheiſt;</hi> though I am confident he would not have deſcribed himſelf ſo wittily, as this <hi>Author</hi> has de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed him.</p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:99012:18"/>
            <p>This <hi>Notion</hi> of <hi>Idolatry</hi> is to me ſo monſtrous a No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that I am apt to look again and again into the Book, to ſee if the words be there in which he has de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver'd it. But when at laſt I find that they are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedly there, I am taken with a new fear, that the <hi>Author</hi> did not <hi>mean</hi> what he <hi>ſays;</hi> and therefore that I do not underſtand <hi>his</hi> meaning, though I under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the meaning of <hi>his words.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In ſuch a Caſe as this, I have nothing to do, but to take another <hi>Notion</hi> of <hi>Idolatry;</hi> which though it be not the <hi>true</hi> and <hi>only Notion</hi> of it, has yet plain ſenſe, and comes as near to his, as a <hi>Notion</hi> that has <hi>Senſe</hi> can come to one that has none. And it is this: That <hi>I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolatry</hi> is the <hi>Worſhip</hi> of the <hi>Sun, Moon,</hi> or <hi>Stars,</hi> or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other <hi>Viſible</hi> and <hi>Corporeal Deity,</hi> as the <hi>Supream God,</hi> not ſo as to <hi>exclude</hi> all <hi>Senſe</hi> and <hi>Apprehenſion</hi> of a <hi>Spiritual</hi> and <hi>Inviſible Godhead;</hi> but ſo as to ſuppoſe that as they are <hi>Viſible Beings,</hi> ſo they have <hi>Inviſible Natures</hi> too, and ſome <hi>Spiritual Perfections,</hi> which are indeed proper to the <hi>true God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now this Notion of <hi>Idolatry</hi> is, in <hi>one part</hi> of it, quite contrary to our <hi>Author's.</hi> For they who worſhip any <hi>Viſible Deity</hi> as the <hi>Supream God,</hi> with this per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſion, that it has indeed <hi>Spiritual</hi> and <hi>Inviſible Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections,</hi> do not thereby <hi>exclude all Senſe and Apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of a Spiritual and Inviſible Godhead;</hi> becauſe they have the <hi>Senſe</hi> of ſuch a <hi>Godhead</hi> in the <hi>Notion</hi> of that very thing which they <hi>worſhip.</hi> But though this is not the <hi>Idolatry</hi> which his Book ſpeaks of, yet, as I ſaid, 'tis the likeſt to it that I can think of. And if he does not mean what his Book ſays, 'tis a hunder'd to one but he means this.</p>
            <p>But if I ſhould be miſtaken, 'tis no great matter;
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:99012:18"/>for if I can but ſhew that this is not the <hi>only Notion</hi> of <hi>Idolatry,</hi> it follows out of hand, that the <hi>Notion</hi> of his <hi>Book</hi> cannot poſſibly be ſo neither: So that one way or other I am ſure to reach him, whether <hi>he</hi> and his <hi>Book</hi> have one meaning or two.</p>
            <p n="1">1. According to this <hi>Notion</hi> then, thoſe who re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain the <hi>ſenſe</hi> and <hi>apprehenſion</hi> of a <hi>Spiritual</hi> and <hi>Invi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible Godhead,</hi> though they do worſhip the <hi>Heavenly Bodies,</hi> the <hi>Sun, Moon,</hi> and <hi>Stars,</hi> but this only as <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferior</hi> and <hi>Subordinate Deities,</hi> cannot be <hi>Idolaters.</hi> And therefore if the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> the <hi>Aegyptians,</hi> for in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, or the <hi>Chaldaeans,</hi> did believe <hi>One Supream God,</hi> and worſhipped the <hi>Sun, Moon,</hi> and <hi>Stars,</hi> upon the account of thoſe <hi>Caeleſtial Spirits</hi> they ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to reſide in them, this worſhip was not <hi>Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trous.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In like manner, thoſe <hi>Gentiles</hi> that worſhipped any <hi>Corporeal Deity,</hi> or any thing <hi>Viſible</hi> or <hi>Inviſible</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides the <hi>Supreme God,</hi> if they believed all the while that it was not the <hi>Supreme God,</hi> and did not wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip it as ſuch, they I ſay could not be <hi>Idolaters.</hi> And therefore I think if the <hi>Gentiles</hi> were <hi>Idolaters</hi> in <hi>worſhipping</hi> any of their <hi>Deities,</hi> it muſt be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they had no knowledge of the <hi>true God.</hi> So that either St. <hi>Paul</hi> or this <hi>Author</hi> was out in the <hi>true</hi> and <hi>only Notion</hi> of <hi>Idolatry.</hi> For though St. <hi>Paul</hi> accuſed the <hi>Gentiles</hi> of <hi>Idolatry,</hi> yet he confeſſed, that they <hi>knew God.</hi> For (ſays he) Though they knew God yet they glorified him not as God. <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.</p>
            <p n="2">2. If we do but interpret the <hi>Cautions</hi> of the <hi>New Teſtament</hi> againſt <hi>Idolatry,</hi> by our <hi>Author's Notion</hi> of <hi>Idolatry,</hi> they will be <hi>Paraphraſed</hi> ſo as I believe they never were done before his time, and I ſuppoſe
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:99012:19"/>will never be after it. For inſtance; When St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaid to the <hi>Corinthian Chriſtians, My dearly Beloved, flee from Idolatry;</hi> this was as much as if he had ſaid, <q>
                  <hi>My dearly Beloved, Idolatry</hi> being neither <hi>more</hi> nor <hi>leſs</hi> than the <hi>Worſhip of the Heavenly Bodies,</hi> the <hi>Sun,</hi> the <hi>Moon,</hi> the <hi>Stars,</hi> or any Other <hi>Viſible or Corporeal Deity as the Supreme God,</hi> I intreat and carneſtly require you to <hi>Flee from Idolatry.</hi> And therefore though I do not bid you worſhip the <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Bodies,</hi> or their <hi>Images</hi> upon <hi>Earth,</hi> yet I ſtrictly charge you, not to worſhip them as the <hi>Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme God,</hi> or as if there were not an <hi>Inviſible God</hi> above them All; if ever you ſhould find it conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient to worſhip the <hi>Sun</hi> or <hi>Moon,</hi> or <hi>Stars,</hi> or any <hi>Repreſentation</hi> of them here below.</q>
            </p>
            <p>This would be an Admirable <hi>Paraphraſe,</hi> and which I doubt not but our <hi>Author</hi> would be able to make good againſt all thoſe that <hi>neither do, nor can, nor ought to underſtand</hi> theſe things. But whether our <hi>Nobility</hi> and <hi>Men</hi> of <hi>Quality</hi> are willing to come into this Number I think I need not ſay.</p>
            <p n="3">3. But becauſe to <hi>Created Beings</hi> he afterwards adds <hi>Mortal Ones,</hi> of which more hereafter, I ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe he means <hi>Reaſonable Beings,</hi> let us ſee how things will go upon theſe <hi>new Terms.</hi> 
               <q>
                  <hi>Dearly Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved,</hi> if ever you ſhould worſhip <hi>Saturn</hi> or <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piter,</hi> or ſuch like men who died long ſince, ſtill remember that they were once <hi>Viſible</hi> and <hi>Mortal Men,</hi> and have a care not to worſhip them as the <hi>Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme God.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>I mention here only dead <hi>Heathens,</hi> there being yet no <hi>Chriſtian Hero's</hi> in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s time to whom any ſuch worſhip was given, nor for ſome <hi>Ages</hi>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:99012:19"/>after. Now I think this will paſs as little as the Other with <hi>Men</hi> that <hi>ought</hi> and <hi>do underſtand.</hi> For beſides the barbarous Stuff which this <hi>Notion</hi> makes the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> to ſpeak, it preſſes a meer <hi>Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter</hi> upon us; That the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> ſuppoſes it utterly impoſſible for a <hi>Chriſtian</hi> that does not at once re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce his whole <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Profeſſion,</hi> to be guilty of <hi>Idolatry.</hi> St. <hi>Paul</hi> certainly was a very deep man in hiding his purpoſe, if by intreating the <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians</hi> to <hi>Flee from Idolatry,</hi> he meant no other thing than that they ſhould not <hi>take</hi> and <hi>worſhip</hi> the <hi>Sun,</hi> or the <hi>Moon,</hi> or ſome <hi>dead man,</hi> as the <hi>Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme God.</hi> And our <hi>Author</hi> is as deep a Man in finding out this hidden purpoſe of the <hi>Apoſtle,</hi> which till He aroſe no man was ever ſo happy as to do.</p>
            <p>But indeed with all his <hi>Rhetorick</hi> he will never make <hi>himſelf</hi> and the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> of <hi>One mind</hi> in this matter. For thus St. <hi>Paul</hi> goes on: <q>
                  <hi>Ye cannot drink the Cup of the Lord and the Cup of Devils; Ye cannot be Partakers of the Lord's Table, and of the Table of Devils. Do we provoke the Lord to Jealouſie?</hi>
               </q> 
               <hi>Are we ſtronger than He?</hi> Now if they who partake in <hi>Idolatrous Sacrifices</hi> are <hi>Idolaters,</hi> and if <hi>Idolaters</hi> have no <hi>Senſe</hi> of a <hi>Supreme God,</hi> above the pretended <hi>Deities</hi> to whom they offer, they will not I conceive care one <hi>Jot</hi> whether they <hi>partake of the Lord's Table</hi> or not, nor be concerned about the <hi>Lord's Jealouſie</hi> at all. And yet St. <hi>Paul</hi> plainly ſuppoſes, that if <hi>Chriſtians</hi> ſhould be guilty of <hi>Idolatry,</hi> they would yet probably be concern'd about <hi>God's Jealouſie,</hi> and deſire to <hi>partake of the Lord's Table.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:99012:20"/>
            <p>Thus when the ſame <hi>Apoſtle</hi> wrote to the very ſame <hi>Perſons not to keep Company, no nor ſo much as to eat with One called a</hi> Brother, <hi>if he were a For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicator, or Covetous, or an IDOLATER, or a Rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler, or a Drunkard.</hi> I cannot but wonder what an <hi>Idolater</hi> has to do in this Company, if this <hi>Author's Idolater,</hi> and St. <hi>Paul's Idolater</hi> were the ſame <hi>Idolater.</hi> For whatſoever the <hi>Fornicator,</hi> or <hi>Covetous,</hi> or <hi>Railer,</hi> or <hi>Drunkard,</hi> might pretend for a Title to <hi>Brotherhood;</hi> I am yet certain, that he is fallen even from all right to that <hi>Name,</hi> who <hi>worſhips</hi> the <hi>Sun</hi> (for inſtance) as the <hi>Supreme God,</hi> and ſo renounces <hi>God</hi> the <hi>Maker</hi> of the <hi>World,</hi> and the Father of our <hi>Lord Jeſus Christ.</hi> St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaks of his <hi>Idolater</hi> as One within the <hi>Church,</hi> and One of thoſe wicked Perſons that were to be caſt out of the <hi>Civil</hi> as well as the <hi>Religious Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion</hi> of it. But if there be no <hi>Idolater</hi> beſides this <hi>Author's Idolater,</hi> who has renounced the <hi>Maker</hi> of <hi>Heaven</hi> and <hi>Earth,</hi> and loſt all <hi>Apprehenſion</hi> of him, he has prevented the <hi>Apoſtle's</hi> direction, and is out of the <hi>Church</hi> by his own <hi>Act.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. Theſe things do, I confeſs, give me a great <hi>Prejudice</hi> againſt this <hi>Author's true and only Notion of Idolatry.</hi> And there is one thing which I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve will make him leſs fond of it <hi>himſelf,</hi> when he comes to conſider it; and that is, that his <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> does by no means ſuit with the <hi>Senſe</hi> of that <hi>Church,</hi> to which he deſigned a good Turn in all this. It is very well known how the <hi>Fathers</hi> of <hi>Trent,</hi> to Vindicate their <hi>Worſhip</hi> of <hi>Images</hi> from being <hi>Parallel</hi> to what the <hi>Gentiles</hi> heretofore paid
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:99012:20"/>to theirs, did, among other Differences, lay down this for one: <q>
                  <hi>That they do not believe any Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity or Vertue to be in them, for which they ought to be Worſhipped.</hi>
               </q> For to believe this, their <hi>Catechiſm</hi> tells us, is to make the <hi>Images</hi> become <hi>Idols,</hi> and by conſequence, the <hi>Worſhip</hi> of them to be <hi>Idolatry.</hi> Now if it be <hi>Idolatry</hi> to worſhip <hi>Images</hi> with ſuch an <hi>Opinion,</hi> then it cannot be the <hi>only Notion</hi> of <hi>Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry</hi> to <hi>worſhip</hi> the <hi>Sun, Moon,</hi> or <hi>Stars,</hi> or any <hi>Corporeal Deity, as the Supream God,</hi> or their <hi>Images</hi> as the <hi>Images</hi> of a pretended <hi>Supreme God:</hi> For without a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing of all this, one may believe <hi>Divinity</hi> and <hi>Virtue</hi> to be in <hi>Images,</hi> and <hi>worſhip</hi> them upon that account.</p>
            <p>For Example: The <hi>Heathens</hi> had a mighty O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion of <hi>Aeſculapius</hi> after his Death, that in his <hi>Temples,</hi> and by his <hi>Images,</hi> he could cure Diſeaſes. Let us ſuppoſe now a Perſon to fall <hi>down</hi> and <hi>worſhip</hi> one of theſe <hi>Images,</hi> in hopes of ſome <hi>Divine Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue</hi> coming thence. Were this Worſhip <hi>Idolatry,</hi> or not? If it were not, then was the <hi>Council</hi> of <hi>Trent</hi> to blame, to make this an inſtance of the <hi>Gentiles Idolatry;</hi> if it were, then in the opinion of the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Church,</hi> the account of <hi>Idolatry</hi> which this <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor</hi> has given, cannot be the <hi>only Notion</hi> of it: For this was neither the Worſhipping of any <hi>Corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>real Deity,</hi> as the <hi>Supream God,</hi> nor of any <hi>Corporeal Image</hi> of the <hi>Supream God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Laſtly, In all the Accounts which the <hi>Miſſionaries</hi> of the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi> have given us of the <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then Nations</hi> where they have come, we find them generally acknowledging a <hi>Supream, Spiritual,</hi> and <hi>Inviſible Godhead.</hi> And that if they worſhip the Sun,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:99012:21"/>Moon, or Stars, it is not that they eſteem them to be meer Viſible and Corporeal Deities, much leſs think them to be the <hi>Supream God, ſo as to exclude all ſenſe and apprehenſion of a Spiritual and Inviſible God above them;</hi> but they worſhip them either as inferiour Deities, to whom God has committed the <hi>Government</hi> of the <hi>World</hi> under him; or they look upon <hi>God</hi> to be the <hi>Soul of the World,</hi> and that therefore the <hi>parts</hi> of it deſerve <hi>Honour</hi> upon that account: or finally, they eſteem <hi>God</hi> to be of ſo great <hi>Perfection</hi> and <hi>Excellency,</hi> that He is above their <hi>ſervice,</hi> and that therefore they ought to pay their <hi>External Adoration</hi> to ſomewhat <hi>below him.</hi> Now I ſhall leave it to this <hi>Author</hi> to conſider up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on what <hi>grounds,</hi> according to his <hi>True and Only Notion of Idolatry,</hi> he will charge theſe men with this <hi>Guilt;</hi> or if out of his great <hi>Charity</hi> he ſhall think fit generouſly to acquit them of it, I will then ſend him to ſome of his Friends of the <hi>Roman Communion</hi> for better Inſtruction.</p>
            <p>Theſe and many other <hi>Reaſons,</hi> that I might add, occur to me upon the very firſt view only, to make me ſuſpect his <hi>Hypotheſis.</hi> But now when I exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine it more particularly, I find it yet more groſs and unreaſonable. The ſum of what he offers for it, is an <hi>Hiſtorical Deduction</hi> of the State of <hi>Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try</hi> in the <hi>Old Teſtament,</hi> compar'd with the Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts that are given of the <hi>Idolatry</hi> of the <hi>Ancient,</hi> eſpecially the <hi>Eaſtern Nations,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pag. 99, 100.</note> 
               <q>Who acknowledged no other Deities, but the Stars, among whom the Sun was Supream; in oppoſition to which falſe Principle, <hi>Rabbi Maimon</hi> ſays, God enacted the <hi>Law of Moſes.</hi> And according to this <hi>Law,</hi> it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:99012:21"/>That Idolatry is giving the Worſhip of the <hi>Supream God</hi> to any <hi>Created,
<note place="margin">Pag. 80, 81.</note> Corporeal,</hi> or <hi>Viſible Deity,</hi> or any thing that can be repreſented by an <hi>I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage,</hi> which nothing but <hi>Corporeal</hi> Beings can; and to ſuppoſe <hi>ſuch a Being the Supream Deity,</hi> in the only <hi>true</hi> and <hi>proper Idolatry.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>In oppoſition to which poſitive <hi>Coneluſion,</hi> I will content my ſelf at preſent to ſay, that there is not one word of truth in it; for that neither was the <hi>Religion</hi> of the <hi>Eaſtern Nations,</hi> ſuch as he pretends, nor the <hi>Nature of Idolatry</hi> under the <hi>Law,</hi> what he repreſents it to have been. And to the end I may plainly clear this whole matter, I will diſtinctly ſhew three things.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>First,</hi> That the <hi>Idolatry</hi> of thoſe Nations whom he mentions, the <hi>Egyptians, Chaldeans, Perſians, Ara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bians,</hi> &amp;c. did not conſiſt in Worſhipping the <hi>Sun, Moon,</hi> and <hi>Stars,</hi> as the <hi>Supream God; So as to exclude all ſenſe</hi> and <hi>apprehenſion</hi> of a <hi>Spiritual and Inviſible Godhead. Nor therefore,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> Was this the <hi>only Idolatry</hi> forbidden to the <hi>Jews</hi> by the <hi>Law.</hi> But</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> That as the <hi>Jews</hi> retaining both the <hi>appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion</hi> and <hi>worſhip</hi> of the <hi>God of Iſrael,</hi> were yet guilty of Idolatry for worſhipping him after a <hi>gentile manner,</hi> ſo may <hi>Chriſtians</hi> be now.</p>
            <p>And therefore that the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi> may juſtly be charged by us as <hi>Idolatrous,</hi> though we do not pretend in any wiſe to ſay either that ſhe worſhips the <hi>Sun, Moon,</hi> and <hi>Stars,</hi> or any other <hi>Viſible</hi> and <hi>Corporeal Deity</hi> as the Supream God; or that ſhe has
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:99012:22"/>loſt all <hi>Apprehenſion of a Spiritual and Inviſible God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And thus having eſtabliſhed the <hi>true Notion</hi> of <hi>Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry,</hi> I ſhall laſt of all conſider ſuch <hi>Objections</hi> as may be neceſſary to be replied to for the clearing of it; and ſo leave the <hi>particular Charges</hi> to be made good by thoſe who ſhall have occaſion ſo to do.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="chapter">
            <pb n="25" facs="tcp:99012:22"/>
            <head>CHAP. III. <hi>Of the</hi> Idolatry <hi>of the</hi> Ancient Heathens; <hi>eſpecially, of the</hi> Chaldeans, Egyptians, <hi>and</hi> Perſians; <hi>and that it did not conſiſt in their Worſhipping the</hi> Sun, Moon <hi>and</hi> Stars, <hi>or any other</hi> Viſible <hi>and</hi> Corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>real Deity, as the Supreme God; <hi>ſo as to exclude all</hi> Senſe <hi>and</hi> Apprehenſion <hi>of a Spiritual and Inviſible Godhead.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THis is the <hi>Fundamental miſtake</hi> of our <hi>Author</hi> concerning his <hi>Notion</hi> of <hi>Idolatry;</hi> and which being overthrown, his whole <hi>Hypotheſis</hi> built upon it, muſt fall together with it.
<note place="margin">P. 80.</note> For thus it is that he ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gues: <q>God deſigned by his <hi>Law,</hi> to preſerve the <hi>Jews</hi> from falling into the Idolatry of the Nations round about them: Againſt this,
<note place="margin">P. 102.</note> we find not only all its <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts,</hi> but even the <hi>Rights</hi> and <hi>Ceremonies</hi> of it, to have been directed. But the <hi>Idolatry</hi> of thoſe Nations was no other than the <hi>Worſhip</hi> of the <hi>Sun,
<note place="margin">P. 97, 100.</note> Moon</hi> and <hi>Stars,</hi> or of ſome the like <hi>Viſible</hi> and <hi>Corporeal Dei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties,</hi> ſo as to exclude all <hi>Senſe</hi> and <hi>Apprehenſion</hi> of a <hi>Spiritual</hi> and <hi>Inviſible Godhead.</hi> And therefore this muſt be the <hi>true</hi> and <hi>only</hi> Notion of it in the <hi>Old Teſtament.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <pb n="26" facs="tcp:99012:23"/>
            <p>I ſhall hereafter more fully ſhew the weakneſs of this <hi>Proof,</hi> when I come to demonſtrate, That there were two ſorts of <hi>Idolatry</hi> mention'd in thoſe <hi>Holy Scriptures</hi> extreamly different the one from the other. And therefore that tho this were the <hi>true</hi> Notion of <hi>Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry</hi> in one reſpect, yet it would not follow that it was the <hi>only Notion,</hi> by reaſon of the other. And this I ſhall do in the <hi>next Chapter.</hi> My buſineſs at preſent is to ſhew, That what he has thus Confidently laid down, is ſo far from being the <hi>only Notion</hi> of <hi>Idolatry,</hi> that it is indeed no <hi>Notion</hi> of it at all; for that thoſe very <hi>Heathens</hi> whom he inſiſts upon for his Warrant in this matter, were not guilty of ſuch an <hi>Idolatry</hi> as he pretends they were.</p>
            <p>We have already ſeen his <hi>Definition</hi> of <hi>Idolatry,</hi>
               <note place="margin">P. 74.</note> that it is neither more nor leſs than this: <q>
                  <hi>The Worſhip of the Heavenly Bodies, the Sun, the Moon, and the Stars, or any other Viſible and Corporeal Deity, as the Supreme God, ſo as to exclude all Senſe and Apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of a Spiritual and Inviſible Godhead.</hi>
               </q>
               <note place="margin">Ibid.</note> This he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends is the only Scripture Notion of it. <q>
                  <hi>And thus</hi> (he ſays) <hi>all Learned Men of all Nations,
<note place="margin">P. 99.</note> all Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gions, ever underſtood the old Notion of Idolatry, till this laſt Age, when Folly and Paſſion caſt it at any thing that peeviſh Men were angry with. So</hi> Rabbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>Mamion, <hi>the most Learned and Judicious of the Jew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſh Doctors Diſcourſes at large, That the Ancient Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry was nothing but the Religion of the</hi> Eaſtern Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,
<note place="margin">P. 100.</note> 
                  <hi>who acknowledg no other Deities but the Stars, among whom the Sun was Supreme.</hi>
               </q> And then he immediately ſubjoyns, <q>
                  <hi>That the Ancient Heathens worſhipped only the Stars,
<note place="margin">Ibid.</note> without any Notion of He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roes or Daemons:</hi> So <hi>Diodorus Siculus</hi> ſays of the
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:99012:23"/>
                  <hi>Egyptians; Herodotus</hi> of the <hi>Perſians</hi> and <hi>Chaldeans; Strabo</hi> and <hi>Juſtin,</hi> of the <hi>Arabians,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">P. 101.</note> and <hi>Caeſar</hi> of the <hi>Germans.</hi> He confeſſes indeed, That there was ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſort of <hi>Idolatry</hi> introduced afterward, the <hi>Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip</hi> of <hi>Men</hi> and <hi>Women;</hi> but this he takes to have been much more <hi>Modern, and a meer Invention of the vain and lying</hi> Greeks; but that whenſoever it <hi>came in, it was grafted upon the old Stock, of giving the Worſhip of the Supreme God, not only to created, but to mortal Beings.</hi>
               </q> So this <hi>Author.</hi> To which I Reply.</p>
            <p n="1">I. That as to this <hi>latter ſort</hi> of <hi>Idolatry,</hi> ſeeing he has declin'd the Conſideration of it, as being of too young a date to found the <hi>Scripture Notion</hi> of <hi>Idolatry</hi> upon it, I ſhall not inſiſt upon it; tho I am by no means ſatisfied, either in his account of its <hi>Antiquity,</hi> or that it was <hi>a meer Invention of the vain and lying</hi> Greeks. For</p>
            <p n="1">1. It has been the Opinion of very Learned Men, that this kind of <hi>Idolatry</hi> was practiſed in <hi>Egypt</hi> ſoon after the Flood. And that the moſt Ancient <hi>Oſiris,</hi>
               <note place="margin">See <hi>Voſſius</hi> de Idol. l. 1. c. 27.</note> was no other than <hi>Mitzraim,</hi> the Son of <hi>Cham,</hi> whom they worſhipped together with his Father, and from whom the whole Country is in <hi>Scripture</hi> called by his <hi>Name.</hi> In the cv. <hi>Pſalm</hi> 23. it is expreſly ſtiled, <hi>the Land of Cham:</hi> And <hi>Plutarch</hi> informs us,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Plutarch</hi> de Iſide &amp; Ofiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de.</note> that in the Sacred Rites of <hi>Iſis,</hi> they call it <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, very probably upon the ſame Account. And that which makes this the more likely is, that in the Diviſion of the World among the Sons of <hi>Noah,</hi> Gen. x. <hi>Arabia</hi> fell to the Lot of <hi>Cham;</hi> and in that <hi>Chuſh</hi> his eldeſt Son fixed himſelf, from whence the Country is called, <hi>the Land
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:99012:24"/>of Cuſh,</hi> in 2 <hi>Kings</hi> xix. 9. And then it may eaſily be conceiv'd that his ſecond Son <hi>Mitzraim,</hi> ſhould go into the next adjoyning Country, the Land of <hi>Egypt.</hi> Now if this be ſo, then it follows, not only that this ſort of <hi>Idolatry</hi> was much more Ancient than is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended; but that being practiſed in <hi>Egypt</hi> before the Children of <hi>Iſraels</hi> going down thither; it may be reaſonably enough allow'd a ſufficient Antiquity for us to derive ſomething from it of the <hi>Notion</hi> of <hi>Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try,</hi> with reference to the times under debate. But,</p>
            <p n="2">2dly, As to the very <hi>Apis</hi> its ſelf, the chief Deity of the <hi>Egyptians,</hi> and whom our <hi>Author</hi> contends to have been the <hi>Sun;</hi>
               <note place="margin">P. 89.</note> it is not improbable, but that they meant no other than the Patriarch <hi>Joſeph</hi> by it; and whom they <hi>Honour'd</hi> with <hi>Divine Honours,</hi> upon the Account of his wonderful Preſervation of them in the <hi>ſeven years Famine,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Jul. Firm. p. 17, 18.</note> Gen. xli. Thus <hi>Julius Firmicus</hi> expreſly Interprets it, and what is more, adds, that this was according to the manner of their Country: <q>
                  <hi>The</hi> Egyp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians (ſays he) <hi>after his Death, according to the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment of their Country, built Temples to Him.</hi> And again,</q> 
               <hi>This Man is worſhipt in</hi> Egypt, <hi>he is adored,</hi> &amp;c.
<note place="margin">Ruffin. l. 2. Hiſt. Eccleſ. c. 23.</note> To him <hi>Ruffinus</hi> agrees; and St. <hi>Auguſtin,</hi> or whoever elſe was the Author of that Book under his Name, <hi>De Mirabilibus Scripturae,</hi> informs us, <q>That the <hi>Egyptians</hi> upon this account, ſet up the <hi>Symbol</hi> of an <hi>Ox</hi> over the Sepulchre of <hi>Joſeph,</hi> in Memory of their Deliverance.</q>
               <note place="margin">Suidas in voce <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Cl. Alex. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. 1.</note> Thus <hi>Suidas</hi> interprets their <hi>Serapis;</hi> who as <hi>Clemens Alexandrinus</hi> (out of <hi>Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteas</hi>) tells us, was the ſame with <hi>Apis;</hi> and both <hi>Suidas, Ruffinus,</hi> and <hi>Julius Firmicus,</hi> add, that his Statue was ſet up with a <hi>Buſhel</hi> upon his Head, to denote the <hi>Plenty of Corn</hi> which he provided for them.
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:99012:24"/>And in the very Scripture it ſelf, <hi>Joſeph</hi> is either call'd, or at leaſt compar'd to an <hi>Ox,</hi> Deut. xxxiii. 17. And ſome of the <hi>Rabbins</hi> have given this account of the very <hi>Calves</hi> of <hi>Jeroboam,</hi> that they were the Symbols of <hi>Joſeph,</hi> ſet up by him in Honour of his Anceſtors, from a part of whoſe <hi>Tribe, viz.</hi> that of <hi>Ephraim,</hi> he was himſelf deſcended.</p>
            <p>Here it were an eaſie matter to multiply Proofs upon this occaſion, to ſhew that the <hi>Idolatry</hi> of Conſecrating <hi>Heroes</hi> into Gods, and Worſhipping them as ſuch, is by no means of ſo freſh a date, as this <hi>Author</hi> would have it thought to be. For what he adds,
<note place="margin">Page 101.</note> 
               <hi>That when<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever</hi> 
               <q>
                  <hi>it came in, it was grafted upon the Old Stock of giving the Worſhip of the Supreme God, not only to Created, but to Mortal Beings:</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>I anſwer, 1. That this is evidently contrary to all the accounts we have of their Worſhip; and accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to which it appears, that the Heathens paid no other Worſhip to their <hi>Divi,</hi> or <hi>deified Men,</hi> than what the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi> at this day does to her <hi>Saints;</hi> but as carefully diſtinguiſh'd between the Adoration of <hi>the Supreme God,</hi> and theſe <hi>Heroes,</hi> as the other do be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween <hi>Him,</hi> and thoſe <hi>Bleſſed Men</hi> that <hi>Reign together with Him,</hi> as their Language tells us.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Whenever this Idolatry came in, 'tis evident that the very nature of it utterly overthrows his <hi>Only No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> of <hi>Idolatry</hi> before laid down; unleſs he ſuppoſes that they thought their <hi>Heroes,</hi> whom whilſt they li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved they knew to be but <hi>men,</hi> born into the World after the common order of Nature, and even dying after the ſame manner as all others, became after Death the <hi>Supreme God</hi> that made <hi>Heaven</hi> and <hi>Earth;</hi> and believed all this ſo firmly, as not only to give the <hi>Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip</hi>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:99012:25"/>of the <hi>Supreme God</hi> to them, but to exclude all <hi>Senſe</hi> and <hi>Apprehenſion</hi> of any <hi>God</hi> above them. For ſo (<hi>he</hi> ſays) a man muſt do, before he can be guilty of <hi>Idolatry.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now if this be his Opinion, I would then ask this <hi>Learned Antiquary</hi> one ſmall <hi>Queſtion:</hi> Seeing the Num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of their <hi>Heroes</hi> was very great, whom the ſame Perſons at the ſame time worſhipped; Did they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve every one of theſe to be the <hi>Supreme God</hi> that made <hi>Heaven</hi> and <hi>Earth,</hi> and give the higheſt <hi>Divine Honour</hi> accordingly unto every one of them as ſuch? That they did this, no man of Senſe will either ſay or believe; and yet if they did not, the <hi>true</hi> and <hi>only Notion</hi> of <hi>Idolatry</hi> is at an end; for which ever of their <hi>Heroes</hi> they believed to be the <hi>Supreme God,</hi> and <hi>Worſhipped</hi> as ſuch, they muſt have Adored the reſt only as <hi>Inferior Deities,</hi> and with an <hi>Honour</hi> ſuitable to their <hi>Apprehenſions</hi> of them.</p>
            <p>Either therefore he muſt quit his <hi>true</hi> and <hi>only No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> of Idolatry, which he tells us is <hi>neither more nor leſs</hi> than,
<note place="margin">Page 74.</note> 
               <q>The Worſhip of the <hi>Heavenly Bodies,</hi> the <hi>Sun,</hi> the <hi>Moon,</hi> and the <hi>Stars,</hi> or any other <hi>Viſible</hi> and <hi>Corporeal Deity,</hi> as the Supreme God, ſo as to exclude all <hi>Senſe</hi> and <hi>Apprehenſion</hi> of a <hi>Spiritual</hi> and <hi>inviſible Godhead;</hi>
               </q> or he muſt give us ſome aſſurance that the <hi>Egyptians</hi> (for inſtance) worſhipping of <hi>Joſeph</hi> under the <hi>Symbol</hi> of an <hi>Ox,</hi> did believe him to be the <hi>Supreme Deity,</hi> ſo as to exclude all <hi>ſenſe</hi> and <hi>apprehenſion</hi> of any <hi>Superior Godhead,</hi> and did worſhip him accordingly; that is, that thoſe men were ſo ſot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſh as to think that a man who had <hi>lived</hi> and <hi>died</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them, was the <hi>Great God</hi> that framed the world<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and all things in it, many Ages before himſelf had any <hi>Being.</hi> But</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:99012:25"/>II. To come to the <hi>Other,</hi> and (as he ſuppoſes) the more Ancient <hi>Idolatry,</hi> and in his Notion of which, I affirm him to have been utterly miſtaken: And here I muſt obſerve, that it is not at all doubted, but that theſe <hi>Heathens</hi> did Worſhip the <hi>Sun, Moon,</hi> and <hi>Stars;</hi> that which I pretend is, that this <hi>Author</hi> is very much out in the Account which he gives of their <hi>Worſhip</hi> of them.</p>
            <p n="1">1. He affirms,
<note place="margin">Page 74.</note> That they worſhipped theſe <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Bodies</hi> as <hi>Viſible</hi> and <hi>Corporeal Deities,</hi> ſo as to exclude all <hi>ſenſe</hi> and <hi>apprehenſion</hi> of a <hi>Spiritual</hi> and <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſible Godhead:</hi> Whereas on the contrary, they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved theſe <hi>very Bodies themſelves</hi> to be animated by <hi>Celeſtial Spirits</hi> who reſided in them, and rendred them thereby proper <hi>Objects</hi> of their Adoration.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That they worſhipped theſe <hi>Viſible</hi> and <hi>Corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>real</hi> Deities, as the <hi>Supreme God;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ibid.</note> whereas they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly acknowledged a <hi>Firſt</hi> and <hi>Inviſible Godhead, ſuperior</hi> to them.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That they worſhipp'd no <hi>other Gods</hi> but theſe,
<note place="margin">Page 97, 100.</note> and amongſt theſe the <hi>Sun</hi> as <hi>ſupreme;</hi> when on the contrary it is certain, even from the very <hi>Authors</hi> that himſelf produces, that they worſhipp'd <hi>other Dei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties,</hi> both <hi>Heroes</hi> and <hi>Daemons,</hi> of which this Man yet pretends with ſo much aſſurance, that <hi>they had no Notion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And all theſe are not only <hi>groſs Errors</hi> for an <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor</hi> who writes with ſuch Confidence as if he would be thought to have been <hi>initiated</hi> into all the <hi>Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> of which he diſcourſes, but ſuch as utterly ruin all that he has to ſay to ſupport his true and only Notion of Idolatry. But I muſt examine theſe Points more particularly. And</p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:99012:26"/>1. <q>That theſe <hi>Nations</hi> did not worſhip the <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Bodies</hi> as <hi>Viſible</hi> and <hi>Corporeal Deities,</hi> ſo as to exclude all <hi>ſenſe</hi> and <hi>apprehenſion</hi> of a Spiritual and inviſible <hi>Godhead.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>This is an Aſſertion not only ſo monſtrouſly abſurd in its ſelf, but ſo contrary to all the Accounts we have from <hi>Antiquity,</hi> of the <hi>Theology</hi> of thoſe <hi>Nations</hi> to which he refers us, that I muſt once more confeſs, that I never lay under a greater Temptation to disbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve my own <hi>Senſes,</hi> or to ſuſpect my underſtanding of plain words than now: On the one hand, I am ſure our <hi>Author</hi> here defines <hi>Idolatry</hi> to be, <q>The Worſhip of the <hi>Heavenly Bodies,</hi> the <hi>Sun,</hi> the <hi>Moon,</hi> and the <hi>Stars,</hi> or ſome other viſible and <hi>Corporeal Deity,</hi> not only as the <hi>Supreme God,</hi> but <hi>ſo</hi> at to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude all <hi>ſenſe</hi> and <hi>apprehenſion</hi> of a Spiritual and <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſible Godhead:</hi>
               </q> That is to ſay, that he who is an <hi>Idolater</hi> muſt worſhip them as mere <hi>Corporeal Parts</hi> of the <hi>Creation,</hi> void of all <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding;</hi> for ſo I think Viſible and <hi>Corporeal Gods</hi> muſt be taken, when oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to all <hi>ſenſe</hi> and <hi>apprehenſion</hi> of a Spiritual and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſible <hi>Godhead.</hi> And yet on the other hand, how to reconcile ſuch a <hi>Paradox</hi> with either the <hi>common Reaſon</hi> of <hi>Mankind,</hi> as I have obſerved before; or the clear Evidences of the <hi>Gentile World</hi> to the contrary, as I obſerve now, I am not able to comprehend: But let our <hi>Author</hi> take his choice; for I will here again do more than I need, rather than be thought to omit any thing that was fit to be taken notice of. If he thinks good to own this Notion, I will then offer what may ſerve to confute it; but if being admoniſhed of the <hi>Abſurdity</hi> of it, he ſhall chuſe rather to wreſt his words to ſome other meaning than they naturally bear, I
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:99012:26"/>ſhall only have ſpent ſome little time in <hi>confuting</hi> that, which if he does not, I am certain no body elſe will ever <hi>affirm.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And to begin where himſelf does, with the <hi>Holy Scriptures,</hi> not only the moſt certain, but the moſt Ancient <hi>Hiſtory</hi> in the <hi>World.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He produces indeed a few Texts from whence it may be concluded, that the <hi>Heathens</hi> of old, did worſhip the <hi>Sun, Moon,</hi> and <hi>Stars;</hi> but that they wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped them (according to his Notion) as <hi>Corporeal Deities,</hi> and ſo as to <hi>exclude all ſenſe and apprehenſion of a Spiritual and Inviſible Godhead;</hi> for this he has not ſo much as offer'd at one ſingle Proof.</p>
            <p>For 1. As to his firſt Inſtance,
<note place="margin">Page 77.</note> (and which indeed is the firſt account we have) of <hi>Idolatry.</hi> The Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, 'tis true, tells us that <hi>Terah, Abraham</hi>'s Father, worſhipped <hi>Strange Gods;</hi> but that theſe <hi>Gods</hi> were Corporeal Deities, and that they worſhipp'd them ſo as to exclude all <hi>ſenſe</hi> and <hi>apprehenſion</hi> of a <hi>Spiritual</hi> and <hi>Inviſible Godhead,</hi> of this there is not a word: See <hi>Joſh.</hi> xxiv. 2. and I ſhall preſently ſhew the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary.</p>
            <p>If we go on with him to the next (and as he thinks the firſt plain) intimation we find of <hi>Idolatry</hi> in <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſtine,</hi> 
               <q>in the Hiſtory of <hi>Jacob;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Page 78.</note> after his Converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion with the <hi>Shechemites,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gen. 35.</note> where upon his departure from that City by God's eſpecial Command, he builds an Altar at <hi>Bethel</hi> to <hi>God,</hi> and commands his Family to put away their <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, or <hi>ſtrange Gods.</hi>
               </q> Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther here ſhall we find our <hi>Author</hi>'s notion ſo much as inſinuated, but as I will now prove, much to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary. It is not to be doubted, but that theſe Gods were the ſame that they worſhipped in <hi>Syria</hi> when they
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:99012:27"/>were in the houſe of <hi>Laban;</hi> and that therefore the Images which <hi>Jacob</hi> buried, could be no other than the <hi>Teraphim,</hi> ſo uſual amongſt them, <hi>i. e.</hi> ſuch as <hi>Rachel</hi> ſtole from her Father <hi>Laban,</hi> Gen. xxxi. 30. How far from hence it might be proved that their <hi>Idolatry</hi> did not conſiſt merely in their worſhipping of the <hi>Sun, Moon,</hi> and <hi>Stars,</hi> I ſhall not now diſpute: Let us ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe theſe <hi>Teraphims</hi> to have been not only made by <hi>Planetary Influences,</hi> but deſigned to repreſent the <hi>Sun,</hi> or ſome other <hi>Heavenly Bodies;</hi> then, I ſay, it follows both from the Hiſtory of <hi>Laban,</hi> and from the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts we have of theſe <hi>Idols,</hi> that they did not wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip the <hi>Sun</hi> as a <hi>Corporeal Deity,</hi> and by conſequence that that cannot be the <hi>true Notion</hi> of their <hi>Idolatry,</hi> which is pretended to be. For,</p>
            <p n="1">1. As to <hi>Laban,</hi> we read <hi>Gen.</hi> xxxi. 53. that when he ratified the Covenant with <hi>Jacob,</hi> he called to witneſs not only the <hi>God of Abraham,</hi> but the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, his own domeſtick Deity too, <hi>i. e.</hi> in our <hi>Author</hi>'s opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, the <hi>Sun,</hi> 
               <q>
                  <hi>The God</hi> (ſays he) <hi>of Abraham, and the God of Nachor judg betwixt us:</hi>
               </q> Now this plainly ſhews that <hi>Laban</hi> lookt upon his <hi>Father's God</hi> (and who was alſo the <hi>God</hi> of <hi>Tera</hi> before-mentioned, <hi>Joſh.</hi> xxiv. 2.) not to be a mere <hi>Corporeal Deity,</hi> but as having an <hi>Intellectual Being</hi> incorporated in it, that was both capable of hearing their <hi>Oath,</hi> and of judging betwixt them, and without which he could never have called him to witneſs their Contract.</p>
            <p n="2">2. For what concerns the <hi>Teraphim,</hi> it appears from Holy Scripture, that the <hi>Chaldeans</hi> made uſe of them not only as <hi>ſymbols</hi> for Worſhip, but for <hi>Oracles</hi> too, and as ſuch, were wont to <hi>conſult</hi> them; it was for this, that <hi>Rachel</hi> is ſuppoſed to have ſtollen away her
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:99012:27"/>Father's <hi>Gods, Gen.</hi> 31. that ſo when he ſhould come, and miſs her husband, he might not be able to <hi>enquire</hi> of them which way to purſue after him. We read in <hi>Ezek.</hi> xxi. 21. <hi>That the King of Babylon conſulted with his Teraphim,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hierom in l. 7. in Ezek. p. 212.</note> which St. <hi>Jerome</hi> calls conſulting with his <hi>Oracle, after the manner of his Country:</hi> And the Prophet <hi>Zachary</hi> x. 2. tells the People, '<hi>That their Teraphim had ſpoken vanity:</hi> Now how could this poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly be, had the <hi>Chaldeans</hi> worſhipped only <hi>Viſible</hi> and <hi>Corporeal Deities?</hi> Is not this an undeniable Evidence, that they acknowledged in the <hi>Heavenly Bodies,</hi> invi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible Spirits to deſcend and influence their <hi>Teraphim,</hi> ſo as to make them ſpeak?</p>
            <p>Many are the accounts that may be given of theſe Idols,
<note place="margin">Voſſius de I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dol. lib. 1. Selden de diis Syris Syntag. 1. c. 2. Dr. Pocock on Hoſea xiii. 2. p. 725.</note> and which have been collected with much exact<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs by thoſe great men, <hi>Gerard Voſſius,</hi> Mr. <hi>Selden,</hi> &amp;c. But I ſhall content my ſelf to ſubjoin the Authority of one only Perſon, now living, and no way inferior to any that can be produced, <q>
                  <hi>It ſeems</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>to have been the Opinion of thoſe Ancient Idolaters, that ſome ſpiritualities from ſuperior Intelligences, and Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Powers, did influence ſuch Images as they made in ſuch Figures as they thought acceptable to them, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicated to them; and therefore called ſuch their Images themſelves God, and thought them ſo, at leaſt</hi> Deos Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carios, <hi>Inferior Deities; Mediators between them and the Superior, and did offer Sacrifice, and burnt Incenſe, that they might draw down and entice (as it were) thoſe ſpiritual Influences to reſide on thoſe Images, that ſo they might declare to them,
<note place="margin">Id. on Hoſea iii. 4.</note> and do for them what they deſired.</hi> And elſewhere he ſays, <hi>That the modern</hi> Za<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bii <hi>not only pretend to ſucceed the old</hi> Chaldees <hi>in their Religion, but that as to their Rites about Teleſms, and
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:99012:28"/>Figures, and Images, we cannot but eaſily believe, that they were derived to them from Ancient Times.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>And now that I mention the <hi>Zabii,</hi> I cannot but obſerve the wonderful acuteneſs of our Author in his Reflections upon them; he calls it <q>
                  <hi>the Dream of the Zabii;</hi>
               </q>
               <note place="margin">Page 76.</note> and he decretorily condemns all that is ſaid by Learned Men on their behalf, merely becauſe <q>
                  <hi>He</hi> (a Perſon ſo acurately verſed in all the Learning of the <hi>Eaſt) can find no Ancient Footſteps of any ſuch people in the world;</hi>
               </q>
               <note place="margin">Pag. 110, 111.</note> and that Dr. <hi>Spencer</hi> has diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver'd for him, <q>
                  <hi>That the name is no older than</hi> Maho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>met, <hi>who call'd them</hi> Zabii, <hi>becauſe they lay Eaſtward from</hi> Arabia;</q> for ſo the word ſignifies, <hi>Eaſterlings.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus this <hi>Author,</hi> and ſtill, as becomes himſelf, he pronounces, <hi>Dictator</hi>-like, and is alway in the wrong; for the Queſtion is not about the name of <hi>Zabii</hi> (which from henceforth muſt ſignifie <hi>Eaſterlings,</hi> tho the Learned Dr. <hi>Spencer</hi> had collected no leſs than <hi>five ſeveral ſignifications</hi> of it,
<note place="margin">De Legib. Heb. l. 2. c. 1. Sect. 1.</note> and every one ſupported by probable <hi>Conjectures);</hi> but about the <hi>People,</hi> or rather the <hi>Religion;</hi> and to draw this matter out of the <hi>Clouds,</hi> and ſhew what an Admirable <hi>Critick</hi> we have got here, it is juſt as if a man ſhould undertake to prove the <hi>Britains</hi> to be a people of no <hi>Antiquity,</hi> becauſe they are now called <hi>Welch,</hi> and that's but a <hi>Modern Name.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now according to this true State of this Matter,
<note place="margin">Spencer ib. l. 2. c. 1. Sect. 2.</note> it is evidently ſhew'd by that <hi>Learned Perſon</hi> I before mentioned, that the Religion of the <hi>Zabii</hi> is not only of no Modern date, but is as Ancient, or even more Ancient than <hi>Abraham. Abulfeda</hi> calls it the <hi>moſt An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Religion;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Dr. Spencer ib. p. 240.</note> and <hi>Saidus Batricides</hi> attributes the Original of the <hi>Zabii,</hi> thus conſider'd, in their Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:99012:28"/>and Superſtitions, to the time of <hi>Nachor,
<note place="margin">De Converſ. Indor. l. 1. c. 4.</note> Abraham</hi>'s Grandfather. To this Subſcribes the Learned and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſitive <hi>Hornbeck;</hi> and who thinks them to be the ſame with thoſe that were anciently called <hi>Sabaei;</hi> and <hi>Abul-Pharajius,</hi> cited by Dr. <hi>Spencer,</hi> thus con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firms it,
<note place="margin">Hiſt. Dynaſt. D. 9. p. 281.</note> 
               <q>
                  <hi>That which we certainly know of the Sect of the</hi> Zabii, <hi>is, that their Profeſſion is altogether the ſame with the Profeſſion of the Ancient</hi> Chaldeans.</q>
            </p>
            <p>As for the point before us;
<note place="margin">Spencer ib. p. 237, 238.</note> we are told that they worſhipped the <hi>Host of Heaven,</hi> ſuppoſing the Stars to be animated by <hi>Divine <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtandings.</hi> Dr. <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cock</hi> adds, <q>That they lookt upon the <hi>Planets,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Not. in ſpec. Hiſt. Arab. p. 143.</note> as Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diators between the Supreme God, and Men; and cites <hi>Gregorius, Abulfaraeus</hi> and <hi>Shareſtanius,</hi> for his War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant; which laſt expreſly ſays,
<note place="margin">Ibid. p. 146.</note> That they worſhip the <hi>Bodies</hi> of the <hi>Planets,</hi> as the <hi>Habitations</hi> of the <hi>living, rational,</hi> and <hi>intellectual Subſtances,</hi> which they ſuppoſe to <hi>animate</hi> them.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Now theſe are all plain and rational Accounts, why they ſhould worſhip theſe <hi>Heavenly Bodies;</hi> but to talk of their worſhipping the <hi>Sun, Moon</hi> and <hi>Stars,</hi> as Viſible and <hi>Corporeal Deities,</hi> and that ſo as to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude all <hi>Senſe</hi> and <hi>Apprehenſion</hi> of a <hi>Spiritual</hi> and <hi>Inviſible Godhead,</hi> is to repreſent their Worſhip con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary not only to <hi>Truth,</hi> but to <hi>common Senſe</hi> and <hi>Reaſon</hi> too. But when Men are reſolved to advance ſuch Notions, as this <hi>Author</hi> does, they muſt have <hi>Proofs</hi> of the ſame kind. And this for the <hi>Chalde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As to the <hi>Egyptians, Jamblicus</hi> informs us,
<note place="margin">Jamblic. de Myſter. Sect. 37.</note> That they worſhipped indeed the <hi>Sun, Moon</hi> and <hi>Stars,</hi> as <hi>Viſible Gods;</hi> but ſuch as were compounded of <hi>Soul</hi> and <hi>Body,</hi> and they eſteem'd thoſe Planets to be <hi>Seats</hi>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:99012:29"/>only of thoſe <hi>Coeleſtial Spirits</hi> that were to take care of human Affairs.</p>
            <p>It was a nice Queſtion put by <hi>Porphyry,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Id. Sect. 1. c. 17.</note> to an <hi>Egyp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian Prieſt,</hi> 
               <q>
                  <hi>How the Sun, Moon and Stars could be Gods, ſeeing the Gods are incorporeal?</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Jamblicus</hi> anſwers, <q>
                  <hi>That the incorporeal Gods aſſume thoſe Bodies, by which they become Viſible.</hi>
               </q> And <hi>Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rianus</hi> aſſerts,
<note place="margin">Syrian. in Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taphyſ. l. 12.</note> The <hi>Coeleſtial Animals</hi> (as he calls them) <q>to be the Images of the Maker of the World, and to communicate Senſe to it.</q>
            </p>
            <p>But it may be ſaid, That theſe were <hi>Philoſophers,</hi> and endeavour'd to make the beſt of their <hi>Idolatry.</hi> I anſwer,
<note place="margin">Jambl. de My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter. Sect. c. 1.</note> That <hi>Jamblicus</hi> declares, he delivers nothing but according to the <hi>old</hi> Egyptian <hi>Books:</hi> And he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livers it for the true <hi>Egyptian Theology;</hi> That there was one Supreme God above all;
<note place="margin">Cap. 2.</note> next him the <hi>Demiur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gus;</hi> the third Principle he calls <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and ſome think the <hi>Sun</hi> is meant by it, as the <hi>immediate Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernor of the World.</hi> If ſo, there is great Reaſon why the <hi>Sun</hi> ſhould be worſhipped under the Names of <hi>Moloch</hi> and <hi>Baal,</hi> as being King and Lord of this <hi>infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rior World.</hi> And thus neither did the <hi>Egyptians</hi> wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip theſe <hi>Heavenly</hi> Bodies, ſo as to <hi>exclude all Senſe of a Spiritual and Inviſible Godhead.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If from both theſe Nations we paſs finally to the <hi>Perſians,
<note place="margin">Gol. not. in Alferg. p. 20, 21.</note> Jac. Golius</hi> will give us the very ſame Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of them, <hi>viz.</hi> That the Ancient <hi>Perſians</hi> did worſhip <hi>Coeleſtial Spirits,</hi> as having a particular preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dency over the material part of the World.</p>
            <p>And now, after ſo many plain Teſtimonies in this matter, were it yet needful to look into any <hi>other Countries,</hi> we ſhould find the Caſe to be every where the ſame.
<note place="margin">Pliny l. 2. c. 6.</note> 
               <hi>Pliny</hi> pleads much for the Divinity of the
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:99012:29"/>
               <hi>Sun;</hi> but do's he believe it to be a <hi>Viſible</hi> and <hi>Corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>real Deity,</hi> ſo as to exclude any <hi>Inviſible</hi> and <hi>Spiritual Godhead?</hi> No, on the contrary, he calls it the <hi>Spirit and Mind of the World.</hi> He attributes Senſe and Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding to it; and affirms from <hi>Homer, That it ſees and hears all.</hi> And indeed this is ſo often inſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon by that <hi>Poet,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Euſtath. in Homer, Odyſſ. T. p. 1871. In Iliad. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> p. 414.</note> that <hi>Euſtathius</hi> from thence ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves, that the <hi>Sun</hi> was to be conſider'd not only as a <hi>Luminary</hi> of the <hi>Heavens,</hi> but as a <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a <hi>Spirit cloathed with ſuch an illuſtrious</hi> Body. And in another place he takes notice of the decency of <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer,</hi> That he calls the <hi>heavenly Powers</hi> to be Witneſſes of <hi>Oaths,</hi> and particularly the <hi>Sun.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> — <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>,</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>,</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</l>
            </q>
            <p>So little Truth is there in this firſt of our Authors Pretence, <hi>'That the Ancients did Worſhip the Sun, the Moon, and the Stars, as Viſible and Coporeal Deities, ſo as to exclude all Senſe and Apprehenſion of a Spiritual and Inviſible Godhead.</hi> Let us ſee</p>
            <p n="2">2dly,
<note place="margin">P. 97.</note> Whether they who worſhipp'd theſe <hi>Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nets,</hi> look'd upon them as the <hi>Supreme Deities,</hi> ſo as not to acknowledg any Divinity above them.</p>
            <p>And here it muſt be confeſs'd,
<note place="margin">Mor. Nevoch. l. 3. c. 29.</note> he has at leaſt an <hi>appearance of Truth.</hi> For, as for the <hi>Chaldeans, Mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monides</hi> tells us of the Ancient <hi>Zabii, That they had no other Gods but the Stars;</hi> and that among them,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:99012:30"/>they look'd upon the <hi>Sun</hi> as Supreme.
<note place="margin">Hornbeck de Converſ. Ind. l. 1. c. 4. Pocock Not. in Spec. Hiſt. Ar. p. 139.</note> From whence our Learned <hi>Pocock</hi> ſeems to think it not far from the Truth, to ſay, that poſſibly they derived their very Name of <hi>Zabii; Saba</hi> in the <hi>Hebrew,</hi> ſignifying an Hoſt, as if one ſhould ſay, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, Worſhippers <hi>of the Hoſt of Heaven.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſame is the Account which <hi>Sanchoniathon,</hi> men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned both by <hi>Euſebius</hi> and St. <hi>Cyril,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Euſeb. Praep. Evan. l. 1. c. 9. p. 30. Cyril. contr. Jul. l. 6. p. 205. c.</note> gives of the <hi>Phaenicians,</hi> 
               <q>
                  <hi>That they worſhipped the</hi> Sun, Moon <hi>and</hi> Stars, <hi>as the only immortal Gods, among which the</hi> Sun <hi>was chief, called by them</hi> Beth-Samen, Lord of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven.</q> And for the <hi>Perſians, Herodotus</hi> tells us, That the <hi>Sun</hi> was their only God:
<note place="margin">Herodot. l. 1.</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; to which <hi>Strabo</hi> and <hi>Trogus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Strabo l. 11. Trogus apud Juſtinum l. 1. vid. Voſſ. de Joel. l. 2. c. 9.</note> in <hi>Juſtin,</hi> aſſent. And <hi>Heſychius,</hi> tho he rejects this, yet acknowledges him to be the firſt or ſupreme God amongſt them <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> (ſays he) <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. All which ſeems to be confirm'd by thoſe Ancient Inſcriptions collected by <hi>Gruterus</hi> and others,
<note place="margin">Apud Voſſ. loc. cit. vid. Hornb. de Con. Ind. p. 19. Elmen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horſt. in Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nob. p. 27, &amp;c.</note>
               <q>
                  <l>
                     <hi>DEO SOLI INVICTO. OMNIPOTENTI DEO.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And again, <hi>SOLI INVICTO &amp; L<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>NAE AETERNAE.</hi>
                  </l>
               </q> from all which it may be thought to follow, that (as this <hi>Author</hi> here tells us) the <hi>Gods</hi> which thoſe Ancient <hi>Heathens</hi> worſhipped,
<note place="margin">P. 97.</note> were <hi>nothing but the Heavenly Bodies, or the</hi> Sun <hi>as the ſupreme Deity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But yet if we enquire more exactly into theſe things, we ſhall find their Worſhip to have been much other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe than what at firſt ſight it appears to be; for to begin with thoſe I laſt named, the <hi>Perſians;</hi> and than whom none have been more famed for <hi>Adoring</hi> the Sun:
<note place="margin">De Iſide &amp; Oſiride.</note> 
               <hi>Plutarch</hi> tells us that they had a Notion of a
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:99012:30"/>
               <hi>Deity</hi> whom they call'd <hi>Oromaſdes,</hi> ſuperior to him, and the Account of whom (derived to them from <hi>Zoroaſter</hi>) he thus delivers to us. They believed that there were two contrary <hi>Principles,</hi> the one <hi>Good,</hi> the other <hi>Evil.</hi> The former of theſe they called <hi>Oromaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des,</hi> whom they alſo look'd upon as the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or <hi>Creator,</hi> as <hi>Agathias</hi> informs us; the other <hi>Arimanius.</hi> Between theſe two, they placed their <hi>Mithras,</hi> or the <hi>Sun,</hi> who was eſteem'd by them, as much Inferior to <hi>Oromaſdes,</hi> as Superior to <hi>Arimanius.</hi> To this <hi>Oro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſdes,</hi> they aſcribed the Creation of the <hi>Stars,</hi> and of the <hi>Good Gods,</hi> thus <hi>Plutarch:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Photius Cod. 81.</note> But <hi>Photius</hi> carries it yet a little further in his Account of a Book writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten by <hi>Theodorus,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Moveſtia,</hi> concerning the <hi>Perſian Rites,</hi> he ſays, That they believed the firſt Principle of all, to be <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and that he begat the other two, which with ſome little difference, he calls <hi>Ormiſdas</hi> and <hi>Satan.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But not to inſiſt upon theſe Accounts:
<note place="margin">Jac. Golius Not. in Alferg. p. 20.</note> We are told by a Learned Man in his Notes upon <hi>Alferganus,</hi> that the <hi>Perſians</hi> gave the Names of their <hi>Gods</hi> to their <hi>Months</hi> and <hi>Days,</hi> according to the Ancient Religion of the <hi>Perſians</hi> and <hi>Magi,</hi> whereby they did believe their <hi>Gods</hi> to preſide over them; it being a Principle amongſt them, as well as among all other <hi>Nations</hi> of the <hi>East,</hi> that the things of this lower World are adminiſtred by <hi>Angels.</hi> The Spirit over the <hi>Sun,</hi> they called <hi>Mihr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gian,</hi> from <hi>Mitro</hi> the <hi>Sun.</hi> But above all thoſe, they believed there was one <hi>Supreme God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Eubulus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Porphyr. de antro Nym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pharum.</note> who wrote the Hiſtory of <hi>Mithras</hi> (which was extant in St. <hi>Jeromes</hi> time) hath given a particular Account of the Cave which <hi>Zoroaſter</hi> made in honour of another and ſuperior <hi>Mithras,</hi> the Father and Maker
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:99012:31"/>of the World. Even <hi>Herodotus</hi> himſelf, whom this Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor ſo confidently produces for his Warrant (but cites no particular paſſage of him) diſtinguiſhes their <hi>Jupi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> from the <hi>Sun,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Herod. Clio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n. 131. p. 56.</note> and ſays, by it they underſtood the whole Heaven in which the <hi>Sun</hi> is fixt; and ſacrificed to him diſtinctly from the other.
<note place="margin">Strabo l. 15. p. 503.</note> And ſo does <hi>Strabo,</hi> another of his <hi>Authors: Xenophon</hi> often mentions a <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as a Deity ſuperior to the <hi>Sun;</hi> eſpecially, where ſpeaking of <hi>Cyrus</hi> being admoniſhed in a Dream of his approaching Death,
<note place="margin">See Dr. Cud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worth. l. 1. c. 4.</note> he tell us, that he ſacrificed to his <hi>Country Jupiter</hi> firſt, and then to the <hi>Sun:</hi> And <hi>Plutarch</hi> brings in <hi>Darius</hi> in like manner addreſſing to him, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>Thou our Country</hi> Jupiter, <hi>or Supreme God of the</hi> Perſians.</p>
            <p>I might add here,
<note place="margin">See Dr Still. Anſw. to T. G. p. 110.</note> That the ſame is the Opinion of thoſe <hi>Perſees,</hi> who ſtick to their Ancient Religion at this day. But theſe have been already collected by a very Eminent Hand. I ſhall conclude, therefore, with the form of that <hi>Proclamation,</hi> which <hi>Cyrus</hi> gave in favour of the <hi>Jews,</hi> and by which it plainly appears that they believed the ſame Firſt and Soveraign Deity with our ſelves, Ezra i. 2. <hi>Thus ſaith</hi> Cyrus <hi>King of</hi> Perſia, <hi>The Lord God of Heaven hath given me all Kingdoms of the Earth, and hath charged me to build him a Houſe at</hi> Jeruſalem. And in the next Verſe, he calls the ſame <hi>God, The Lord God of</hi> Iſrael. And I hope this Author will not ſay that was the <hi>Sun,</hi> or any other <hi>Viſible</hi> and <hi>Corporeal Deity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I have enlarged my ſelf the more on this part of Antiquity, becauſe the <hi>Perſians,</hi> if any, muſt have been found to worſhip the <hi>Sun,</hi> as the <hi>Supreme God.</hi> I ſhall be very ſhort in other Nations, and ſo cloſe this Conſideration.</p>
            <pb n="43" facs="tcp:99012:31"/>
            <p>And for what concerns the <hi>Egyptians,</hi> I have already given ſome Account of their <hi>Theology;</hi> and we may learn from thence, how it came to paſs, that the <hi>Sun</hi> (whom none of the <hi>Heathens</hi> looked upon as abſolutely the <hi>ſupreme</hi> and <hi>higheſt Being</hi>) is yet ſo often ſpoken of by them as ſuch.
<note place="margin">See before.</note> For as <hi>Jamblicus</hi> informs us out of the old <hi>Egyptian</hi> Books, they believ'd <hi>one Supreme God above all,</hi> next him the <hi>Demiurgus,</hi> and then <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or the <hi>Sun;</hi> whom they eſteem'd the <hi>Supreme Viſible God,</hi> and as he who had the Super-intendency over the viſible World. To which I will add the Authority of <hi>Prophyry,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Euſeb. pr. Ev. lib. 3.</note> and that the rather for that in his Epiſtle to <hi>Anebo,</hi> he ſeems to ſuſpect that the old <hi>Egyptians</hi> look'd no farther than the <hi>Sun, Moon</hi> and <hi>Stars.</hi> But 'tis plain that this was only a difficulty, which he puts to the <hi>Egyptian</hi> Prieſt; ſince himſelf owns that they repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented the <hi>Creator,</hi> whom they call'd <hi>Cneph,</hi> with an Egg in his <hi>Mouth,</hi> to ſignifie the Production of the World; and of which the <hi>Sun</hi> is but a Part.</p>
            <p>And here I may not omit another Notion of the <hi>Egyptians,</hi> and which was not theirs only; and from whence we may again know how to underſtand thoſe who ſeem to repreſent the <hi>Sun</hi> as the <hi>Supreme Deity.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Porphyr. de Abſt. l. 2. Sect. 34.</note> It was a Principle in their <hi>Theology,</hi> that the <hi>Supreme God</hi> of all, is not to be worſhipped by any <hi>External and Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible thing, not ſo much as by Vocal Prayer, but only by pure Silence and Contemplation:</hi> But that Sacrifices and <hi>Hymns were to be made to Powers inferior to Him.</hi> Among theſe they eſteemed the <hi>Sun, Moon</hi> and <hi>Stars</hi> to be the chief; from whence it was obvious enough to miſtake, that becauſe theſe were the <hi>higheſt Deities,</hi> to whom they paid any <hi>External Adoration,</hi> therefore they had no other ſuperior to them.</p>
            <pb n="44" facs="tcp:99012:32"/>
            <p>And now there remains only the <hi>Chaldeans</hi> and <hi>Phoenicians,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Not. in Spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cim. Hiſt. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rab. p. 143.</note> to be conſider'd; and of theſe, both <hi>Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garius Abulfarajus</hi> and <hi>Shareſtanius,</hi> cited by our Learned Dr. <hi>Pecock,</hi> gives us Accounts very different from that of <hi>Maimonides</hi> before mention'd; and that <hi>Judicious</hi> and <hi>Reverend Author,</hi> juſtly eſteems the Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit of <hi>Abulfarajus,</hi> preferrable to <hi>R. Maimon</hi>'s, for that he was better acquainted with their Writings, and read them in their own Language, which the other did not. And if what <hi>Shareſtanius</hi> reports be true,
<note place="margin">Ibid. p. 140.</note> That it was their Principle, that between the Supreme God <hi>and</hi> Us, <hi>there muſt be ſome</hi> Mediators; this again will furniſh us with yet <hi>another Reaſon,</hi> why the <hi>Sun</hi> may eaſily have been miſtaken for their <hi>Supreme Deity,</hi> becauſe he was the principal <hi>Mediator</hi> betwixt <hi>God</hi> and them, and the Higheſt to which they paid any immediate <hi>External Adoration.</hi> And tho this <hi>Author</hi> is as poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive, as if he had all the Evidence in the World for it,
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 76.</note> 
               <q>
                  <hi>That God made an extraordinary Diſcovery of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to</hi> Abraham, <hi>as</hi> Lord <hi>of all things, in oppoſition to the Idolatry of his own Country,</hi>
               </q> by which he would imply that the <hi>Chaldeans</hi> in thoſe days did not ſuppoſe <hi>God</hi> to be the <hi>Lord of all things;</hi> yet is it (like the reſt of his Book) all Imagination, without any thing to ſupport it. For indeed we have all the reaſon in the World to believe that the <hi>Chaldeans</hi> had at this time the knowledg of the <hi>one true God.</hi> 1. It appears by ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt Computation, that <hi>Shem,</hi> from whom <hi>Tera</hi> and <hi>Abraham</hi> were deſcended, was yet living with them, and it is altogether unaccountable, either that him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf ſhould have loſt the knowledg of the <hi>one true Supreme God;</hi> or that if he retain'd it, all the reſt of his Family ſhould have been utterly ignorant of it.
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:99012:32"/>2. It is indeed ſaid in Holy Scripture, <hi>Joſh.</hi> xxiv. <hi>v.</hi> 2. that they <hi>worſhipped ſtrange Gods;</hi> but it is not ſaid that they either worſhipped them as the <hi>Supreme God,</hi> or had utterly loſt all <hi>ſenſe</hi> and <hi>apprehenſion</hi> of any ſuch <hi>ſpiritual</hi> and <hi>inviſible Godhead.</hi> 3. In all the Hiſtory of <hi>God</hi>'s calling <hi>Abraham</hi> out of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>r</hi> of the <hi>Chaldees,</hi> we do not find any thing to make us believe that God was pleaſed to make the diſcovery of himſelf to him, as <hi>Lord of all things,</hi> in oppoſition to the <hi>Idolatry</hi> of his Family. 4. It is hard to ſuppoſe, that when all the barbarous Nations, as we have ſeen, preſerv'd the Notion of the True, Supreme <hi>God,</hi> only theſe <hi>Chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deans</hi> ſhould loſe it; it was but on the other ſide the River, that we find the knowledg of <hi>God</hi> preſerv'd in the Land of <hi>Canaan.</hi> And laſtly, we do certainly know, that but two Generations after <hi>Laban,</hi> tho he did wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip (as it is ſaid of <hi>Tera</hi>) <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ſtrange <hi>Gods</hi> too, yet he retain'd with them a very good <hi>ſenſe</hi> and <hi>apprehenſion</hi> of the <hi>Supreme</hi> God, as is plain from <hi>Gen.</hi> xxxi. where the <hi>God</hi> of <hi>Abraham</hi> is found <hi>to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear to him, v.</hi> 29. And again <hi>v.</hi> 53. he ratifies his <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant</hi> with his Son <hi>Jacoh,</hi> ſwearing by the <hi>God of Abraham,</hi> as well as by the <hi>ſtrange God,</hi> the God of <hi>Nahor.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To conclude; <hi>Macrobius,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Macrob. Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turnal.</note> than whom none could have taken more pains to ſhew the univerſal Worſhip of the <hi>Sun,</hi> was yet ſo far from thinking that it exclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded all <hi>ſenſe</hi> and <hi>apprehenſion</hi> of a <hi>Supreme</hi> God, that he plainly ſays in the beginning, that he intended to treat only of the <hi>Dij qui ſub Coelo ſunt,</hi> the lower ſort of <hi>Worldly Gods;</hi> and in his <hi>Commentary</hi> upon the <hi>Dream</hi> of <hi>Scipio,</hi> he plainly acknowledges a higher Divinity, whom he calls the <hi>Prima Cauſa, &amp; Omnipo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentiſſimus
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:99012:33"/>Deus; The Firſt Cauſe,</hi> and moſt Almighty God.</p>
            <p>I ſhall cloſe all with a paſſage of <hi>Plutarch,</hi> which will at once ſhew both that the Heathens had a know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg of the <hi>Supreme God</hi> amongſt them,
<note place="margin">Plutarch de I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide &amp; Oſiride.</note> and that it was <hi>He</hi> whom they all every where <hi>Adored</hi> as ſuch, however differing in their <hi>Manners</hi> and <hi>Ceremonies</hi> from one another:
<q>
                  <hi>No inanimate thing can be a God to men; but they who beſtow upon us a continual ſupply of what is ſufficient for us, have therefore been esteemed Gods by us; which Gods are not different among diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent Nations, as if the</hi> Barbarians <hi>and</hi> Greeks, <hi>the</hi> Southern <hi>and</hi> Northern <hi>People had not the ſame God; but as the Sun, and Moon, and Heaven, and Earth, and Sea, are common to all, but are called differently by different men; ſo tho there be but</hi> ONE WORD, <hi>or</hi> REASON, <hi>ordering all thoſe things, and but</hi> ONE PROVIDENCE <hi>diſpenſing all things, and the Inferior Powers which are appointed over all, having had ſeveral Names and Honours from ſeveral Perſons, and by the Laws of ſeveral Countries, have been every where wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipp'd throughout the whole World.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>I paſs on finally to enquire,</p>
            <p n="3">3. Whether theſe Ancient <hi>Idolaters,</hi>
               <note place="margin">P. 97, 100.</note> as is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended, did ſo Worſhip theſe <hi>Heavenly Bodies,</hi> as to Worſhip <hi>nothing</hi> beſides, and in particular ſo as to exclude all <hi>Notion</hi> of <hi>Heroes</hi> and <hi>Daemons.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This indeed is an <hi>Aſſertion</hi> worthy our <hi>Author,</hi> who as he has hitherto advanced nothing but <hi>Paradoxes,</hi> ſo he reſolves he will not now alter his <hi>Character</hi> by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſenting <hi>Antiquity truly</hi> at the laſt.</p>
            <pb n="47" facs="tcp:99012:33"/>
            <p>I have already ſhewn in oppoſition to this ſuggeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, how the <hi>Egyptians</hi> had their <hi>Divi,</hi> or <hi>Canonized men</hi> preſently after the <hi>Flood;</hi> and that we have ſome reaſon to believe their principal <hi>Deities,</hi> viz. <hi>Apis</hi> and <hi>Oſyris,</hi> to have been ſuch; I will now add, that the firſt <hi>Dynasties</hi> of <hi>Manetho,</hi> of <hi>Gods</hi> and Demi-Gods upon Earth, confirms this, and to which the old <hi>Egyptian Chronicon</hi> in <hi>Syncellus</hi> adds yet more force. St. <hi>Cyril</hi> tells us from <hi>Sanchoniathon,</hi> that not only the moſt Ancient <hi>Greeks,</hi> but eſpecially the <hi>Phoeniceans</hi> and <hi>Egyptians,</hi> from whom this Superſtition was deri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to all others (tho our <hi>Author,</hi> ever in the wrong,
<note place="margin">P. 101. Cyrillus Alex. contra Julian, l. 6. p. 205. C.D.</note> will have the <hi>Greeks</hi> to be the Inventors of it) eſteem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed thoſe the <hi>greatest Gods, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> who had either found out ſome things uſeful for the life of man, or otherwiſe deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved well of their Country.</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>And looking upon them as their Benefactors and Cauſes of great good to them,</hi> they worſhipped them as Gods, and <hi>prepared</hi> Temples <hi>for that purpoſe, and conſecrated Pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars and other Enſigns of Honour to their Memory.</hi> And as the <hi>Holy Father</hi> from the ſame <hi>Author</hi> goes on, <hi>Theſe they</hi> greatly worſhipped, <hi>and the</hi> Phoenicians <hi>eſpecially, dedicated Festivals unto them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But it was not enough for our <hi>Author</hi> merely to advance a moſt falſe Concluſion concerning theſe <hi>Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles,</hi> unleſs he alſo chuſe an <hi>Evidence</hi> for it that ſpeaks the <hi>direct contrary</hi> to his <hi>Aſſertion:</hi> For thus it became him to keep up a juſt <hi>decorum</hi> between his <hi>Principles</hi> and his <hi>Proofs,</hi> that ſo we may be ſatisfied, that he values <hi>Truth</hi> alike in both.</p>
            <pb n="48" facs="tcp:99012:34"/>
            <p>
               <q>
                  <hi>This</hi> (ſays he) <hi>is atteſted by all Hiſtorians,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Page 100.</note> viz. <hi>That the old Heathen Nations worſhipped only the Stars, without any Notion of Heroes and Demons.</hi>
               </q> And the very firſt he inſtances, in is <hi>Diodorus Siculus</hi> for the <hi>Egyptians.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But this is perfectly to aſtoniſh us, and too plainly ſhews that ſome <hi>mens aſſurance</hi> is without bounds, as well as without reaſon: For what? Does <hi>Diodorus Siculus</hi> ſay that the <hi>Egyptians</hi> worſhipp'd only the Stars, without any Notion of <hi>Heroes</hi> and <hi>Demons?</hi> This is worſe than to write <hi>History</hi> out of an <hi>Inviſible Manuſcript;</hi> 'tis indeed to write Hiſtory directly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the <hi>Viſible Records</hi> out of which he pretends to have taken it: For let this <hi>Author</hi> look into <hi>Diodo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus Siculus,</hi> whom I would willingly hope he has never yet read,
<note place="margin">Diodorus Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culus Ed. Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nov. G. L. An. 1604.</note> and there he will find him in <hi>his Firſt Book,</hi> ſo far from what he pretends, that on the contrary, he expreſly diſtinguiſhes between two <hi>ſorts</hi> of <hi>Gods</hi> among the <hi>Egyptians,</hi> and diſcourſes of them in Order: And firſt of the <hi>Celeſtial Gods, p.</hi> 10. two of which he ſays the <hi>Egyptians</hi> firſt of all had, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the <hi>Sun</hi> and the <hi>Moon:</hi> Having diſcourſed of theſe, he thus formally concludes his Account,
<note place="margin">Page 12.</note> 'And this the <hi>Egyptians</hi> ſay concerning their <hi>Celeſtial Gods,</hi> and ſuch as had an <hi>Eternal Generation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And then goes on immediately on the <hi>other ſort,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ibid.</note> which this Author pretends <hi>Diodorus Siculus</hi> denies them to have had ANY NOTION OF: <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>But be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides theſe</hi> (the <hi>Sun</hi> and <hi>Moon,</hi> &amp;c.) <hi>they ſay there are other</hi> Terreſtrial Gods, Mortals <hi>indeed by Nature,</hi> but for their <hi>Wiſdom and Prudence, and the benefits
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:99012:34"/>they did to mankind, endued with Immortality;</hi> of which kind (ſays he) were ſome of the <hi>Kings</hi> of <hi>Egypt.</hi> In the next <hi>page</hi> he places amongſt theſe,
<note place="margin">P. 13.</note> our Author's Friends, <hi>Iſis</hi> and <hi>Oſiris,</hi> whoſe Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory he relates: And finally, to raiſe his ill choice to the higheſt Evidence, having given a long relation of theſe kind of <hi>Deities,</hi>
               <note place="margin">P. 101:</note> he concludes as directly againſt our <hi>Author</hi>'s other <hi>Aſſertion,</hi> 
               <q>
                  <hi>That this kind of Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try was the Invention of the vain and lying Greeks,</hi>
               </q> as if he had been retain'd on our ſide,
<note place="margin">Diod. Siculus p. 20, 21.</note> by ſhewing ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly how they derived this kind of <hi>Idolatry</hi> from the <hi>Egyptians,</hi> by the means of <hi>Orpheus,</hi> who had been initiated in the <hi>Egyptian</hi> Rites; and then gives us this univerſal Concluſion, <hi>p.</hi> 21. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>That the Egyptians do in general ſay, that the Grecians have appropriated to themſelves the moſt eminent of their Heroes and Gods, as well as of their Colonies.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So much would it have been for our <hi>Author</hi>'s Repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, if <hi>Diodorus Siculus</hi> too, had been an <hi>Inviſible Manuſcript.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. The next <hi>Author</hi> he produces, is <hi>Herodotus,</hi> who, he ſays, affirms the ſame of the <hi>Perſians</hi> and <hi>Chaldeans,</hi> that they worſhipped only the <hi>Stars,</hi> without any Notion of <hi>Heroes</hi> and <hi>Demons;</hi> but concerning the former part of his Aſſertion, I have already ſhewn, that they did not worſhip <hi>only</hi> the <hi>Stars,</hi> but acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged a <hi>Supreme Deity</hi> above them; and for the lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, the very ſame <hi>Herodotus</hi> who ſays this of the <hi>Perſians,</hi> in his firſt Book,
<note place="margin">Page 100, 101.</note> does directly contradict his <hi>Concluſion,</hi> 
               <q>
                  <hi>That this was the ſenſe of all the old Heathen Nations, but eſpecially that the worſhipping of
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:99012:35"/>Men and Women, was the Invention of the vain and lying Greeks,</hi>
               </q> in the very next, where he tells us that they derived <hi>their Twelve Gods from the Egyptians,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Herodotus, l. 2. c. 4. p. 91.</note> who were the firſt Inventors of this <hi>Idolatry.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. The ſame (he ſays) in the next place is affirm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by <hi>Strabo</hi> and <hi>Juſtin,</hi> of the <hi>Arabians:</hi> Had he been pleaſed to produce ſome paſſages from theſe Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors wherein they do ſay, <q>
                  <hi>That the Arabians wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip only the Stars, without any Notion of Heroes and Demons,</hi>
               </q> we ſhould have had leſs cauſe to ſuſpect his Aſſertion;
<note place="margin">Strabo l. 16. p. 539.</note> 
               <hi>Strabo</hi> indeed ſays that the <hi>Arabians</hi> worſhip the <hi>Sun,</hi> but that either <hi>He</hi> or <hi>Juſtin</hi> have ever affirmed what this Author pretends, I am yet to learn; in the mean time this I am ſure, that other <hi>Authors</hi> have given us a very contrary account of them.
<note place="margin">Lucan l. 9. v. 517.</note> 
               <hi>Lucan</hi> tells us, that their only God was <hi>Jupi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Ammon,</hi> whom that Learned <hi>Critick, Gerard Voſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi> does not without reaſon ſuppoſe to have been <hi>Cham,</hi> whoſe Eldeſt <hi>Son Chus,</hi> as I have before ſhewn, firſt planted himſelf there. <hi>Arrian</hi> in his Hiſtory of <hi>Alexander's Expedition,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Arrian de Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped. Alep. l. 7. p. 486.</note> ſays that they had two <hi>Gods,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or the Heaven, and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or <hi>Bacchus;</hi> and that 'twas this encouraged that great <hi>Conqueror</hi> to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vade them, that he might make himſelf a <hi>Third God</hi> amongſt them; and this may be well enough con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtent with the other Account, if what ſome Learned Men ſuppoſe, be allow'd; that theſe were their own <hi>proper Gods,</hi> whereas <hi>Jupiter Hammon,</hi> was rather the Deity of the <hi>Ammonites,</hi> among whom his Oracle ſtood, and to whom they only ſent Ambaſſadors to conſult upon occaſion, it not appearing that the <hi>Ara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bians</hi> had any Temple for him in their <hi>own Country:</hi> So that here too our <hi>Author</hi> is miſtaken, for that the
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:99012:35"/>
               <hi>Arabians</hi> had other <hi>Gods</hi> than the <hi>Stars,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Voſſius de 1. dol. l. 1. c. 26.</note> and were not without all Notion of <hi>Heroes</hi> and <hi>Doemons.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. His Fourth Inſtance is in the Ancient <hi>Germans,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Caeſ. Com. l. 6.</note> and of them I confeſs <hi>Caeſar</hi> does ſay what he pretends, but then it is to be obſerv'd, that in the very ſame place, he utterly overthrows all the uſe this <hi>Author</hi> can be ſuppoſed to make of it, <hi>viz.</hi> to ſhew, <q>
                  <hi>That all the old Heathen Nations worſhipped only the Stars, without any Notion of Heroes or Demons;</hi>
               </q> ſeeing in the very ſame place, he ſays of the Ancient <hi>Gauls,</hi> that they worſhipp'd ſuch kind of <hi>Gods</hi> as he denies any of the Heathen did, and that with a Superſtition ſo like that of ſome of his Acquaintance, that I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not forbear taking notice of it: <q>
                  <hi>The Gauls,</hi> ſays he, <hi>are very ſuperſtitious, and therefore if they fall into any dangerous diſtemper, or are concerned in War, or in any other danger, they ſtraightway ſacrifice,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>For this purpoſe they have their particular Gods;</hi> Mercury <hi>to proſper them in their Journeys, or help them in their Traffick;</hi> Apollo <hi>to cure them in their ſickneſs; Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerva to find out any Artificial Works;</hi> Mars <hi>for War,</hi> &amp;c.</q> And this our <hi>Author</hi> could not but know, ſince in the very Paſſage to which he refers, he op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes the <hi>Germans</hi> to them; the <hi>Germans</hi> (ſays he) differ much from <hi>this cuſtom (viz.)</hi> of the <hi>Gauls,</hi> which he had juſt before recounted; for they eſteem them only for <hi>Gods</hi> whom they ſee, and by whom they are manifeſtly help'd, the <hi>Sun, Vulcan,</hi> and the <hi>Moon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But I have yet more to except againſt this inſtance; for however <hi>Ceſar</hi> came to be ſo miſinformed, the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient <hi>Germans</hi> had other <hi>Gods,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hiſt. l. 6. Cap. 64.</note> even ſuch as this <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor</hi> denies to all the <hi>Ancient Idolaters. Tacitus</hi> men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:99012:36"/>
               <hi>Mars</hi> as the chief God of the <hi>Tencteri,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cap. 9.</note> a Nation bordering upon the <hi>Rhine;</hi> and in his Book <hi>de Moribus Germanerum,</hi> he ſpeaks of <hi>Hercules</hi> as another of their <hi>Deities.</hi> That they alſo Worſhipped <hi>Mercury,</hi> we learn from the ſame Author, whom in their Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage they called <hi>Gota,</hi> or <hi>Wota,</hi> as <hi>Gotefridus Viter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bienſis</hi> in his <hi>Chronicon</hi> obſerves,
<note place="margin">Voſ. de Idol. l. 1. p. 240.</note> from whence alſo he ſuppoſes, that their word <hi>Got,</hi> ſignifying <hi>God,</hi> is deri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved; tho in this, other Learned Men diſſent from him.</p>
            <p>And laſtly,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>De</hi> Moribus Germ. c. 2.</note> the ſame <hi>Tacitus</hi> mentions yet another God more Ancient than all theſe, the firſt Founder of their Country, <hi>Tuiſto,</hi> whom they worſhipped, with his Son <hi>Manus;</hi> and theſe, ſome think, were no other than <hi>Gomar,</hi> and his Son <hi>Thogorma</hi> or <hi>Aſchenar,</hi> by whom <hi>Germany</hi> was peopled after the Flood, tho <hi>Voſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi> rather ſuppoſes them yet of a greater Antiquity, believing <hi>Tuiſto</hi> to be <hi>Adam,</hi> and <hi>Manus,</hi> to whom alſo <hi>Tacitus</hi> aſſigns three <hi>Sons, Noah,</hi> by whom the World was again eſtabliſhed after the Flood.</p>
            <p n="4">4. And this may ſuffice for his particular <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorities.</hi> His next are univerſal; for he ſays <hi>Euſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bius</hi> in his Book <hi>de preparatione Evangelica,
<note place="margin">Page 100.</note> has ſhewn this to be the ſenſe of all the Old Heathen Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, as may be ſeen in his Collections of their ſeveral Opinions, where he proves,</hi> 
               <q>
                  <hi>That the Ancient Heathens only worſhipped the Stars, without any Notion of He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roes or Demons.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Good <hi>God!</hi> What can be done with ſuch a <hi>Man</hi> as this? <hi>Euſebius</hi> has proved that all the Ancient <hi>Heathens</hi> worſhipped only the <hi>Stars,</hi> without any Notion of <hi>Heroes</hi> and <hi>Demons,</hi> which was a <hi>mere In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention of the vain and lying Greeks:</hi> And yet has this
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:99012:36"/>very <hi>Euſebius</hi> quoted <hi>Diodorus Siculus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Euſeb. praep. Evan. l. 2 c. 1.</note> for his account of the <hi>Egvptian Theology.</hi> He diſtinguiſhes with him their <hi>Gods</hi> into <hi>Coeleſtial</hi> and <hi>Terreſtrial:</hi> Of the firſt, he Treats in his firſt. Book from that Author; of the ſecond in his next. The very Title of his Chapter is,
<note place="margin">Lib. 1. c. 7. Lib. 2. c. 1. p. 45.</note> 
               <hi>An Epitome of the</hi> Egyptian <hi>Theology, and how it paſſed from them to the</hi> Greeks. In the beginning of it, he ſpeaks how <q>
                  <hi>their Gods, who had been mortal Men, were for their Benefits they did to Mankind, and for their Wiſdom, made immortal Deities.</hi>
               </q>
               <note place="margin">Pag. 45, 46, 47, 48.</note> He exemplifies this in a large account of their <hi>Mythology;</hi> and then con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes expreſly with his <hi>Author,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>That the</hi> Greeks <hi>had appropriated to themſelves, the principal</hi> Hero'<hi>s, and Gods of the</hi> Egyptians. And yet this is the <hi>Author</hi> that has ſhewn at large,
<note place="margin">P. 100.</note> how <hi>all theold Heathen Nations worſhipp'd only</hi> Stars, <hi>without any Notion of</hi> Hero<hi>'s and</hi> Daemons.</p>
            <p>His other Author is <hi>Macrobius,</hi> who he ſays, has proved it of all the Ancient <hi>Idolaters,</hi> that they wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped the <hi>Sun</hi> as the <hi>Supreme Deity.</hi> He ſhould have added to make good his Concluſion,
<note place="margin">P. 100.</note> and <hi>that ſo as to exclude all Notions of</hi> Hero'<hi>s and</hi> Daemons. But this <hi>Macrobius</hi> never undertook to do: And I have before ſhewn, that in the very Book of his <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turnals,</hi> here mention'd, He was ſo far from ſhewing that they worſhipp'd the <hi>Sun</hi> as the (abſolutely) <hi>Supreme Deity,</hi> that in the beginning of his Diſcourſe, he expreſly reſtrains it to the <hi>Dii duntaxat qui ſub Coelo ſunt,</hi> or <hi>Sub-Coeleſtial Deities:</hi> And in his <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> upon <hi>Scipio</hi>'s <hi>Dream,</hi> he acknowledges above the <hi>Sun</hi> and <hi>Heaven,</hi> many other Gods; <hi>viz.</hi> 1. An <hi>Eternal Pſythe,</hi> the Creator both of the <hi>Heaven,</hi> and the
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:99012:37"/>
               <hi>Sun.</hi> 2dly, A perfect <hi>Mind</hi> or <hi>Intellect,</hi> and (as he calls him) <hi>Omnipotentiſſimus Deus,</hi> the moſt Omnipotent of all Gods.</p>
            <p n="5">5. He has two <hi>Authors</hi> whom he produces; our own Learned <hi>Selden,</hi> in his Book <hi>De Diis Syris,</hi> and <hi>Gerard Voſſius,</hi> in nothing inferior to him, who have proved <q>
                  <hi>all the Idols mention'd in Scripture, to have been ſo many Appellations of the</hi> Sun, <hi>whom the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Idolaters believed to have been the Supreme God, and Creator of the World,</hi> (and therefore of himſelf too, for he is part of it) as <hi>Baal, Baal-Peor, Bel, Molech, Baal-Zebub,</hi> and <hi>Mythras;</hi>
               </q> tho I doubt this laſt was taken from ſome Inviſible <hi>Manuſcript</hi> of the <hi>Bible,</hi> for I do not remember that I have ever met with it in any of the <hi>Editions</hi> that are extant of thoſe <hi>ſacred Volumes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But to let this paſs too; Did Mr. <hi>Selden</hi> then, and <hi>Gerard Voſſius</hi> in good Truth, undertake to ſhew, that all the Ancient <hi>Idolaters</hi> worſhipp'd the <hi>Sun</hi> as the <hi>Supreme God,</hi> ſo as to exclude all Notion of <hi>Dae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons</hi> and <hi>Hero</hi>'s?</p>
            <p n="1">1ſt, Mr. <hi>Selden</hi> gives only a Critical Account of the <hi>Syrian Deities;</hi> and in ſeveral of them ſhews, that others at leaſt have believed them to be ſomewhat elſe than the <hi>Sun.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2dly, <hi>Gerard Voſſius</hi> is ſo far from favouring this Man's pretences, that on the contrary 'tis he, who has ſpent his whole <hi>firſt Book</hi> of <hi>Idolatry,</hi> to give an Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of the Ancient <hi>Hero</hi>'s, that were conſecrated by the <hi>Gentiles</hi> into Gods; 'Tis he that interprets the <hi>Egyptians Oſyris</hi> to be <hi>Mitzraim;</hi> the <hi>Beel</hi> of the <hi>Chaldeans</hi> to be <hi>Nimrod;</hi> the <hi>Tuiſco</hi> of the <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans, Gomer,</hi> or perhaps <hi>Adam.</hi> In ſhort, he ſhews
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:99012:37"/>this ſort of <hi>Idolatry</hi> to have been introduced a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the <hi>Heathens</hi> the very Age after the <hi>Flood,</hi> even before <hi>God</hi> called <hi>Abraham</hi> from <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>z</hi> of the <hi>Chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dees.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And thus have I conſider'd this <hi>Author</hi>'s Pretences to <hi>Antiquity;</hi> and I think I may ſay, there is nothing but <hi>Falſeneſs</hi> and <hi>Viſion,</hi> in all his <hi>Notions</hi> and <hi>Authorities.</hi> Upon the whole, I ſhall beg leave very briefly, to Conclude as to the Nature of <hi>Idolatry.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">I. That ſeeing all theſe Ancient <hi>Idolaters,</hi> did ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledg one <hi>Supreme, Inviſible</hi> and <hi>Spiritual Godhead,</hi> their <hi>Idolatry</hi> did not conſiſt in worſhipping the <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Bodies,</hi> ſo as to exclude all <hi>Senſe</hi> and <hi>Appehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion</hi> of any ſuch thing.</p>
            <p n="2">II. That ſeeing they believed the <hi>Sun</hi> and other <hi>Heavenly Bodies,</hi> to be the <hi>Vehicles</hi> only of <hi>imma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terial</hi> and <hi>ſpiritual Subſtances,</hi> who had the <hi>Superin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendency</hi> over the Affairs of this <hi>lower World,</hi> and were to be applied to as <hi>Mediators</hi> between <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Them;</hi> their <hi>Idolatry</hi> did not conſiſt in worſhipping any <hi>Viſible</hi> or <hi>Corporeal Deities,</hi> as the <hi>Supreme God,</hi> ſo as to exclude all <hi>Senſe</hi> and <hi>Apprehenſion</hi> of a <hi>Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual</hi> and <hi>Inviſible Godhead,</hi> Superior to their Deities. By Conſequence,</p>
            <p n="3">III. That either this, which our Author here lays down, is not (as he pretends) the <hi>true</hi> and <hi>only No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> of <hi>Idolatry;</hi> or if it be, none of thoſe Ancient <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions</hi> were <hi>Idolaters.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">IV. Tho I dare not preſume to eſtabliſh <hi>true</hi> and <hi>only Notions</hi> in this Caſe; yet from what has been ſaid, I think we may reaſonably Conclude their <hi>Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry,</hi> to have conſiſted eſpecially in theſe two things;
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:99012:38"/>Either, 1ſt, That they worſhipp'd the <hi>true God</hi> by <hi>Corporeal</hi> and Viſible Symbols; or that 2dly, together with the true <hi>God,</hi> they worſhipp'd other <hi>inferior Deities;</hi> whether <hi>Intelligences,</hi> (which they ſuppoſed to reſide in the <hi>Heavenly Bodies</hi>) or <hi>Daemons.</hi> And that by conſequence,</p>
            <p>To Worſhip the <hi>Supreme God</hi> in any Corporeal Repreſentation or <hi>Image</hi> whatſoever; or to pay <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Worſhip</hi> to any <hi>Created Being,</hi> whether <hi>Spirit</hi> or <hi>ſeparate Soul;</hi> either as having the Power over this <hi>inferior World</hi> to Adminiſter things in it, or as <hi>Mediators</hi> between the <hi>Supreme God</hi> and <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s;</hi> this is, if not the <hi>only,</hi> yet at leaſt a <hi>true Notion</hi> of <hi>Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="4" type="chapter">
            <pb n="57" facs="tcp:99012:38"/>
            <head>CHAP. IV. <hi>Of the</hi> Notion <hi>of</hi> Idolatry <hi>under the</hi> Law; <hi>and that it did not Conſiſt in the giving the worſhip of the</hi> Supreme God <hi>to ſome</hi> Created, Corporeal <hi>or</hi> Viſible Deity <hi>as</hi> ſuppoſing <hi>it to be the</hi> Supreme God.</head>
            <p>THis was the next <hi>point</hi> I propoſed to examine, and our <hi>Author</hi> thus delivers his <hi>Opinion</hi> of it. <q>That according to the <hi>Law,
<note place="margin">Page 80.</note> Idolatry</hi> is giving the <hi>worſhip</hi> of the <hi>Supreme God</hi> to any <hi>created, corporeal,</hi> or <hi>viſible deity,</hi> or any thing that can be <hi>repreſented</hi> by an <hi>image,</hi> which nothing but <hi>corporeal Beings</hi> can,
<note place="margin">Pag. 81.</note> and to ſuppoſe ſuch a <hi>Being</hi> the <hi>Supreme Deity.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>And though there may ſeem to be <hi>two ſorts</hi> of it. Firſt, either to <hi>worſhip</hi> a <hi>material and created Being</hi> as the <hi>Supreme Deity,</hi> or Secondly to aſcribe any <hi>corporeal Form</hi> or <hi>Shape</hi> to the <hi>Divine Nature;</hi> yet in the reſult both are but One; for to aſcribe unto the <hi>Supreme God</hi> any <hi>Corporeal Form,</hi> is the ſame thing as to worſhip a <hi>Created Being,</hi> for ſo is every <hi>Corporeal Subſtance.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This is, I ſay, the <hi>TR<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>E</hi> and <hi>ONELY Notion</hi> of Idolatry.</p>
            </q>
            <p>This indeed is <hi>Great</hi> and <hi>Magiſterial,</hi> and would almoſt diſpoſe a man to think, that there ſhould cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly be at leaſt <hi>ſomething</hi> of <hi>Truth,</hi> where there is ſo <hi>very much confidence.</hi> But we have had
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:99012:39"/>already ſufficient reaſon to ſuſpect him, where he ſeems leaſt to ſuſpect himſelf. Here I cannot but wonder that a perſon of his <hi>Character</hi> ſhould ſend abroad ſuch <hi>Notions</hi> into the world for the <hi>Dictates</hi> of <hi>Holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,</hi> as are evidently contrary to the Tenor of it; unleſs he thought our <hi>Nobility and Gentry</hi> as little acquainted with that <hi>Book,</hi> as ſome of their <hi>Guides</hi> are ſaid to have thought it fit they ſhould be.</p>
            <p>To make a man an <hi>Idolater</hi> according to the <hi>Idea</hi> this <hi>Author</hi> has given of it, two things are requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, which I much queſtion whether they ever yet concurred in any conſiderable number of men in the world, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>1. That he give the <hi>worſhip</hi> of the <hi>Supreme God</hi> to ſome <hi>Created, Corporeal,</hi> and <hi>Viſible</hi> part of the Univerſe.</item>
               <item>2dly, That he give this <hi>worſhip</hi> to it as eſteeming ſuch a Being to be the <hi>Supreme God.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>I will not be ſo rude as to enquire by what <hi>Rules</hi> of <hi>Diſcourſe</hi> he infers all this from the <hi>Second Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> that becauſe <hi>God</hi> there forbids the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> to make any <q>
                  <hi>Graven Image, the likeneſs of any thing that is in Heaven above, or in the Earth beneath or in the water under the Earth; to bow down be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it and worſhip it;</hi>
               </q> therefore, this <hi>Image</hi> muſt be the <hi>ſimilitude of ſome viſible and Corporeal deity;</hi> and that <hi>Deity</hi> be ſuppoſed to be the <hi>Supreme God,</hi> and be <hi>worſhiped</hi> as ſuch. He that can infer this from the Second Commandment, would doe well to tell us how he does it. But not to be importunate here. If this be the <hi>true and onely Idolatry,</hi> according to the Law, I would deſire to know;</p>
            <pb n="59" facs="tcp:99012:39"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> Seeing the <hi>Law</hi> was deliver'd by the <hi>Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry</hi> of <hi>Angels,</hi> and theſe were no <hi>viſible</hi> and <hi>Corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>real deities;</hi> what if the <hi>Jews</hi> had paid <hi>Divine Ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration</hi> to them? would this have been <hi>Idolatry</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Law? If it would, I ſhould be glad to know what <hi>part</hi> of his <hi>definition</hi> it is that makes it to be ſo?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> I have before ſhewn that the ancient <hi>Heathens,</hi> the <hi>Egyptians, Chaldeans,</hi> &amp;c. though they <hi>worſhiped</hi> indeed the <hi>Sun, Moon</hi> and <hi>Stars;</hi> yet they neither <hi>believed</hi> them to be the <hi>Supreme God</hi> nor the <hi>Image</hi> of the <hi>Supreme God;</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> that they were onely <hi>viſible,</hi> and <hi>Corporeal deities:</hi> They look'd upon them as the <hi>vehicles</hi> of <hi>Celeſtial Spirits,</hi> which dwelt in them; and as ſuch they pay'd their <hi>Adoration</hi> to them. Now then was this <hi>Idolatry</hi> by the <hi>Law,</hi> or was it not? If it were not, how came the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> to be charged with <hi>Idolatry</hi> (according to this <hi>Author's</hi> own <hi>prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples</hi>) for joyning with them in this <hi>Service?</hi> If it were, how will this agree with his <hi>true and onely Notion of Idolatry?</hi> Seeing they worſhip'd theſe Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly bodies neither as the <hi>Supreme God,</hi> nor ſo as to exclude all <hi>ſenſe and apprehenſion of a ſpiritual and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſible deity.</hi> But,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> To come to the <hi>Holy Scripture</hi> it ſelf we read 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 11. that <hi>Soloman</hi> in his old age turned away his Heart,
<note place="margin">—Verſ. 4. Collat. <hi>cum</hi> Joſ. 24.2. Pag. 93.</note> and worſhiped <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>other Gods,</hi> viz. <hi>Aſhtoreth,</hi> and <hi>Milcom,</hi> and <hi>Chemoſh,</hi> and <hi>Moloch,</hi> i. e. according to this <hi>Learned Man's Notion,</hi> the <hi>Sun,</hi> and <hi>Moon,</hi> and I ſuppoſe he will not deny that herein he committed <hi>Idolatry.</hi> But now can any one believe that <hi>Solomon</hi> who had been ſo well inſtructed in the knowledge of the <hi>Lord
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:99012:40"/>God of Iſrael;</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Kings 3.5.—9.2.</note> he to whom God had <hi>twice himſelf appeared;</hi> and whom he had endu'd with <hi>wiſedom</hi> above all the men upon the Earth; finally who had not ſo long ſince built him a magnificent <hi>Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple</hi> at <hi>Jeruſalem;</hi> where the Service of the true God was continued, even whilſt he worſhiped the Gods of his Wives. Can any one, I ſay, be ſo ſtupid as to believe that this <hi>Solomon</hi> gave the worſhip of the <hi>Supreme God</hi> to the <hi>Sun</hi> and <hi>Moon,</hi> as ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing them to be the <hi>Supreme deities,</hi> and that he did not onely not worſhip but likewiſe not ſo much as believe the onely ſupreme God? And yet this we muſt ſay, if we will allow this <hi>Author</hi> to have given us the <hi>true</hi> and <hi>onely notion of Idolatry.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Beſides it is certain that whilſt he was engaged in his Idolatrous worſhip, God did not utterly for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake him, but admoniſhed him of it and threatned him with the loſs of his Kingdom for ſerving ſtrange Gods, which is inducement enough to conclude that he had ſtill an apprehenſion of the True God. If <hi>Solomon</hi> did immediately upon this admonition give over his Impious worſhip, it ſhewed evidently that he retained the knowledge of that God who had twice appeared to him. For to ſuppoſe that he had quite loſt all ſenſe and apprehenſion of him juſt when he fell to Idolatry, and juſt recovered ſome ſenſe of him upon this admonition, and that all the while between, he believed his <hi>viſible</hi> and <hi>Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poreal deities,</hi> or ſome one of them to be the <hi>Supreme God,</hi> and had no ſenſe of him who is truely ſo, is to make <hi>Solomon</hi> almoſt ſuch a man as I before ſhewed our <hi>Author</hi>'s Idolater to be according to the meaning of his words: I am
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:99012:40"/>ſure it is not to make him one of the wiſeſt men that ever was in the World. But ſuppoſing that <hi>Solomon</hi> went on for ſome time after this to worſhip his ſtrange Gods, yet he muſt now at leaſt have recovered ſome Senſe of the <hi>true God,</hi> it being this admonition in all likelyhood, that ſooner or later brought him to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance: And then our Author's Principles do from that time that he was admoniſh'd, acquit <hi>Solomon</hi> of all <hi>Idolatry,</hi> though he went on to ſerve the Gods of his Wives.</p>
            <p>It is a ſhame to run this matter any farther, and I make no doubt but that I have all men of Senſe whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of ours, or of the Roman Church with me in this matter againſt our Author. But that I may not ſeem onely to deſtroy his <hi>Idea,</hi> without fixing any other in the room of it; I now proceed to obſerve, That we find two ſorts of <hi>Idolatry</hi> mention'd in the <hi>Old Teſtament;</hi> and (ſuch is the misfortune of this poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive man,) both of them <hi>utterly deſtructive</hi> of his <hi>true</hi> and <hi>onely Notion</hi> of it, viz.</p>
            <list>
               <item>I. The worſhiping of the <hi>true God,</hi> by a <hi>material Symbol</hi> or <hi>Repreſentation.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>II. The worſhiping of <hi>other Gods,</hi> than the <hi>God</hi> of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and that whether it be ſo as,</item>
               <item>1. Utterly to <hi>forſake</hi> the <hi>true God,</hi> and ſerve <hi>others</hi> onely, Or</item>
               <item>2. To worſhip <hi>other Gods</hi> together with <hi>Him.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <q>1ſt. That according to the <hi>Holy Scripture,</hi> it was eſteemed <hi>Idolatry</hi> among the <hi>Jews,</hi> to worſhip the <hi>true God</hi> by any material <hi>Symbol</hi> or <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſentation.</hi>
            </q>
            <pb n="62" facs="tcp:99012:41"/>
            <p>And of this I ſhall deſire no better proof, than thoſe very <hi>inſtances</hi> which this <hi>Author</hi> ſo much in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts upon, for the eſtabliſhing of his <hi>Notion,</hi> viz. thoſe of the <hi>Golden Calf,</hi> and of the <hi>Calves of Dan</hi> and <hi>Bethel.</hi> That the <hi>Children</hi> of <hi>Iſrael</hi> did commit <hi>Idolatry</hi> in the <hi>worſhip</hi> of theſe is on all hands agreed; And yet that both theſe were deſigned as <hi>Symbols</hi> of the <hi>true God,</hi> and not of any <hi>viſible</hi> or <hi>Corporeal de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ities,</hi> will I think appear evident, almoſt to a <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtration,</hi> from theſe following reflexions.</p>
            <p n="1">1ſt. That it is altogether incredible that the <q>
                  <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raelites</hi> in either of thoſe <hi>Caſes,</hi> could ſo ſoon have forgotten the <hi>true God,</hi> as to give <hi>divine worſhip</hi> to <hi>viſible</hi> and <hi>Corporeal Beings,</hi> as ſuppoſing them to be the ſupreme Deity.</q>
            </p>
            <p>If we conſider their Circumſtances when they wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhiped the <hi>Golden Calf, Exod.</hi> 32. It was but a very few days ſince <hi>God</hi> had made a very great <hi>diſcovery</hi> of Himſelf to them at Mount <hi>Horeb,</hi> when he gave them the Law, and aſſerted Himſelf to be the <hi>Jeho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vah,</hi> their God which had <hi>brought them up out of the Land of Egypt,</hi> Exod. 20.1.</p>
            <p>And in the Caſe of <hi>Jeroboam's Calves,</hi> the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of <hi>God</hi> in which they had been bred up; a continued <hi>publick Service</hi> of Him at <hi>Jeruſalem;</hi> the <hi>Feaſts</hi> and <hi>Sacrifices,</hi> and other <hi>Ceremonies</hi> which they obſerved in Obedience to his Command, the very <hi>Seal</hi> of his <hi>Covenant</hi> which they carried about them in their <hi>Fleſh,</hi> not to ſay any thing of that <hi>Temple</hi> which <hi>Solomon</hi> had ſo lately built unto him; all theſe muſt certainly have made too deep an Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion upon their minds, to permit them ſo ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dainly to fall away into ſuch an utter forgetfulneſs of
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:99012:41"/>him, as to worſhip <hi>viſible</hi> and <hi>corporeal deities</hi> as the <hi>ſupreme God,</hi> ſo as to exclude all <hi>ſenſe</hi> and <hi>appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion</hi> of him who really is the <hi>ſupreme God.</hi> Such an Ignorance as this is hardly to be found, even a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong thoſe <hi>Infidels</hi> that have never had any revela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of the <hi>true God</hi> at all made to them: But that Men who had once been inſtructed in the <hi>knowledge</hi> and worſhip of him, ſhould ſo ſuddenly fall off from both, as they muſt here have done according to this <hi>Author's true</hi> and onely <hi>Notion</hi> of their <hi>Idolatry,</hi> this I think is as <hi>incredible,</hi> as the notion it ſelf, which he would prove by the ſuppoſition of it. But,</p>
            <p n="2">2dly. That the people did not fall into any <q>ſuch <hi>Apoſtafie,</hi> but deſign'd in thoſe <hi>Calves</hi> to worſhip the <hi>God</hi> of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> is evident from the <hi>Characters</hi> given of that <hi>deity</hi> whom they ſerved by them.</q>
            </p>
            <p>For as to the <hi>Golden Calf,</hi> we read <hi>Exod.</hi> 32.4. that when it was ſet up they cry'd out, <q>This is thy God O <hi>Iſrael, which brought thee up</hi> out of the Land of Egypt, and <hi>Aaron</hi> built an Altar <hi>before it,</hi> and <hi>made proclamation and ſaid, to Morrow is a Feaſt to the Jehovah</hi> or <hi>the Lord.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>And ſo <hi>Jeroboam</hi> in the very ſame manner, having ſet up his <hi>Calves</hi> in <hi>Dan</hi> and <hi>Bethel,</hi> 1 Kin. 12.28. <q>
                  <hi>It is too much for you</hi> (ſaid he to the people) <hi>to go to Jeruſalem; Behold</hi> thy God O Iſrael, <hi>which brought thee up out of the Land of Egypt.</hi>
               </q> Now may I deſire this Learned <hi>Author</hi> to tell us. 1. Where in <hi>Holy Scripture</hi> do's he find the name <hi>JEHOVAH,</hi> or the <hi>LORD</hi> attributed to any other but the <hi>true God?</hi> Or if we ſhould ſuppoſe the people to be Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant in this Caſe, yet could <hi>Aaron</hi> the <hi>High-prieſt</hi> be ſo forgetfull, as not to remember that this was that
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:99012:42"/>
               <hi>peculiar name</hi> which <hi>God</hi> aſſumed to himſelf, <hi>Exod.</hi> 6.3. and of which our <hi>Author</hi> himſelf takes notice, <hi>p.</hi> 80.81. 2. Whom ſhould they then, and <hi>Jerobo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am</hi> mean after by the Jehovah <hi>that</hi> had brought them up <hi>out of the Land of Egypt,</hi> but him who at the delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of the Law, appropriated this Character to himſelf, <hi>Ex.</hi> 20.1. and who was under that Title worſhiped by the <hi>Jews</hi> at <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> where his <hi>Temple</hi> ſtood, and whither all the <hi>Tribes</hi> were wont to go up to <hi>worſhip</hi> him. <hi>It is too much for you to go up to</hi> Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem. <hi>Behold thy</hi> God, <hi>O</hi> Iſrael, <hi>which brought thee up out of the Land of Egypt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. Had <hi>Jeroboam</hi> hereby deſigned to ſet up a <hi>new God</hi> amongſt them, how came it to paſs that He uſed no <hi>Arguments</hi> with them at all as to that mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, but merely remonſtrated to them the trouble of going up to <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> to <hi>worſhip?</hi> Never ſure were people eaſier perſuaded out of their <hi>religion</hi> than the <hi>ten Tribes,</hi> if our <hi>Author</hi> thinks, that the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of place made him chuſe rather to return to the <hi>Idolatry</hi> of <hi>Egypt,</hi> than to be at ſo much pains to <hi>worſhip</hi> the true <hi>God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3dly. But all this will farther appear, in that it is altogether incredible that the <hi>Egyptian Gods</hi> ſhould be the <hi>God</hi> that delivered the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> out of the hand of <hi>Egypt;</hi> and ſent all thoſe <hi>Plagues</hi> upon their own ſervants. But eſpecially that <hi>thick darkneſs</hi> under which they lay for three days, ſeems to be a very odd <hi>Effect</hi> for the Sun to have wrought. But to quit ſuch <hi>Suppoſitions;</hi> Two things there are by which it undoubtedly appears that the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> in theſe <hi>Caſes,</hi> could not have deſign'd any return to the <hi>Egyptian Idolatry.</hi> For,</p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="65" facs="tcp:99012:42"/>1. As to the <hi>Golden-Calf,</hi> it is ſaid that they <hi>offer'd burnt offerings, and brought Peace offerings unto it.</hi> And <hi>Jeroboam</hi> ſacrificed unto the <hi>Calves</hi> which he had made and <hi>Conſecrated Prieſts with</hi> a bullock and <hi>ſeven</hi> rams to their Service.</p>
            <p>Now all this was moſt agreeable to what <hi>God</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired in his Service: but ſo utterly repugnant to the <hi>Superſtition</hi> of the <hi>Egyptians</hi> that our Author himſelf confeſſes <hi>God</hi> commanded their beaſts to be offer'd in Sacrifice to him, in contempt of the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>credneſs in which they were held by thoſe <hi>Idolaters.</hi> He tells us <q>That to offer a <hi>young Ram</hi> was the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt affront that could be put upon the <hi>Egyptians,</hi> who held a <hi>Ram</hi> not onely in religious eſteem, but the moſt ſacred of all their <hi>Holy Animals.</hi> And particularly upon the account of the ſacred<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of theſe <hi>Animals,</hi> the <hi>Egyptians</hi> (ſays he) <hi>NEVER OFFER'D</hi> any of their Species in Sacrifice. In ſo much that when <hi>Pharaoh</hi> bid <hi>Moſes</hi> go ſacrifice to the Lord in the Land of <hi>Egypt,
<note place="margin">Exod. 8.26.</note> Moſes</hi> anſwers that they durſt not doe it, <hi>becauſe it would be an Abomination to the</hi> Egyptians, ſo that they would <hi>ſtone them:</hi> that is, it would be a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaneneſs and open affront to the Religion of the <hi>Egyptians</hi> if they ſhould offer in Sacrifice thoſe very Animals that the <hi>Egyptians</hi> had conſecrated to the Honour of their Gods. And for the ſame reaſon the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> were alſo commanded to Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice <hi>young-Bullocks,</hi> as well as <hi>Rams;</hi> for that next to a <hi>Ram</hi> the <hi>Bullock</hi> was the moſt <hi>Sacred</hi> of all the <hi>Holy Animals.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Our <hi>Author</hi> is very large on this Argument; but I think what I have here offer'd, is little leſs
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:99012:43"/>than a <hi>demonſtration</hi> againſt him as to this <hi>point;</hi> that the Jews in the Worſhip of their <hi>Calves</hi> did not return to the <hi>Idolatry</hi> of <hi>Egypt,</hi> ſeeing they offer'd ſuch <hi>Sacrifices</hi> before them as by his own confeſſion were <hi>an open affront to the Religion of the</hi> Egyptians.</p>
            <p n="2">2dly. It is evident from <hi>Holy Scripture,</hi> that the <hi>Idolatry</hi> of theſe <hi>Calves</hi> was a diſtinct <hi>Idolatry</hi> from that of <hi>worſhipping</hi> the <hi>Heavenly Bodies;</hi> and accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Eſtimate which <hi>God</hi> himſelf put upon it, much leſs heinous. And this we find in both the <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances</hi> before mention'd. For as to the <hi>Golden Calf, Stephen</hi> ſays Acts 7.41, 42. <q>That <hi>they made a Calf</hi> in thoſe days, and oſſer'd Sacrifice to the Idol, and rejoyced in the work of their hands; <hi>THEN God gave them up to worſhip the Hoſt of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven.</hi>
               </q> Now here muſt be a manifeſt difference al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low'd between theſe two, ſeeing the one is repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted as the <hi>puniſhment</hi> of the <hi>other,</hi> and what a ridicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous <hi>paraphraſe</hi> would it make of theſe words, to ſuppoſe that they <hi>Adored</hi> the <hi>Sun</hi> in both; viz. <q>That for worſhiping the <hi>Sun,</hi> under the <hi>Symbol</hi> of the <hi>Golden Calf,</hi> God gave them up to worſhip the <hi>Sun</hi> under the <hi>name</hi> of <hi>Moloch.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>As for <hi>Jeroboam's Calves,</hi> we find this alſo diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh'd from that of worſhiping the Heavenly Hoſt. For thus the <hi>Idolatry</hi> of <hi>Ahab</hi> was aggravated a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him; 1 Kings 16.31. That <q>
                  <hi>as if it had been a ſmall thing for Him to walk in the Sins of</hi> Jeroboam <hi>the Son of</hi> Nebat; <hi>He went and ſerved</hi> Baal, <hi>and worſhipped Him.</hi>
               </q> Now if the <hi>Idolatry</hi> of the <hi>Golden Calves</hi> was the worſhip of the <hi>Sun</hi> too, (as this Author would have it,) then this paſſage concerning <hi>Ahab</hi> muſt be expounded in this
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:99012:43"/>manner; <q>That as if it had been a ſmall thing for him to worſhip the <hi>Sun</hi> under the <hi>Calves,</hi> He even proceeded to ſuch a height of <hi>Impiety;</hi> as to wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip the <hi>Sun</hi> under the name of <hi>Baal.</hi>
               </q> But 4thly, and to conclude this Point; That under the <hi>Calves</hi> they worſhiped the <hi>true God,</hi> is evident from the whole Courſe of the Hiſtory of the ten Tribes, and of the <hi>State</hi> of <hi>Religion</hi> under them. We find <hi>God</hi> as well revealing himſelf to theſe as to the other two. His Prophets came amongſt them, and though they of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten inveigh'd againſt their <hi>Altars,</hi> yet never charged them as deſerters of the <hi>God</hi> of <hi>Iſrael.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nay, in many <hi>Caſes</hi> we find thoſe who worſhiped the <hi>Golden Calves,</hi> yet accepted by <hi>God</hi> as zealous in his Service. I ſhall inſtead of many, offer onely one Example, that of <hi>Jehu.</hi> 2 Kings 10.16. who as he was expreſly deſign'd by <hi>God</hi> to be <hi>King</hi> over <hi>Iſrael,</hi> ſo he there bids <hi>Jehonadab,</hi> 
               <q>come and ſee his Zeal for the <hi>LORD.</hi>
               </q> Now the <hi>zeal</hi> he there meant was in deſtroying of <hi>Baal</hi> out of <hi>Iſrael.</hi> This he moſt Effectually did, as may be ſeen at large in that <hi>Chapter;</hi> and for the doing of it, had the Throne confirm'd by <hi>God</hi> to his Poſterity for <hi>four Generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</hi> I ſhall therefore make bold to conclude, that <hi>Jehu</hi> was no worſhipper of <hi>Baal</hi> or the <hi>Sun,</hi> but of the <hi>God of Iſrael,</hi> whoſe Service he promoted, and for whom <hi>Elijah</hi> not long before had appeared in oppoſition to this very <hi>Baal,</hi> 1 Kings 18.21. <hi>How long</hi> (ſays he) <hi>Halt ye between two opinions, if the Lord be God follow him;
<note place="margin">2 <hi>Kings</hi> 10.29, 31.</note> but if BAAL</hi> then follow him. And yet <hi>Jehu ſtill worſhip'd the Golden Calves</hi> that <hi>were in</hi> Bethel, <hi>and that were in</hi> Dan; He obſerved not to walk in the Law of the <hi>LORD
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:99012:44"/>God of Iſral</hi> with <hi>ALL HIS HEART, ſeeing he departed not from the Sin</hi> of Jeroboam <hi>which made</hi> Iſrael to <hi>Sin.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I conclude upon the whole, that that cannot be the <hi>true</hi> and <hi>ONELT Notion</hi> of <hi>Idolatry</hi> which this Author pretends, viz. <q>
                  <hi>The giving the worſhip of the Supreme God to ſome Created Corporeal or viſible Deity,</hi>
               </q> 
               <hi>as ſuppoſing it to be the Supreme deity,</hi> ſince (as we have now ſeen) to worſhip even the <hi>true God,</hi> under the worſhip of ſome <hi>Corporeal Symbol</hi> or <hi>repreſentation,</hi> as the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> did in theſe <hi>Calves,</hi> is in the account of the <hi>Holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture</hi> to commit <hi>Idolatry.</hi> I go on,</p>
            <p n="2">2dly. To ſhew: That to worſhip any <hi>other God,</hi> beſides the <hi>God</hi> of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> whether it be ſo as to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake the <hi>true God,</hi> or but onely to joyn the worſhip of any <hi>other with him;</hi> This is alſo according to the ſenſe of Holy Scripture, to commit Idolatry.</p>
            <p>Now this will appear from the Examples of this kind of <hi>Idolatry,</hi> that occur in thoſe <hi>Sacred Writings;</hi> I ſhall mention onely an <hi>Inſtance</hi> or two in either kind. And,
<q>1ſt. That to give <hi>divine worſhip</hi> to any other than to the God of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> though they do not worſhip that <hi>Being</hi> as the <hi>Supreme deity,</hi> but on the Contrary worſhip the <hi>true God</hi> together with it, is according to the Cenſure of the <hi>Holy Scripture</hi> Idolatry.</q>
            </p>
            <p>This was the <hi>Caſe</hi> of <hi>Solomon</hi> in ſome of the laſt years of his Life, for however, at the perſuaſion of his <hi>Wives;</hi> he neglected very much the Service of
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:99012:44"/>the <hi>true God,</hi> yet we do not find that he utterly for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſook either the <hi>Worſhip</hi> or the <hi>Acknowledgment</hi> of him. On the Contrary, the <hi>Holy Scripture</hi> plainly enough inſinuates, that he ſtill ſerved the <hi>God of Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael,</hi> and his fault was, that he did not ſerve him onely, but worſhiped <hi>Moloch,</hi> and <hi>Chemoſh</hi> and <hi>Aſhtoreth,</hi> and <hi>Milcom</hi> together with him. For thus ſpeaking of his <hi>Idolatry</hi> it ſays, 1 Kings 11.4. <hi>That his heart was not</hi> perfect, <hi>with the Lord his God:</hi> and again ver. 6. <hi>That he went not</hi> fully <hi>af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Lord</hi> as did <hi>David his Father, i.e.</hi> He did not wholly give up himſelf to ſerve the Lord, and him <hi>ONELT</hi> as his Father had done.</p>
            <p>Another, and a more notable Inſtance of this we meet with in 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 18. Where the King of <hi>Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyria</hi> having led the ten Tribes into Captivity, and planted ſome of his own Subjects in their Countrey, we read <hi>ver.</hi> 24.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>ver.</hi> 25.</note> that <hi>God ſent</hi> 
               <q>
                  <hi>Lions amongſt them to deſtroy them,</hi>
               </q> becauſe they neglected to worſhip him. Upon this the King of <hi>Aſſyria</hi> ordered one of the Prieſts of <hi>Bethel</hi> to go up and teach them,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>ver.</hi> 27.</note> 
               <q>
                  <hi>the manner of the God of the Land; then</hi> one <hi>of the</hi> Prieſts <hi>whom they had carried away from</hi> Samaria,
<note place="margin">28.</note> 
                  <hi>came and dwelt in</hi> Bethel, <hi>and taught them how they ſhould</hi> fear <hi>or ſerve the Lord. Hombeit every man made</hi> Gods <hi>of his own, and ſo they ſeared the Lord and ſerved their</hi> own Gods <hi>and their</hi> Graven Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Such was the State of theſe <hi>Samaritans,</hi> and their practice will furniſh us with two very uſefull Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marks upon this Occaſion. For 1. Since theſe <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maritans</hi> were puniſhed for not <hi>worſhiping</hi> the <hi>God of the Countrey, i.e.</hi> of the God whom the <hi>Iſraelites</hi>
               <pb n="70" facs="tcp:99012:45"/>were wont to worſhip; it follows that the God of the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> was not the ſame with the <hi>God</hi> of the <hi>Sama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritans:</hi> And therefore ſince theſe are ſuppoſed to have worſhipped the <hi>Sun,</hi> it follows that the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> did not worſhip the <hi>Sun;</hi> but ſome other and him the <hi>true God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2dly. That theſe <hi>Samaritans</hi> at the ſame time that they committed <hi>Idolatry</hi> in ſerving their <hi>own Gods,</hi> did alſo both <hi>know</hi> and <hi>fear</hi> the <hi>true God,</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore their <hi>Idolatry</hi> could not conſiſt in giving the worſhip of the <hi>Supreme God,</hi> to their <hi>created</hi> and <hi>viſible Deities,</hi> as <hi>ſuppoſing them ſo to be.</hi> But their Sin was that they gave <hi>divine worſhip</hi> to their own <hi>falſe Gods,</hi> after they had been inſtructed in the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of the <hi>true,</hi> and joyned both the one and the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in their <hi>Religious Service.</hi> But,
<q>2dly. As it was therefore thought to be <hi>Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try,</hi> to worſhip any other <hi>being</hi> together with <hi>God,</hi> ſo muſt it much more have been eſteemed ſo, to <hi>forſake</hi> the <hi>true God,</hi> and worſhip any other <hi>Corporeal</hi> and <hi>viſible Dei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>An Inſtance of this we ſeem to have in <hi>Ahab,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Kings</hi> 16.30.</note> who ſeduced by <hi>Jezabel</hi> his <hi>Wife, did evil in the ſight of</hi> the <hi>Lord, above all that were before him,</hi> and what this was we find in the next <hi>verſe,</hi> viz. That not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent with the <hi>Idolatry</hi> of <hi>Jeroboam,</hi> in worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>God</hi> after an <hi>Idolatrous manner,</hi> he utterly <hi>for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſook</hi> him and ſerved <hi>Baal,</hi> and built a <hi>Temple</hi> and an <hi>Altar</hi> for him.</p>
            <p>Now that <hi>Ahab</hi> had utterly laid aſide the Service of the <hi>true God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Kings</hi> 18.4.</note> ſeems evident upon two accounts, 1ſt. Of the Great perſecution that he ſuffered his <hi>Wife</hi>
               <pb n="71" facs="tcp:99012:45"/>to make of the Prophets of the <hi>LORD,</hi> 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 18.4. When as <hi>Obadiah</hi> tells <hi>Elijah,</hi> he hid them in <hi>Caves</hi> from her fury. 2dly. From the miſerable <hi>State</hi> of the Kingdom, in that time as we find <hi>Elijah</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porting it even to <hi>God himſelf,</hi> 1 Kings 19.14. <q>
                  <hi>The Children of Iſrael,</hi> ſays he, <hi>have forſaken thy Covenant, thrown down thy Altars,</hi> and ſlain thy Prophets <hi>with the Sword, and I even I onely am left, and they ſeek my Life to take it away.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Indeed it is not to be doubted, but that the Idolatry of this time was very deplorable. But now whereindid it conſiſt? Did <hi>Ahab</hi> worſhip <hi>Baal</hi> or the <hi>Sun</hi> as a <hi>Corporeal Deity,</hi> ſo as to exclude all <hi>Senſe</hi> and <hi>appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion</hi> of a <hi>Superiour, Spiritual</hi> and <hi>Inviſible God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head?</hi> This is not credible, ſeeing throughout his whole Reign we find him correſponding upon all occaſions with the <hi>Prophets</hi> of the <hi>LORD,</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſure he could not be without ſome <hi>Senſe</hi> and <hi>ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion</hi> of him.</p>
            <p>And what I have now ſhewn in the Example of <hi>Ahab</hi> I will yet farther confirm in another, that will perhaps be liable to leſs exception, and that is the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of <hi>Manaſſe</hi> King of <hi>Judah.</hi> This King not content to forſake the <hi>God</hi> of his Fathers ſet up his <hi>Idolatry</hi> in the very Temple of the Lord; but yet neither had he loſt all <hi>ſenſe</hi> and <hi>apprehenſion</hi> of a <hi>ſpiritual</hi> and <hi>Inviſible Godhead.</hi> He had been bred up by his Father in the knowledge of the <hi>true God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 <hi>Chr.</hi> 33.10.</note> the <hi>Prophets</hi> of the <hi>LORD</hi> ſtill continued to put him in mind of his danger, and no ſooner did he feel the puniſhment of his <hi>Rebellion,</hi> but he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned to his <hi>God,</hi> ver. 12. <q>
                  <hi>When he was in afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on he beſought the Lord his God, and humbled him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:99012:46"/>greatly before the God of his Fathers.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>And thus have I taken a ſhort <hi>View</hi> of the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral ſorts of <hi>Idolatry</hi> which occur in the <hi>Old Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> and from thence it appears, that this ſin is conſiſtent not onely with the <hi>acknowledgment</hi> but even with the <hi>worſhip</hi> of the <hi>true Supreme Deity,</hi> and therefore that it is a very falſe account, which this Author has here given us of it, <hi>viz.</hi> 
               <q>
                  <hi>That</hi> Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try <hi>is neither more nor leſs than the Worſhip of the</hi> heavenly bodies,
<note place="margin">Pag. 74.</note> the Sun, Moon <hi>and</hi> Stars or <hi>any other</hi> viſible and <hi>Corporeal</hi> Deity <hi>as the S<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>PREME</hi> God;
<note place="margin">Pag. 80, 81.</note> or as he elſewhere defines it, <hi>that Idolatry is the giving the worſhip of the</hi> Supreme God <hi>to any</hi> Created, Corporeal <hi>or</hi> Viſible Deity, and <hi>to ſuppoſe ſuch a</hi> Being <hi>the</hi> Supreme Deity is the <hi>ONELY,</hi>
               </q> 
               <hi>TR<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>E</hi> and <hi>PROPER IDOLATRY.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But before I quit this <hi>point</hi> it may not be amiſs to obſerve yet one inſtance more of <hi>Idolatry,</hi> (I am ſure generally ſuppoſed at leaſt to be ſo) and which I cannot tell whether it may properly be reduced to any of the foregoing kinds, and it is that of the <hi>Brazen-Serpent</hi> to which the Children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> burnt <hi>Incenſe</hi> in <hi>Hezekiah</hi>'s time, as we may ſee 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 18.4. This pious King obſerving their ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition cauſed it to be broke into pieces, and we find this recorded among the Reſt of <hi>his Enterprizes,</hi> for Rooting <hi>Idolatry</hi> out of his Country. <q>
                  <hi>He Removed the</hi> High places and <hi>brake the</hi> Images, and <hi>cut down</hi> the Groves, and <hi>brake in pieces the</hi> Brazen-Serpent, <hi>that</hi> Moſes <hi>had made: for unto thoſe days the Children of</hi> Iſrael <hi>did burn</hi> Incenſe <hi>to it,</hi>
               </q> 
               <hi>and he called it</hi> Nehuſhtan.</p>
            <pb n="73" facs="tcp:99012:46"/>
            <p>I do not believe that even this <hi>Author</hi> himſelf will have the confidence to ſay that this was an <hi>Image</hi> of either the <hi>Sun, Moon</hi> or <hi>Stars,</hi> or of any other <hi>Viſible</hi> and <hi>Corporeal Deity,</hi> or that the people <hi>Worſhiped</hi> it as ſuppoſing it to be <hi>the Supreme God,</hi> ſo as to exclude all <hi>ſenſe</hi> and <hi>apprehenſion</hi> of a <hi>ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual and Inviſible Godhead,</hi> and yet the learned men on both ſides confeſs, that here was <hi>Idolatry</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, though it may be <hi>the people</hi> were far from thinking that they did ſo, and then it will remain <q>that to give any <hi>appropriate Acts</hi> of <hi>divine Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip</hi> to any <hi>Creature,</hi> whatever <hi>ſenſe</hi> men have of the <hi>thing</hi> to which they give them, or their <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenſion</hi> be in ſo doing, is nevertheleſs eſteemed by <hi>God</hi> to be <hi>Idolatry.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="5" type="chapter">
            <pb n="74" facs="tcp:99012:47"/>
            <head>CHAP. V. <hi>The objections againſt the Notion of</hi> Idolatry <hi>laid down in the foregoing</hi> Chapter <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider'd, and refuted.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>SInce I firſt began the examination of this <hi>Book,</hi> I have been under ſome temptations to doubt whether the <hi>Author</hi> of it really deſigned to ſerve the intereſt of thoſe of the <hi>Church of Rome</hi> in the writing of it, or by a ſeeming defence of their <hi>Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry,</hi> intended onely to ſhew how little he could ſay in their behalf, and to give us an occaſion by Anſwering his Arguments to convince the World upon what juſt <hi>Grounds</hi> we advance that <hi>Charge</hi> againſt them.</p>
            <p>It does indeed a little ſtartle me when I conſider how baſe a thing it is, and unbecoming the Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter of a <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> to put on onely an <hi>appearance of Zeal</hi> in behalf of a <hi>Party,</hi> to whom it muſt be confeſs'd he has been highly Obliged, and whom therefore if he <hi>could not ſerve,</hi> yet at leaſt he <hi>ought not to have betray'd.</hi> But then it ſeems to be ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing worſe, I do not now ſay for a <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> but for a <hi>Biſhop</hi> that has not yet quitted either the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venues</hi> or the <hi>Communion</hi> of the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> nor retracted the <hi>ſubſcription</hi> he once made of this very <hi>charge of Idolatry</hi> againſt thoſe for whom he would now be thought to plead; to revile that <hi>Church</hi> which nouriſhes him, and whoſe <hi>Opinions</hi> we muſt
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:99012:47"/>ſuppoſe him to hold, till we ſee him as <hi>formally</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce them, as ever he once <hi>ſubſcribed</hi> to them. And if on the one hand he ſeems to ſhew a great deal of bitterneſs againſt us in his <hi>Expreſſions,</hi> yet on the other, it muſt be confeſſed his Arguments are ſo <hi>extremely civil</hi> as not to carry ſo much as the <hi>appearance of Reaſon</hi> in them. And few of the <hi>Romaniſts</hi> have ever undertaken this cauſe, that have not ſaid a great deal more in their <hi>own defence,</hi> than this <hi>Amphibious Advocate</hi> has offer'd <hi>for them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But whether this <hi>Author</hi> deſigned to expoſe <hi>them</hi> or <hi>us</hi> or <hi>himſelf</hi> onely, as I am not much concern'd to know, ſo neither will I undertake to determine. This is plain, that had he meant to ridicule the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi> never ſo much, he could not have taken a more effectual way of doing it. And whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther our <hi>Nobility do,</hi> or <hi>can,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pag. 9.</note> or <hi>ought</hi> to underſtand <hi>Tranſubſtantiation</hi> or no, yet I am ſure men of much meaner capacities than thoſe <hi>Honourable Perſonages</hi> for the moſt part are, will be able to diſcern the truth of this remark. And that he muſt indeed have thought them not onely <hi>uncapable of judging of Abſtruſe propoſitions,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ibid.</note> but even deſtitute of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon <hi>ſenſe</hi> and <hi>reaſon,</hi> if he hoped to impoſe ſuch <hi>diſcourſe</hi> as this upon them for <hi>Arguing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now to make this appear, I ſhall need onely de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire the <hi>Reader</hi> to obſerve with me theſe two things:</p>
            <p n="1">I. That the poſition he undertakes to defend is, that the notion of <hi>Idolatry</hi> in holy Scripture is nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>MORE</hi> nor <hi>LESS</hi> than this.
<note place="margin">Pag. 74.</note> 
               <q>
                  <hi>The worſhip of the Heavenly bodies, the Sun, the Moon, and the Stars, or any other viſible and Corporeal Deity, as the
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:99012:48"/>Supreme God, ſo as to exclude all ſenſe and apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of</hi> a ſpiritual and inviſible Godhead.</q>
            </p>
            <p n="2">II. That to prove this, it is not ſufficient to ſhew, that this is <hi>Idolatry,</hi> or that the <hi>Jews</hi> did ſometimes fall into it: But it muſt be ſhewn that they never committed any other <hi>Idolatry;</hi> and particularly that this was the <hi>Idolatry</hi> of the <hi>Golden-Calf,</hi> and of the <hi>Calves</hi> of <hi>Dan,</hi> and <hi>Bethel.</hi> For though the <hi>worſhip of the Heavenly Bodies,</hi> (as the <hi>Author</hi> repreſents it) were one ſort of <hi>Idolatry,</hi> yet if the Scripture has charged the <hi>Jews</hi> with this <hi>Guilt</hi> for any <hi>other worſhip,</hi> wherein they did not adore <hi>the Sun, Moon</hi> and <hi>Stars, or any other viſible and Corporeal Deity as the Supreme God,</hi> it will then follow that this, which is alledged,
<note place="margin">Pag. 80, 81.</note> cannot be the <hi>ONELY Notion</hi> of <hi>Idolatry,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Page 74.</note> and it muſt be falſe to aſſert, that <hi>Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try</hi> according to the <hi>word of God</hi> is neither <hi>MORE</hi> nor <hi>LESS</hi> than this.</p>
            <p>Now from theſe two <hi>remarks</hi> onely, it will pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently appear what ſlender pretences ſome men will take up with to run out into the moſt exceſſive cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours againſt thoſe whom they oppoſe. For, 1ſt. As to what he ſo largely inſiſts upon, as if there were ſomething very important at the bottom of it, viz.
<note place="margin">Pag. 83.</note> 
               <hi>That the Jews were a people prone to Idolatry, and that the deſign of God throughout the whole Law, was to preſerve them from it,</hi> though it be a great truth, yet it is certainly in this place a great imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinence. Seeing neither do we deny this, nor can he make any uſe of it, in eſtabliſhing his <hi>true</hi> and <hi>onely notion of Idolatry.</hi> For I hope he did not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to argue thus, <hi>The</hi> Jews <hi>were very prone to Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry, and God intended his Law</hi> to reſtrain them
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:99012:48"/>from it; Therefore <hi>Idolatry</hi> is neither <hi>more</hi> nor <hi>leſs,</hi> than the worſhip of the <hi>Heavenly bodies, the Sun, Moon and Stars,</hi> as the <hi>Supreme Deity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2dly. It will from hence appear, that all thoſe paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſages of <hi>Holy Scripture,</hi> where God charges the <hi>Jews</hi> with <hi>worſhiping other Gods,</hi> with <hi>ſerving the Hoaſt of Heaven,</hi> &amp;c. conclude nothing, ſeeing it is confeſſed that they did fall into <hi>this Idolatry too;</hi> but that does not hinder but that they may have fallen into <hi>ſome other</hi> beſides; and we are aſſured that ſo they did; nay, that they were ſuffered by God to fall into this, as a <hi>puniſhment</hi> for having committed the other, ſo St. <hi>Stephen</hi> expreſly tells us, <hi>Acts</hi> 7.41, 42. <hi>They made a Calf in thoſe days, and offered Sacrifice to the Idol, and rejoyced in the work of their hands. THEN God gave them up to worſhip the Hoaſt of Heaven.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nor is it any more to the purpoſe, 3dly,
<note place="margin">Pag. 99.</note> to prove that the <hi>Scripture</hi> ſays, that to worſhip the <hi>Sun</hi> and <hi>Moon</hi> is <hi>Idolatry;</hi> unleſs he could find out ſome <hi>Text</hi> where it adds, <hi>that they who worſhiped the</hi> Sun <hi>and</hi> Moon, <hi>worſhiped them as</hi> viſible <hi>and</hi> Corporeal Dei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties <hi>with the Honor due to the</hi> Supreme God; <hi>and ſo as to exclude all</hi> ſenſe <hi>and</hi> apprehenſion <hi>of a</hi> ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual <hi>and</hi> inviſible Godhead, <hi>and that this is the true and onely Idolatry.</hi> But now this which was the <hi>onely point</hi> in queſtion, he has prudently forgot, and whilſt he lives will never be able to prove it.</p>
            <p>In ſhort if there be any thing more than <hi>noiſe</hi> and <hi>ſhew</hi> in what he has ſaid, it muſt be in his Account of the <hi>two points</hi> before conſider'd. <hi>viz. The Golden-Calf</hi> and the <hi>Calves</hi> of <hi>Dan</hi> and of <hi>Bethel:</hi> For as for the <hi>Brazen-Serpent</hi> and the <hi>honor</hi> paid to that, he is as ſilent as if there had been no ſuch thing in his <hi>Bible.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="78" facs="tcp:99012:49"/>
            <p>For the former of theſe, the <hi>Golden-Calf,</hi> he ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patiates very much, but ſure never were <hi>Words</hi> put together with leſs pertinence than here. The thing to be proved is,
<note place="margin">Pag. 84. 85, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>that the</hi> Jews <hi>intended by this</hi> Calf <hi>to worſhip the</hi> Egyptian Apis <hi>or</hi> Serapis <hi>or</hi> Oſyris, <hi>that is, the</hi> Sun <hi>as the</hi> Supreme Deity.</p>
            <p>But how does he go about to prove this. <hi>Firſt,</hi> He learnedly ſhews that the <hi>Apis</hi> whom the <hi>Egyp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians</hi> worſhiped was not the <hi>King</hi> of the <hi>Argives,</hi> nor <hi>Son</hi> to <hi>Jupiter.</hi> And this I think may be foreign enough to what we are ſeeking, which is the deſign of the <hi>Jews</hi> in ſetting up the <hi>Golden-Calf. Secondly.</hi> He aſſures us 'tis much more propable that the <hi>Greeks</hi> borrowed the very word <hi>Apis</hi> from the <hi>Egyptians.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pag. 87.</note> And thereupon he takes occaſion to make a Learned reflexion upon our <hi>Tranſlation</hi> of <hi>Jer.</hi> 46.15. which it may be was one of the paſſages for which he has been wont to cenſure our <hi>verſion</hi> with as little <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſty</hi> as <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding.</hi> For to ſay no more of it than this, if we have rendred this Verſe amiſs we have erred not onely with all the Learned <hi>Verſions</hi> the <hi>Syriack,</hi> the <hi>Chaldee Paraphraſe,</hi> and even the <hi>Vulgar Latin</hi> it ſelf, but with the <hi>Original Hebrew</hi> too; and in all which there is this onely Difference, that what they call <hi>Valiant</hi> in one Number, we ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der <hi>Valiant Men</hi> in the other. And all this is ſtill as impertinent to the <hi>Point</hi> in hand, as any thing can well be imagined to be.</p>
            <p>And yet from this, <hi>Thirdly,</hi> He boldly infers, <q>
                  <hi>That the Calf muſt have been the</hi> Symbol <hi>of ſome</hi> Egyptian Idol,
<note place="margin">Ibid.</note> 
                  <hi>and that the people thinking them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves betray'd or deſerted by</hi> Moſes <hi>after fourty days abſence forced</hi> Aaron <hi>to reſtore to them the Symbols
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:99012:49"/>of their old Gods to go before them, inſtead of this new God that ſeemed to have deſerted them.</hi>
               </q> And this indeed is pertinent, but it has another terrible <hi>defect, viz.</hi> that it wants proof. In ſhort the onely <hi>reaſon</hi> he has to offer for what he ſays, is this; <hi>That all their other worſhip ſeems to have been forced and conſtrained, but this is free and voluntary: And that there could be no other Ground of that great joy they ſhew'd on this occaſion, but that they were reſtored to the Exerciſe of their former Religion.</hi> And to this I have many things to reply.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> That this is at beſt but a <hi>plauſible preſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> and ſuch as if compared with the <hi>reaſons</hi> I have alledged to the contrary, will not be thought to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the name of an <hi>Argument.</hi> For,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> Whereas this <hi>Author</hi> (always <hi>poſitive,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pag. 88.</note> if that might paſs for <hi>proof)</hi> ſays, <hi>that there could be no other ground of this joy than that they were reſtored to the worſhip of their old Gods;</hi> I would fain know how he comes to be aſſured of this? I am confident were it fit to eſtabliſh a <hi>Principle</hi> of this moment upon the <hi>ſandy Foundation</hi> of our own <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jectures,</hi> one might be able to find out other reaſons for it. For why might they not have had juſt cauſe of rejoycing to behold a <hi>Symbol</hi> of their <hi>own God</hi> ſet up amongſt them, as well as if it had been a figure of an <hi>Egyptian Idol?</hi> what if deſpairing of <hi>Moſes</hi>'s re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn to them, as they deſign'd this <hi>Symbol</hi> to ſupply his place, to direct them in their journey, and to be an <hi>Oracle</hi> at which they might continually enquire <hi>God</hi>'s pleaſure, ſo they teſtified ſome tranſports of joy upon the erecting of it? Nay but,</p>
            <pb n="80" facs="tcp:99012:50"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> What if we ſhould ſay that we cannot diſcern any ſuch <hi>extraordinary joy,</hi> more than what the <hi>Solemnity</hi> of a <hi>Feaſt</hi> Dedicated to the <hi>JEHOVAH</hi> for the ſetting up of a viſible <hi>Symbol</hi> of his <hi>preſence</hi> amongſt them might very well warrant? The caſe in ſhort was this; <hi>Moſes</hi> delay'd to come down from the <hi>Mount,</hi> the people were impatient to continue on their Journey towards the <hi>Promiſed Land;</hi> but how to learn <hi>God</hi>'s pleaſure they knew not, and for this purpoſe they cryed unto <hi>Aaron,</hi> that he would make them a <hi>God to go before them;</hi> ſuch as very probably they had ſeen in <hi>Egypt,</hi> and which might ſerve inſtead of an <hi>Oracle</hi> unto them. This <hi>Aaron</hi> makes, and for the <hi>Dedication</hi> of it appoints <hi>a Feaſt unto the Lord,</hi> and offers ſuch <hi>Sacrifices</hi> as <hi>God</hi> indeed required, but which this <hi>Author</hi> himſelf confeſſes were an <hi>Abomination to the Egyptians:</hi> And upon the occaſion of this <hi>Feaſt</hi> it was that it is ſaid, <hi>They rejoyced in the works of their hands.</hi> Acts 7.41. And again, <hi>The people ſate down to eat and drink and roſe up to play,</hi> 1 Cor. 10.7. And what this joy was we find particularly expreſſed, <hi>Exod.</hi> 32:19. <hi>They were ſinging, and dancing before the Calf.</hi> Now all this was very natural on ſuch an occaſion; and what ever ſin they committed in it, yet I cannot ſee any ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity there is to conclude that there could be no <hi>other ground for ſuch a joy than their returning to the Idols of Egypt.</hi> And the Arguments I have before given clearly ſhew that whatever its was, it could not be that, ſeeing that the whole Solemnity was conſecra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the <hi>JEHOVAH,</hi> and performed in a manner utterly inconſiſtent with the <hi>Egyptian Idolatry.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="81" facs="tcp:99012:50"/>
            <p>As for the <hi>Calves</hi> of <hi>Dan</hi> and <hi>Bethel,</hi> our <hi>Author</hi> has (if poſſible) yet leſs to ſay againſt their being the <hi>Symbols</hi> of the <hi>God of Iſrael,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pag. 93.</note> than he had in the <hi>for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Caſe.</hi> He produces onely the Learned <hi>Viſorius</hi> to prove that <hi>Monceius</hi> was miſtaken in imagining that <hi>Jeroboam</hi> ſet up theſe <hi>Calves</hi> in imitation of <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon's Cherubim.</hi> But now this is not our <hi>queſtion,</hi> whether the <hi>Calves</hi> were made in imitation of the <hi>Cherubim,</hi> but whether the <hi>God of Iſrael,</hi> or the <hi>Gods of Egypt</hi> were worſhiped by the <hi>Ten Tribes</hi> at <hi>Dan</hi> and <hi>Bethel?</hi> And yet without ſaying one pertinent word, he concludes, with as good Aſſurance as if he had made a demonſtration of it; <q>
                  <hi>So that it is plain that theſe Calves were ſet up by him as Idols, or Symbols of a new or ſeparate Religion from the Tribe of Judah.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>One thing indeed there is that may ſeem to deſerve an <hi>Anſwer,</hi> and that is, why the people for three whole years did not comply with him, if he kept up the <hi>old Religion</hi> that had been eſtabliſhed under <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> and <hi>Solomon?</hi> But now this is a groſs <hi>Miſtake</hi> in a perſon that would be thought ſo <hi>Learned in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures.</hi> The people did comply very readily with <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roboam,</hi> and were far from refuſing for any ſuch time as is pretended. And that paſſage to which this <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor</hi> muſt, I ſuppoſe, refer 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 11.17. is ſpoken not of the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> but of the <hi>Kingdom of Judah;</hi> namely, <hi>that for three-years they walked in the way of David and Solomon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now let any reaſonable man conſider what a pitifull <hi>Vindication</hi> is this, to ſupport ſo much <hi>Cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour</hi> and <hi>confidence?</hi> And how muſt all men of ſenſe, even in the <hi>Roman Communion</hi> deſpiſe ſuch tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fling
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:99012:51"/>after what they have ſeen their own <hi>Dr. Godden</hi> perform upon this very ſubject? The truth is we ought to give that <hi>Learned Man</hi> his due. He has ſaid what was to be ſaid to excuſe his <hi>Church</hi> from <hi>Idolatry;</hi> and his performance ſhews that he wanted nothing but a better <hi>Cauſe</hi> to have acquitted himſelf to every one's ſatisfaction. But he had a hard <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſs</hi> to ſerve, and he was not unſenſible of it. But for this new <hi>Advocate</hi> his Arguments are as much ſhort of the <hi>Doctor</hi>'s, as his aſſurance is greater. There the <hi>D.</hi> of <hi>Paul</hi>'s found ſomething worthy his conſideration, but here is nothing but a <hi>great noiſe,</hi> and a great deal of Anger and Scorn, without any juſt oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion, though in ſuch a Caſe the Cauſe ought to be very plain. In ſhort, I cannot imagine any other effect this <hi>Diſcourſe</hi> can poſſibly have than to raiſe the Credit of Dr. <hi>Godden</hi>'s; and after whom it is indeed a bold undertaking for another to engage: for could this <hi>Point</hi> have been <hi>defended,</hi> he was the <hi>Perſon</hi> that of any other ſeems to have been the moſt likely to have done it. But he too has fail'd, and becauſe his performance was good, conſidering the matter of it, the worth of the man argues the badneſs of the <hi>Cauſe,</hi> and the impoſſibility of defending it.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="6" type="chapter">
            <pb n="83" facs="tcp:99012:51"/>
            <head>CHAP. VI. <hi>That the</hi> Account <hi>which has been given of the</hi> Notion <hi>of</hi> Idolatry <hi>under the</hi> Law, <hi>is equally applicable to the Caſe of the</hi> Chriſtians <hi>now. The</hi> Objection <hi>from the</hi> Cherubims <hi>anſwered: and the whole</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded.</head>
            <p>I Am now come to the laſt <hi>point</hi> to be conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and it is indeed ſo neceſſarily conſequent up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the foregoing, that if what I have before ſaid concerning the <hi>Notion</hi> of <hi>Idolatry</hi> under the <hi>Old-Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> be allowed, this cannot be denied: viz. <hi>That as the Jews retaining both the Apprehenſion and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip</hi> of the truely Supreme God, <hi>were nevertheleſs guilty of Idolatry, for worſhiping him after</hi> a Gentile manner, <hi>ſo may</hi> Chriſtians <hi>be now, and therefore that the</hi> Church of Rome <hi>may juſtly be charged by us</hi> as Idolatrous, <hi>though we do not pretend in any wiſe to ſay either that ſhe worſhips the</hi> Sun, Moon, <hi>and</hi> Stars, <hi>or</hi> any <hi>other</hi> viſible <hi>and</hi> Corporeal Deity <hi>as the</hi> Supreme God, <hi>or that ſhe has loſt all</hi> Apprehenſion <hi>of a</hi> Spiritual and inviſible Godhead.</p>
            <p>I ſhall not much enlarge my ſelf upon the <hi>proof</hi> of a <hi>Conſequence,</hi> both in it ſelf very plain, and which this <hi>Author</hi> is ſo far from denying, that his <hi>whole Book</hi> is built upon the <hi>Suppoſal</hi> that he makes of the <hi>truth</hi> of it; It is indeed the onely thing wherein he ſeems to have any reaſon, nor can any thing be more
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:99012:52"/>juſt than for the underſtanding what <hi>Idolatry</hi> is to ſearch the <hi>Holy Scriptures,</hi> and ſee what is there de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared to be ſo.</p>
            <p>As for the <hi>New-Teſtament,</hi> we find the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> earneſt indeed in their <hi>Cautions</hi> againſt <hi>Idolatry,</hi> but we do not ſee that they any where defined the <hi>Nature</hi> of it; They ſpake as to men who underſtood theſe things, and were acquainted with the <hi>Notion</hi> of <hi>Idolatry,</hi> and needed onely to be warn'd againſt fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling into it. They give not the leaſt intimation that it was not the ſame then, it had ever been eſteemed before, or that <hi>Chriſtians</hi> were to think any other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe of it, than the <hi>Jews</hi> had been wont to do under their <hi>Law.</hi> All we can conclude from their <hi>Exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations to</hi> the <hi>Chriſtians</hi> to avoid it is, that <hi>Chriſtians</hi> were capable of falling into it, and by conſequence that Men who have not loſt all <hi>Senſe</hi> and Apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of a <hi>Supreme, Spiritual</hi> and <hi>Inviſible Godhead</hi> may for all that become <hi>Idolaters.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So that to know what the <hi>Scripture Notion</hi> of <hi>Idolatry</hi> is, we muſt with this <hi>Author</hi> ſearch into the Hiſtory of the <hi>Old Teſtament,</hi> and from thence I have ſhewn two <hi>Caſes</hi> wherein Men may without exclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding either the <hi>Senſe</hi> or <hi>Worſhip</hi> of the <hi>true God,</hi> yet juſtly be charged with this Crime. I. By worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the <hi>true God,</hi> by any <hi>Corporeal Image or repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation.</hi> II. By giving <hi>divine Worſhip</hi> to any other beſides <hi>God,</hi> though they do not onely retain the <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> but even the <hi>Adoration</hi> too of the <hi>true God</hi> to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with it.</p>
            <p>It were an eaſie matter to enlarge upon both theſe <hi>points here</hi> in the <hi>Application</hi> of them, but my de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign now is not to accuſe any <hi>particular Church</hi> of this
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:99012:52"/>
               <hi>Guilt,</hi> but onely to ſhew in General what <hi>Idolatry</hi> it ſelf is, and that the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi> though it both <hi>knows</hi> and <hi>worſhips</hi> the <hi>true God</hi> yet may do it in ſuch amanner, and give ſuch <hi>worſhip</hi> to <hi>other beings,</hi> as juſtly to deſerve the cenſure which has been brought againſt her, for any thing this <hi>Author</hi> has ſaid to clear her of it.</p>
            <p>Indeed as to the former of theſe <hi>ways</hi> whereby I pretend a Man may be guilty of <hi>Idolatry,</hi> viz. <hi>By worſhiping God by any Corporeal Image or Repreſenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> he has offer'd ſomewhat in prejudice of it.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>pag.</hi> 125. 127.</note> For did not <hi>God himſelf</hi> command <hi>two Cherubims to be made, and uſed in his worſhip? and were not theſe Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Images ſet up in the place of worſhip, and does not this ſhew that</hi> God <hi>was ſo far from forbidding the uſe of</hi> Images <hi>in his Service, that he would not be worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed without them?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But, to this I anſwer that <hi>God</hi> did indeed com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand two <hi>Cherubims</hi> to be made and placed at the two ends of the <hi>Mercy Seat;</hi> But that they were put there for any uſe to be made of them in his <hi>Service,</hi> or for any other purpoſe than to over-ſhadow the <hi>Mercy Seat,</hi> from whence <hi>God</hi> had promiſed to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver his <hi>Oracles</hi> unto them, this we utterly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny.</p>
            <p>Hence we find that when <hi>God</hi> had directed <hi>Moſes</hi> how to make this Throne of his glory, <hi>Exod.</hi> 25.22. he commanded him, <hi>To put the Mercy Seat a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove upon the Ark of the Teſtimony, and there (ſays he) I will meet thee, and I will commune with thee from above the Mercy Seat from between the two Che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rubims which are upon the Ark,</hi> and in the VIIth. of <hi>Numbers</hi> ver. 89. It is ſaid, That when <hi>Moſes went
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:99012:53"/>into the Tabernacle of the Congregation to ſpeak with God, he heard the Voice of one ſpeaking to him, from off the Mercy Seat, from between the two Cheru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bims.</hi> Now here we may plainly ſee what the <hi>Object</hi> of <hi>Divine Worſhip</hi> was, not the <hi>Cherubim</hi> but the <hi>Inviſible Majeſty</hi> which ſpake from between them, and communed with <hi>Moſes.</hi> The <hi>Mercy Seat</hi> it ſelf was but the place where <hi>God</hi> had promiſed to meet them; The <hi>Cherubim</hi> were the <hi>Ornament,</hi> and <hi>cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring</hi> of that, But neither the <hi>one</hi> nor the other of theſe were the <hi>Object</hi> of <hi>Divine Worſhip,</hi> or <hi>Figures</hi> or <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militudes of that God who</hi> alone was adored there.</p>
            <p>And this the Learned Men of the <hi>Church of Rome</hi> confeſs no leſs than we,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Aquinas</hi> 12. Q. 102. Art. 4. ad 6.</note> 
               <hi>Aquinas</hi> having objected a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the <hi>Second Commandment,</hi> That the <hi>Cherubim</hi> were put in the <hi>Tabernacle</hi> and in the <hi>Temple:</hi> An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers that they were neither put there as <hi>repreſenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of God,</hi> nor for <hi>any Worſhip to be paid to them.</hi> And explaining the <hi>Ark</hi> and all that belong'd to it as a <hi>Myſtery,</hi> he ſays, That the <hi>Holy</hi> of <hi>Holies</hi> repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented <hi>Heaven;</hi> The <hi>Ark</hi> was the <hi>Foot ſtool</hi> of the <hi>Divine Majeſty;</hi> But that becauſe <hi>God</hi> was <hi>Incompre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſible</hi> to any Creature, <hi>propter hoc nulla Similitudo ejus ponebatur,</hi> therefore was there <hi>no Similitude of him placed there</hi> the better to denote his <hi>Inviſibility.</hi> As for the <hi>Cherubim</hi> he ſays they <hi>repreſented</hi> the <hi>mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude</hi> of <hi>Angels</hi> attending upon his <hi>Throne;</hi> and there was therefore <hi>more</hi> than <hi>One, that all worſhip might be excluded from them,</hi> to whom it had been commanded <hi>that they ſhould worſhip</hi> onely one <hi>GOD.</hi> So far was <hi>Aquinas</hi> from thinking — that theſe <hi>Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges</hi> were any <hi>Repreſentations</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> or that any <hi>wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip</hi> was to be paid to them, and the ſame has been
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:99012:53"/>confeſſed by others of no leſs note of that Church, <hi>Vaſquez Lorinus, Azorius</hi> and even by his own <hi>Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſorius,</hi> whom he has before alledged, but is not plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to take notice of on this occaſion.</p>
            <p>But here our <hi>Author</hi> ſuppoſes he has ſomething to boaſt of. For if we may believe him our own great <hi>Defender</hi> of this <hi>charge</hi> has given up the Cauſe as to this matter, and confeſſed that it was <hi>lawfull to wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip TOWARDS</hi> an <hi>Image,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>pag.</hi> 130.</note> but not to give wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip <hi>to one.</hi> This is I fear a wilfull <hi>perverting</hi> of that <hi>Learned man's</hi> words. The <hi>Queſtion</hi> was about the <hi>Jews Adoration towards the Ark, and the holy of Holies.</hi> His <hi>Anſwer</hi> is this; <hi>That they onely directed their worſhip towards the place, where God had promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to be ſignally preſent among them, which</hi> (ſays he) <hi>ſignifies no more to the worſhip of Images, than lifting up our Eyes to Heaven doth when we pray, becauſe God is more eſpecially preſent there.</hi> What is there in all this to allow it to be <hi>lawfull to give worſhip TO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>WARDS an Image, but not to it?</hi> Nay he plainly deni'd that there were <hi>any Images for worſhip</hi> there, <hi>or any worſhip directed towards them.</hi> But there was <hi>a Symbol</hi> of <hi>God's immediate preſence</hi> as on his <hi>Throne</hi> between the <hi>Cherubim,</hi> and this appointed by <hi>God</hi> himſelf, and thither the people <hi>directed their worſhip,</hi> and I deſire this <hi>Author,</hi> if he can, to tell me what there was more in this, than there is in <hi>directing</hi> our <hi>worſhip towards Heaven</hi> when we pray. And whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther according to his <hi>true</hi> and <hi>onely Notion</hi> of <hi>Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try,</hi> he may not as well ſay that we worſhip <hi>Apis</hi> or <hi>Baal</hi> or <hi>Moloch, i. e.</hi> The Sun, Moon, and Stars, in this, as that the <hi>Jews</hi> worſhip'd the <hi>Cherubim</hi> by that?</p>
            <pb n="88" facs="tcp:99012:54"/>
            <p>Nor is there any more Sincerity in what he calls his <hi>Second reply,</hi> and in which he repreſents him as allowing <hi>that the Cherubim might be Adored once a year by the high Prieſt, but not expoſed to the people to worſhip.</hi> For in that very place he denies the <hi>Che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rubim to have been any repreſentations of God, But ſays that his Throne was between them on the Mercy Seat;</hi> and adds in plain words, <hi>That they were never intended for objects of worſhip.</hi> And yet this <hi>Author</hi> inſults and triumphs upon this, in a very glorious manner, as if the Cauſe had been gained by it. Had that <hi>Learned Man</hi> ſaid <hi>that the high Prieſt adored the Cherubims once a year,</hi> then indeed there might have been ſome Colour forthoſe ſweet Expreſſions of <hi>ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs ſhifts and pretences.</hi> But this he utterly deny'd; and he might as well have made him confeſs it to be <hi>law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to worſhip Images,</hi> though he diſputed againſt it, and have brought him in allowing that 'twas no <hi>Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry</hi> ſo to do, as to repreſent him confeſſing that the <hi>high Prieſt adored the Cherubim once every year.</hi> But what defence can there be againſt ſuch <hi>Adverſaries,</hi> as will make men <hi>confeſs</hi> what they <hi>reject,</hi> and <hi>affirm</hi> what they <hi>deny;</hi> and yet when they have done, dare to appeal both to <hi>God</hi> and the <hi>World</hi> for their <hi>Sincerity?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now from what has been ſaid, I will venture to <hi>conclude</hi> in behalf of our <hi>Church,</hi> and of thoſe <hi>Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned men</hi> of our <hi>Communion,</hi> who have been concern'd in this <hi>Controverſie,</hi> that the <hi>Notion</hi> of <hi>Idolatry</hi> which both the one <hi>Teaches,</hi> and the <hi>others</hi> have <hi>Defended,</hi> is after all this <hi>Author</hi>'s Clamours againſt it neither <hi>new</hi> nor <hi>unlearned,</hi> nor <hi>Fanatical,</hi> nor <hi>Anticatholick,</hi> nor <hi>Antichriſtian,</hi> nor any of thoſe ill things he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends;
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:99012:54"/>but the truly <hi>Ancient, Learned,</hi> and <hi>Catholick Notion</hi> of it. The <hi>Notion</hi> which <hi>God</hi> in his Holy Word has Eſtabliſhed; Which the <hi>Jews</hi> received; The <hi>Apoſtles</hi> taught, and the <hi>Chriſtian Church</hi> till theſe latter days, that mens <hi>intereſt</hi> prompted them to ſeek out to themſelves <hi>new Inventions,</hi> conſtantly maintained. It was by this Notion that St. <hi>Paul</hi> cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured the Worſhip of the <hi>Golden Calf</hi> as <hi>Idolatrous,</hi> and condemned the <hi>Gentile World</hi> of the ſame crime, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.21, 23. <hi>That though they knew God, yet they did not Glorify him as God, but changed the glory of the incorruptible God, into an Image made like unto Corruptible Man, and to Birds, and fourfooted Beaſts and creeping things.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This was the <hi>Notion</hi> that made our fore-runners in the <hi>Faith,</hi> chuſe rather to ſuffer <hi>Martyrdom</hi> than to give <hi>Religious worſhip</hi> to any <hi>Creature</hi> whatſoever. And whatever this <hi>Author</hi> thinks of thoſe <hi>Primitive Saints,</hi> I am conſident he will find but very few be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, that will believe they Sacrificed their Lives to their <hi>Folly and Paſſion,</hi> and died onely to defend a <hi>miſtaken Notion of Idolatry.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It was this <hi>Notion</hi> upon which the <hi>Ancient Fathers</hi> condemned the <hi>Arians</hi> of <hi>Idolatry;</hi> They did not believe <hi>Chriſt,</hi> to be either the <hi>Sun</hi> or <hi>Moon,</hi> or any <hi>other viſible</hi> or <hi>Corporeal Deity,</hi> or the <hi>Image,</hi> of the <hi>Supreme</hi> and <hi>inviſible Godhead.</hi> They believed him to be the moſt Divine and excellent <hi>Being</hi> after <hi>God,</hi> onely they denied that he was <hi>Coëternal</hi> and <hi>Coëqual with the Father;</hi> and yet thoſe <hi>Holy, Orthodox Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers</hi> cenſur'd them as <hi>Idolaters,</hi> becauſe ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing him to be a <hi>Creature</hi> they worſhiped him as a <hi>God.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="90" facs="tcp:99012:55"/>
            <p>And upon the very ſame Notion it is that the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed Churches</hi> have ever looked upon the <hi>worſhip</hi> of <hi>Images</hi> and <hi>Saints</hi> in the <hi>Church of Rome,</hi> as deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the very ſame cenſure; And I cannot but won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der that this <hi>Author</hi> ſhould charge the Invention of this <hi>Notion</hi> upon a perſon <hi>now living,</hi> which he muſt needs have known both our <hi>Church</hi> and the <hi>Writers</hi> of it have conſtantly aſſerted, before any of this <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration</hi> ever ſaw the light.</p>
            <p>I ſhould now add ſomewhat in <hi>Anſwer</hi> to thoſe <hi>bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter reflexions</hi> he has made upon the ſame <hi>Reverend Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,</hi> whom he ſeems to have reſolved at any rate to run down: But though the <hi>Charge</hi> be ſevere, yet is it ſo inartificially laid, as plainly ſhews there was no <hi>Achitophel</hi> in the Contrivance; And I will onely ſay that whoſo ſhall conſider the little Credit he had in thoſe days, to which this <hi>Author</hi> refers, with them whom himſelf looks upon as the <hi>Contrivers</hi> and <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagers</hi> of that <hi>Plot</hi> which he would be thought to lay to his <hi>Charge,</hi> will ſoon diſcover a great deal <hi>of ill will</hi> utterly <hi>ruined,</hi> for want of a little <hi>skill</hi> in the <hi>management</hi> of it.</p>
            <p>But we ought not to wonder, if he who in the beginning of his Diſcourſe flew out into ſuch violence againſt all the Abettors of this <hi>Charge</hi> as a company of <hi>Fanatick, Anti-monarchal Villains</hi> has in the <hi>Cloſe</hi> thought fit to fix ſome particular marks of his Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſuere, upon the laſt and moſt <hi>Learned Aſſertor</hi> of it. This was the leaſt he could do to make amends for the misfortune of a approving and <hi>Licenſing</hi> that <hi>very Book</hi> which was written in <hi>Defence</hi> of this <hi>Charge.</hi> And it is well for us all that there are ſome
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:99012:55"/>men in the World, who as <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lpian</hi> tells us <hi>can do no injury, Sive pulſent five concivium dicant.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>How far this <hi>Author</hi> may be reckoned in the number of theſe I ſhall leave <hi>the final reſult of his Judgement in</hi> this caſe to ſatisfie the world, <hi>viz. That Idolatry made the Plot, and the Plot made Idolatry, and the ſame perſons made both.</hi> For whether this can be the <hi>reſult</hi> of any man's <hi>Judgment</hi> that is <hi>well</hi> in his Head, I ſhall leave it to thoſe who have no Diſtempers there to determine.</p>
            <p>But <hi>he has delivered himſelf, as he will anſwer for his Integrity to God and the World.</hi> To this <hi>Judgment</hi> I now leave him: And though I fear it be too late to provide againſt the ſentence of the Laſt, yet I heartily pray he may conſider what he has done, and how he will <hi>ſtand</hi> in <hi>Judgment</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the other.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:99012:56"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Books lately Printed for</hi> Will. Rogers.</head>
            <p>THE Doctrines and Practices of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> truly Repreſented; in Anſwer to a Book intituled, <hi>A Papiſt Miſrepreſented, and Repreſented, &amp;c.</hi> Quarto.</p>
            <p>An Anſwer to a Diſcourſe intituled, <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts proteſting againſt Proteſtant Popery;</hi> being a Vindication of <hi>Papiſts</hi> not <hi>Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>repreſented</hi> by <hi>Proteſtants:</hi> And containing a particular Examination of Monſieur <hi>de Meaux,</hi> late Biſhop of <hi>Condom,</hi> his Expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition of the Doctrine of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> in the Articles of <hi>Invocation</hi> of <hi>Saints, Worſhip</hi> of <hi>Images</hi> occaſioned by that Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe. Quarto.</p>
            <p>An Anſwer to the <hi>Amicable Accommoda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> of the Differences, between the <hi>Repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenter</hi> and <hi>Anſwerer.</hi> Quarto.</p>
            <p>A View of the whole Controverſie, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the <hi>Repreſenter</hi> and the <hi>Anſwerer;</hi> with an Anſwer to the <hi>Repreſenter</hi>'s laſt <hi>Reply;</hi> in which are laid open ſome of the Methods, by which <hi>Proteſtants</hi> are <hi>Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>repreſented</hi> by <hi>Papiſts.</hi> Quarto.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:99012:56"/>
            <p>The Doctrine of the <hi>Trinity</hi> and <hi>Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſubſtantiation,</hi> compared as to <hi>Scripture, Reaſon</hi> and <hi>Tradition;</hi> in a new Dialogue between a <hi>Proteſtant</hi> and a <hi>Papiſt,</hi> the firſt Part: wherein an Anſwer is given to the late Proofs of the Antiquity of <hi>Tranſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiation,</hi> in the Books called, <hi>Conſenſus Vete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum,</hi> and <hi>Nubes Teſtium,</hi> &amp;c. Quarto.</p>
            <p>The Doctrine of the <hi>Trinity,</hi> and <hi>Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſubſtantiation,</hi> compared as to <hi>Scripture, Reaſon</hi> and <hi>Tradition</hi> in a new Dialogue between a <hi>Proteſtant</hi> and a <hi>Papiſt,</hi> the Second Part: Wherein the Doctrine of the <hi>Trinity</hi> is ſhewed to be agreeable, to <hi>Scripture</hi> and <hi>Reaſon,</hi> and <hi>Tranſubſtantiation</hi> repugnant to both. Quarto.</p>
            <p>An Anſwer to the Eighth <hi>Chapter</hi> of the <hi>Repreſenter</hi>'s Second Part, in the firſt Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logue, between him and his Lay-Friend.</p>
            <p>Of the Authority of <hi>Councils,</hi> and the Rule of <hi>Faith.</hi> By a Perſon of Quality: With an Anſwer to the Eight <hi>Theſes,</hi> laid down for the Tryal of the <hi>Engliſh Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion;</hi> in a Book that came lately from <hi>Ox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sermons and Diſcourſes, ſome of which
<pb facs="tcp:99012:57"/>never before Printed: The third Volume. By the Reverend Dr. <hi>Tillotſon,</hi> Dean of <hi>Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terbury.</hi> Octavo.</p>
            <p>A Manual for a <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Souldier, Written by <hi>Eraſmus,</hi> and Tranſlated into <hi>Engliſh.</hi> Twelves.</p>
            <p>A new and eaſie Method to learn to <hi>Sing</hi> by Book, whereby one (who hath a good Voice and Ear) may without other help, learn to <hi>Sing</hi> true by Notes. Deſign'd chiefly for, and applied to the promoting of <hi>Pſalmody;</hi> and furniſhed with Variety of <hi>Pſalm-Tunes</hi> in Parts, with Directions for that kind of <hi>Singing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Perſwaſive to frequent Communion in the <hi>Sacrament</hi> of the <hi>Lord</hi>'s <hi>Supper.</hi> By <hi>John Tillotſon,</hi> Dean of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> in Octa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vo, Price Three Pence.</p>
            <p>A Diſcourſe againſt <hi>Tranſubſtantiation.</hi> In Octavo. Price Three Pence.</p>
            <p>The State of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> when the Reformation began, as it appears by the Advices given to <hi>Paul</hi> III. and <hi>Julius</hi> III. by Creatures of their Own. With a Preface leading to the matter of the Book. Quarto.</p>
            <p>A Letter to a Friend, Reflecting on ſome
<pb facs="tcp:99012:57"/>Paſſages in a Letter to the D. of <hi>P.</hi> in An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to the Arguing Part of his firſt Letter to Mr. <hi>G.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Reflecter</hi>'s Defence of his Letter to a Friend, againſt the Furious Aſſaults of Mr. <hi>I. S.</hi> in his ſecond Catholick Letter. In four Dialogues. Quarto.</p>
            <p>A Sermon Preached at the Funeral of the Reverend <hi>Benj. Calamy,</hi> D. D. and late Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter of St. <hi>Lawrance-Jury, Lond. Jan.</hi> 7th. 1685/6. By <hi>W. Sherlock.</hi> D. D. Maſter of the <hi>Temple.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Vindication of ſome Proteſtant Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of Church-Unity and Catholick-Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion, from the Charge of Agreement with the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi> In Anſwer to a late Pamphlet, Intituled, <hi>An Agreement be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the Church of</hi> England <hi>and the Church of</hi> Rome, <hi>evinced from the Concertation of ſome of her Sons with their Brethren the Diſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters.</hi> By <hi>William Sherlock,</hi> D. D. Maſter of the <hi>Temple.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Preſervative againſt Popery: being ſome Plain Directions to unlearned Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants, how to Diſpute with <hi>Romiſh</hi> Prieſts. The firſt Part by <hi>William Sherlock,</hi> D. D. Maſter of the <hi>Temple.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
